Dieses Diagramm zeigt Pekings Feinstaubbelastung im Januar 2013
An 25 Tagen in einem Monat wurden hohe Feinstaubwerte gemessen
Zu dieser Zeit war ich in Peking
ich blickte über das Jahr zurück
versuchte mich an Geschehenes zu erinnern
aber ich konnte nicht
zu dieser Zeit sagte Jeder der Nebel
wurde hervorgerufen durch das Wetter
Niemand nahm dieses Problem ernst
In diesem Monat war ich auf vier Geschäftsreisen:
In Shaanxi, Henan, Jiangxi and Zhejiang
Erinnere ich mich an den Himmel während dieser Reisen,
erschien es als sei China in Smog getaucht
der 25 Provinzen und 600 Millionen Menschen bedeckt
Ich war mittendrin, aber merkte es nicht
nur das ungute Gefühl blieb im Hals
Als ich in Xi'an war, konnte ich wegen meines Hustens nicht schlafen
Ich legte mir deshalb eine Zitrone neben mein Kopfkissen
Zurück in Peking,
stellte ich fest, dass ich schwanger war
So sah sie aus als ich sie das erste Mal sah
In diesem Moment wusste ich, dass sie ein Mädchen ist
wegen ihres mädchenhaften Haarschnitts
Als ich das erste Mal ihr Herz schlagen hörte
wollte ich nur das es ihr gut geht
Aber
bei ihr wurde ein gutartiger Tumor diagnostiziert
was eine Operation direkt nach der Geburt notwendig machte
vor der Anästhesie sagte mir der Arzt
“Sie ist so jung, es besteht die Möglichkeit
dass sie die Narkose nicht übersteht.
Sie sollten darauf vorbereitet sein.”
Bevor ich sie in den Armen halten konnte, wurde sie zum Operationssaal gebracht.
Eine Schwester gab mir einen Plüschbären
den sie zum Trösten von Kindern benutzte
Stattdessen tröstete sie mich
Als ich meinen kleinen Engel nach der Operation sah, war sie bewusstlos.
Der Arzt sagte,
“Die Operation verlief erfolgreich.
Aber verzeihen sie mir einen Fehler:
Sie ist so dicklich, dass wir mehrere Versuche benötigten um eine Vene zu finden.”
Ich nahm ihre kleine mit Nähten übersähte Hand,
und führte sie zu meinem Gesicht
Ich sagte ihren Namen
und sie öffnete ihre Augen und sah mich an
ich war so glücklich
Ich kündigte meinen Job
um für sie da zu sein und zu sorgen
Solange wir zusammen waren, gesund und mutter, zählte nichts anderes
Aber auf dem Heimweg fühlte ich mich ängstlich
Schwarzer Rauch und der Geruch von Feuer war überall
Ich bedeckte ihre Nase mit meinem Taschentuch
Ich weiß es war dumm,
denn in ihrem Ringen nach Luft, atmete sie noch mehr Smog ein
vor diesem Tag hatte ich mir nie Gedanken darüber gemacht
und trug nie einen Atemschutz
Aber nun hat man ein kleines Leben,
was sie atmet, drinkt und isst mit zu verantworten
Das ist der Punkt an dem die Angst aufkeimt
Der stärkste Smog 2013 dauerte 2 Monate an
Der andauernde Smog sagte mir, dass es mehr als ein kurzweilige Phänomen sei
und das es nicht schnell enden würde
Es war der gleiche Himmel wie vor 10 Jahren, als ich in Shanxi war
Interview 2004
Chai: “Sieht es so jeden Tag aus?”
Boy: “Jeden Tag in jedem Jahr, sieht es so aus!
Es hält nun schon drei Jahre so an.”
“Benzopyrene sind gefährliche Krebserreger
Über die Zeit sammeln sie sich in deinem Körper
Wenn ihre Konzentration hoch genug ist, steigt die Chance an Krebs zu sterben signifikant.”
Flüsse in Shanxi: 88.4% sind verunreinigt, 62% unbenutzbar
Chai: “Denken sie das ist ein Fluss?”
Wang: “Das ist kein normales Wasser, das ist Abwasser.
Jährliche Tests haben gezeigt
dass der Benzopyrenanteil 290 mal höher als erlaubt ist.”
Stillgelegte Bergwerke: Grundwasserspiegel gefallen; Umweltkatastrophen drohen
Person: “Alle Bäume dort sind abgestorben.
Diese beiden großen Bäume sind aufgeplatzt.”
Chai: “Haben sie schonmal einen richtigen Stern gesehen?”
Wang Huiqing: “Nein, habe ich nicht.”
Chai: “Und einen blauen Himmel?”
Wang Huiqing: “Nur ein leichtes blau.”
Chai: “Und weiße Wolken?”
Wang Huiqing: “Nein, noch nie.”
Als ich dieses Mädchen 2004 interviewte,
kam mir nicht in den Sinn, dass das was sie sagte
die gleiche Erfahrung sein könnte die meine Tochter machen würde
Diese Bilder zeigen jeden Tag in Peking 2014
Nur wenn die Luftqualität gut war, konnte ich es riskieren mit meiner Tochter raus zu gehen
Aber wie viele gute Tage gab es schon?
175 wiesen eine zu hohe Verschmutzung auf
Das bedeutet die Hälfte des Jahres keine Wahl zu haben
aber sie wie eine Gefangene zu behandeln
Zehn Jahre zuvor, sagte mir der Leiter des Umweltschutzamtes,
“Xiaoyi ist ein Mikrokosmos von Shanxi; Shanxi ist ein Mikrokosmus von China.”
In nur einer Dekade,
Musste ich zusehen wie seine Worte wahr wurden
März-April 2014
46 Fotografen
Nahmen Bilder an 40 Folgetagen auf
Tianjin - 197 Tage Luftverschmutzung 2014
Shenyang - 152 Tage Luftverschmutzung 2014
Chengdu - 125 Tage Luftverschmutzung 2014
Lanzhou - 112 Tage Luftverschmutzung 2014
Shijiazhuang - 264 Tage Luftverschmutzung 2014
Ich schaute einmal die TV-Serie "Under the Dome"
Sie handelte über eine kleine Stadt die von einer Kuppel umschlossen wurde
Abgeschnitten von der Welt, ohne Auswege
Aber eines Tages realisierte ich, dass wir in dieser Kuppel leben
Manchmal wenn ich morgens aufstehe
sehe ich meine Tochter wie sie gegen das Glas unserer Balkontür klopft
das ist ihre Art zu sagen, dass sie raus will
Ich denke eines Tages wird sie mich fragen
Mama, wieso hälst du mich hier drinnen fest?
Was ist dort draußen?
Kann es mir schaden?
Alles was ich dieses Jahr tat war
mir die Fragen zu stellen die sie mich zukünftig fragen könnte
Was ist Smog?
Wo kommt er her?
Was können wir dagegen tun?
Also, was ist Smog?
Manchmal mache ich das Licht aus
ich will es sehen
ich weiß der Feinstaub ist da
luftgetragene Partikel mit einem Durchmesser von 2,5 Mikrometern
die einen Großteil des sichtbaren Lichts reflektieren,
die unsere Sicht stark einschränken
aber ich kann sie nicht sehen
weil der kleinste für das menschliche Auge sichtbare Partikel 20 Mal größer ist
mit anderen Wort ein Kampf gegen einen unsichtbaren Feind
Es gibt nur eine Möglichkeit sie zu sehen
Hier
ein Feinstaubmessgerät
Ich legte einen neuen Filter in das Gerät ein
und trug es 24 Stunden bei mir
26.November 2014 - Luftqualität: 282
So sah der Filter beim Einlegen aus, richtig?
Nach 24 Stunden
sah er so aus
Wenn ich mein Kind nicht schütze
wird sie alles ungefiltert einatmen
Wieviel wird sie einatmen?
305,91 Mikrogramm pro Kubikmeter
Aber wer versteht schon diese Zahl? Wir können sie aber vergleichen.
(Diagramm:  maximale Feinstaubkonzentration, 24-Stunden Durchschnitt)
Das ist der WHO Standard für die maximale Feinstaubbelastung pro Tag
Standard in den USA
Standard in Europa
und das ist der Standard in China
Wieviel haben wir an diesem Tag eingeatmet?
5 mal mehr als das erlaubte Maximum in China
Das mag wie eine vereinzelte alarmierende Zahl klingen
Ich wollte wissen welche Stoffe sich in dieser Probe befanden
Prof. Qiu Xinhua von der Peking Universität war so freundlich
diesen Test für mich durchzuführen
Hier sind die Ergebnisse der Analyse:
es wurden 15 Krebserreger gefunden
inklusive Benzopyrene, einer der weltweit stärksten Krebserreger
Um das wievielfache wurde der Standard überschritten?
ich konnte diese Zahl nicht glauben
Könnt ihr euch erinnern, als ich in Xiaoyi stand,
umgeben von Kohlekraftwerken?
Die Menge an Benzopyrenen die ich dort einatmete
waren nur 9 mal über dem Standard
Heute lebe ich im Zentrum einer internationalen Metropole
Im Umkreis befinden sich keine Fabriken oder Schlote
Wie kann der Wert also 14fach über dem erlaubten Maximum liegen?
Professor Qiu zweifelte die Ergebnisse ebenfalls an
Er sagte "Es scheint unmöglich das es so hoch ist. Ich werde den Versuch erneut durchführen."
Am Folgetag rief er mich an und erklärte
"Es gab keinen Fehler; es ist 14fach über dem Maximum."
“Ein breiterer Test ergab
das manche Menschen einer noch größeren Belastung ausgesetzt waren - 20fach über dem legalen Maximum.”
Alle Krebserreger hafteten am Filter den ich ihnen zuvor zeigte
verbunden mit Rußpartikeln
Er ist klein, nur 0,2 Mikrometer
Aber er hat eine Kettenstruktur, wird er aufgedröselt
können 2 Gramm einen Basketball-Platz bedecken
deshalb kann Ruß Krebserreger und Schwermetall-Partikel absorbieren
Wieviel Ruß gibt es in China?
Dies sind Schätzungen der NASA aus dem Jahr 2009
Dieser helle violette und weiße Fleck ist China
Er schwebt über uns wie ein Geist
Also besuchte ich die Peking Universität
Ich wusste das es ein Labor für derartige Experimente gab
Ich meldete mich bei einem Experten als Freiwillige
“Schließen sie mich in eine Testkammer mit einer hohen Rußkonzentration
überwachen und testen sie meine Körperfunktionen,
damit ich die Ergebnisse veröffentlichen kann.”
Er zögerte eine Weile und antwortete
“Es tut mir Leid ich kann dieses Experiment nicht durchführen.”
Ich fragte warum.
Er sagte, “Jedes Experiment setzt akademisch-ethische Maßstäbe voraus.
Diese Maßstäbe sollen Teilnehmer vor Schaden schützen.
Ich kann kein Experiment unter diesen Maßstäben durchführen
Auch wenn die Konzentration draußen höher wäre als in der Testkammer."
“Um es anders zu sagen, jeder von uns
lebt Zeit seines Lebens in einer Testkammer
und wir wissen nicht was das Ergebnis dieses Experiments sein könnte."
Die Peking Universität bediente sich einer anderen Herangehensweise
Sie hielten fest wie Menschen auf verschmutzte Luft reagierten
Für ein Jahr wohnte ich diesem Experiment bei
Das ist das Ergebnis:
Ich habe chronische Atemwegsbeschwerden und gehöre zu einer Risikogruppe
Feine Partikel wirken sich auf die Atemwege aus, reizen und erschweren die Atmung
und wirken sich auf das Herz-Kreislauf-System aus
Kleine Partikel korrelieren mit einer höheren Wahrscheinlichkeit eines Herzinfarkts und reduzieren den Blutdruck
Ich verstehe zwar keine medizinischen Fachbegriffe
aber mit der Hilfe von Wissenschaftlern
erstellten wir diese Animation um den Effekt zu erklären
Ich bin Feinstaub
ich habe viele Brüder und Schwestern
polyzyklische aromatische Kohlenwasserstoffe und andere Schwermetall-Partikel
alles geduldete Waffen
im Kriegsspiel gegen den menschlichen Körper
vermisse ich selten
Szene 1: Nasenloch
Nasenhaare und Schleim können große Partikel blockieren
90% aller Partikel sind größer als 10 Mikrometer und werden abgetötet
aber sie können mich nicht aufhalten
Szene 2: Hals
im oberen Atemwegstrakt befinden sich 10 Mikrometer kurze Härchen
sie bewegen sich 20 mal in einer Sekunde, aber ich komme leicht an ihnen vorbei
die weichen Muskeln der Luftröhre werden gereizt, kontraktieren und
versuchen mich zu blockieren, aber sie können mich nicht stoppen
Szene 3: Unterer Atemwegstrakt
Hier die Ausläufer der Bronchien die wie ein Baum in die kleineren Bronchiolen münden
das sind die besten Skipisten für uns
wir kämpfen gegen Leukozyten und Lymphozyten
diese Kämpfe führen zu vielerlei Entzündungen im menschlichen Körper
Unsere Truppen erreichen schließlich ihr Ziel:
die Astspitzen, die Lungenbläschen
die menschliche Lunge hat mehr als 300 Millionen Lungenbläschen
Wenn wir die Lungenbläschen blockieren, kann der Mensch nicht mehr atmen
Wie auch immer, unser größter Feind ist hier: die Makrophagen
ihre Spezialität ist es Fremdstoffe aufzunehmen
und sind bekannt als die körpereigenen Straßenkehrer
Das wird ein harter Kampf.
Wie auch immer wir sind zahlenmäßig überlegen
unser Kern ist schwer zu teilen, und wir enthalten giftige Schwermetalle
Makrophagen können nicht alle von uns neutralisieren
und können leicht durch übermäßigen Konsum absterben
So wird das menschliche Immunsystem geschwächt
Wir haben eine andere Spezialeinheit:
Partikel kleiner als 0,5 Mikrometer
Einmal im Lungenbläschen, sind sie klein genug um in Blutgefäße zu gelangen
beschädigen die Blutgefäße und verengen die Arterien
was zu hohem Blutdruck und Thrombose führt
Wir können auch den Kern des menschlichen Körpers erreichen
über den Lungenkreislauf
und dein Herz angreifen
verursachen Durchblutungsnot und Herzrhythmusstörungen
was zu Herzinfarkten führt
Fürchtet uns, Menschen.
Wir sind in jedem eurer Atemzüge.
Diese Informationen wurden von der Chinesischen Akademie der Wissenschaften zur Verfügung gestellt.
Diese Darstellungen demonstrieren
das wenn die Feinstaubkonzentration ansteigt,
die menschliche Sterberate ebenfalls ansteigt
Andere wissenschaftliche Forschungseinrichtungen haben den selben Trend beobachtet
Der frühere chinesische Gesundheitsminister Chen Zhu
hat errechnet das die Zahl der Tode von Frühgeborenen hervorgerufen
durch die Luftverschmutzung in China jedes Jahr
500.000 beträgt
In diesem Kampf gegen Menschen,
sind unsere Kinder und Eltern
am verwundbarsten.
Diese Babies sind 2 Monate alt.
Sie waren noch nie draußen
haben aber eine Lungenentzündung.
Hier werden Sie mit Zerstäubern therapiert.
Die Eltern baten mich, ihre Kinder zu fotografieren
Sie vermuteten, ihr Kind sei durch schlechten Schutz bei starkem Smog krank geworden.
Der Arzt sagte ihnen:
“Ich kann nur eine Diagnose auf 'Lungenentzündung aus unbekanntem Grund' geben."
denn es gibt nicht genug aktuelle epidemiologische Studien.
Aber ich kann ihnen die Statistiken sagen:
Während des landesweiten Smog im Januar 2013
zeigten 27 Städte einen exponentiellen Anstieg
von Krankenhausbesuchen.
Die Mütter in meiner Gegen sprachen einmal darüber.
Eine Mutter fragte mich:
“Wie sollen wir mit dem Smog umgehen?
Sollen wir unsere Kinder so früh wie möglich
dem Smog aussetzen, um sie zu trainieren, so dass sie sich anpassen
und nicht von Anfang an benachteiligt sind?"
Ein Medizinexperte aus Los Angeles,
eine Stadt, die unter extremer Luftverschmutzung litt, informierte uns
über die Risiken, unsere Kinder der Luftverschmutzung auszusetzen
in der Hoffnung, sie könnten sich den Bedingungen anpassen:
Mir sind keine Informationen bekannt
die bestätigen, ein Kinder der Luftverschmutzung auszusetzen
würde ihnen helfen sich anzupassen.
Setzen wir sie dem den ersten Tag aus, verlieren sie etwas Funktion.
Setzen wir sie dem an Tag zwei aus, verlieren sie nicht die selbe Menge.
Aber das liegt nicht daran, dass sie sich angepasst haben,
sondern weil die Funktion bereits verloren wurde.
Sie wurden bereits verletzt.
Viele Studien weltweit zeigen,
dass Kinder in sauberen Orten schneller wachsen
als Kinder in verschmutzteren Gegenden.
Frühe, schlechte Lungenfunktion
ist ein Vorbote für Lundenprobleme im Alter.
Tun wir also etwas für die Luft, während ein Kind wächst,
können wir das Leben dieses Kindes ändern.
Das ist der Platz vor meinem Haus.
Das Foto habe ich 2 Tage zuvor bei schwerem Smog gemacht.
Der AQI (Air Quality Index) lag über 500,
über dem “gefährlichen” Smog-Level
Doch die Kinder der angrenzenden Schule
spielten immer noch Ball und rannten herum.
Wenn Leute Sport treiben
atmen sie fünf mal öfter und viel tiefer als sonst.
Als ich das sah, wurde ich der Tatsache bewusst,
dass ich mein Kind nicht beschützen kann.
Eines Tages wird sie in die Gesellschaft gehen
Sie wird immer atmen,
das lässt sich nicht verhindern.
Es (PM2.5) ist in jedem Atemzug.
Ein Erwachsener wie wir atmet 25000 mal am Tag ein.
Wenn es sich über die Zeit addiert ... was machen diese Substanzen in unseren Lungen?
Wir bedanken uns bei einer Patientin und einem Doktor,
im Beijing Krebs-Krankenhaus, die zustimmten diese Operation zu filmen.
Diese Patientin hat Lungenkrebs im Anfangsstadium.
Weiblich, in den Fünfzigern.
Sie arbeitet in der Buchhaltung des Krankenhauses.
Sie und ihre Familie haben nie geraucht.
Dieser Ausschnitt wurde mit Zustimmung der Familie der Patientin und dem Krankenhaus gefilmt.
Die folgenden Szenen können Unbehagen bei Zuschauern hervorrufen.
In den Hohlräumen der Lunge
Jeder atmet diese schwarzen Partikel ein.
Auch wir.
Raucht diese Person?
Nein, sie ist Nichtraucher.
Aber sie ist aus (zensierter Stadtname)
Aus deiner Heimatstadt.
Die Luft-Qualität ist wirklich schlecht.
Genau, es ist (dort) nicht sauber.
Das (könnte) also der Schmutz aus der Luft sein.
Ein Lungen-Lümpfknoten - Kohlenstoff-Partikel haben ihn komplett schwarz gefärbt.
In ihrem gesamten Körper sind nur die Lympfknoten der Lunge schwarz.
Weil sie eine Menge Staub eingeatmet hat.
Das Lympfsystem ist essentiell für die Funktion des Immunsystems
Yang Yue, Leiter des Peking University Krebskrankhauses, zweite Thorax Abteilung
Das bedeutet, das Lympfsystem hilft dem Immunsystem gegen Krankheiten.
Sammelt sich dieses schwarze Zeug darauf
beeinflusst das die Fähigkeit des Körpers sich gegen Krebszellen zu wehren?
Es ist möglich, dass es das Lympfsystem überfordert.
Darum berichtete die Weltgesundheitsorganisation (WHO),
dass chronische Kungenleiden
das höchste Risiko für Lungenkrebs darstellen.
Wir können beruhigt sein,
dass diese Art Operation sehr erfolgreich ist
und der Patient völlig genest
nachdem der Tumor entfernt wurde.
Nach der Entfernung der schwarzen Lympfknoten
zeigte der Doktor sie der Familie.
Sie fragten: "Können Sie mir sagen, warum meine Frau Krebs hat?"
Er sagte, “Ich kann nur sagen, dass, durch meine medizinische Erfahrung,
mein Verdacht die Luftverschmutzung ist.
(Da Feinstaub in der Luft zunimmt und die Verschmutzung schlimmer wird, wird auch das Risiko für Lungenkrebs höher.  Feinstaub ist als Haupt-Krebserreger für Menschen klassifiziert.)
Als er mir das sagte, hatte ich eine Frage
Hat Lungenkrebs nicht eine Inkubationszeit
von mindestens 10 Jahren oder so?
Aber von der Verschmutzung haben wir vor zwei Jahren zu hören begonnen, richtig?
Wie konnte es also so schnell zu Lungenkrebs führen?
Darum bin ich für einen kleinen Gefallen zur NASA gegangen.
Ich fragt, ob sie mir Satellitenfotos senden könnten
von Nord China aus den vergangenen 10 Jahren
Das ist, was ich erhielt
Die Luft über Peking
Peking im Dezember
Die Luft über Nord-China
Schauen wir 10 Jahre zurück
Nord-China 2005
Aber ich konnte es nicht glauben.
Ich lebte unter diesem Himmer in Nord-China zu dieser Zeit.
Wie konnte ich diesen Smog 10 Jahre nicht bemerken?
Also habe ich unsere Landes-Behörde für die Luftqualität während der Olympischen Spiele aufgesucht.
Einen Akademiker namens Dr. Tang Xiaoyan
Sie gab mir diesen Graph
Das ist 2004
vor 11 Jahren
Damals hatten wir PM2.5 noch nicht zu messen begonnen.
Doch wir hatten die Werte für PM10
Sie sagte, auf Basis damaliger Schätzungen
konnten zu einer Zeit
in der die Luft sehr verschmutzt war
PM2.5-Wert von 300-400 gegeben haben.
Heute würden wir das als ungesunde Luftverschmutzung nennen.
Ich fragte sie
Konnte ich wirklich so blind sein?
Ich war 2004 in Peking.
Sie sagte: "Schau dieses Foto an.
Was ist das?"
Ich sagte: "Das ist wahrscheinlich Smog, richtig?"
Wie kam es also, dass ich das damals nicht wusste?
Sie sagte, ich solle nachschlagen
was die Zeitungen an diesem Tag berichteten.
“Der Flughafen von Peking hat wegen Nebel die meisten Verspätungen der letzten Jahre.” - 2. Dezember, 2004, Sina News
Damals dachten wir, es wäre nur Nebel.
Wir nannten es weiterhin "Nebel".
Nachdem ich dieses Bild sah,
als ehemaliger Reporter
war ich woller Gewissensbisse
denn all die ganzen Jahre habe ich gedacht
ich würde über die Luftverschmutzung des Landes berichten.
Aber ich dachte immer
es wird nur "Luftverschmutzung" genannt, wenn man Explosionen in Minen hört
er wird nur "Luftverschmutzung" genannt, wenn man Rauch aus Schornsteinen sieht.
Ich dachte nie, dass es die unter uns, die in Metropolen lebten, betraf.
Die Luft, die wir jeden Tag sahen
war auch verschmutzt.
Als ich keine Reporterin mehr war
war ich bereits zum Zuschauer geworden.
Aber ich hatte immernoch eine Frage
Wenn es wirklich so war,
als ich jung war hatte jede Familie
einen Kerosinofen, richtig?
Jede Nacht wachten wir auf
durch den Geruch des Rauchs
Wie kommt es, dass ich damals nie von Leuten gehört hatte, die Lungenkrebs bekamen?
Ich habe diese Frage immer wieder gestellt
Bis ich Professor He Xingzhou traf,
der diese Thema seit 30 Jahren untersucht.
Er gab mir ein Buch Daten
Dieses.
Eine Untersuchung der Beziehung zwischen Luftverschmutzung und Todesursachen in 26 chinesischen Städten von 1976-1981
Dadurch ist klar ersichtlich
Die Zusammenfassung ist auf dem Beamer zu sehen.
Es ist ganz einfach
Die Luftversmutzung damals
korrelierte bereits mit der Todesrate durch Lungenkrebs
Die Luftverschmutzung damals entstand durch die Verbrennung von Kohle.
Es war tatsächlich so, dass diese Daten
als "interne Information" betrachtet wurden.
Es ist nicht so, dass die Leute damals
den erdrückenden Rauch nicht riechen konnten.
Aber die Wärme und Energie, die Kohle brachte,
war damals wichtiger.
In den 80ern
gab es 3700 Fabriken in Peking.
Für ein Land der Agrarkultur, nach Entwicklung strebend,
waren Schornsteine ein Zeichen des Fortschritts.
For some people, they are just two smokestacks
For some people, they are reference points to direct you home
We had absolutely no experience or consciousness of pollution
Nor the ability to control it
Major pollutants did not have any set standards
Even though the amount of coal burned was nowhere near the amount we burn today
The pollution discharged was enormous
In terms of PM2.5 levels
In 2006, the average concentration of PM2.5 was higher than it is today
It was this year that China proposed saving energy and reducing emissions
And setting standards for sulphur dioxide and other major pollutants
Afterwards, air pollution started to decrease
But the amount of fine particles affecting visibility increased
The amount of days with extremely high pollution increased
People started feeling strongly about pollution
Economic development has increased life expectancy in China
And has brought more ways to recover from illness
But the risks that come from air pollution have become obvious
In the past 30 years,
the death rate from lung cancer in China has increased by 465%
Even though smoking and an ageing society
Are major factors in this statistic
The clear risk of developing lung cancer that comes from fine particulate matter
Is receiving increased attention
Monitoring of PM2.5 levels started in 2012 and
China implemented its “Air Pollution Prevention Plan”
As wages increased and information became more transparent
People’s expectations on the environment rose as well
A person
Or not even a person
How should a living organism live?
When spring arrives, you open your doors
the wind blows in
The smell of flowers fills the air
and colors come back to life
Sometimes when it rains
or when it’s foggy out
You can’t help but breathe the air deep into your lungs
and experience the feeling of small water droplets filling them up
Both piercingly cold but also pure and fresh
In autumn
you would spend a whole afternoon
with a loved one doing absolutely nothing
basking lazily in the sun
In the Winter
you would go outside with your kids
when it’s snowing
and she sticks out her tongue and to catch the snowflakes
You would teach her
about nature and the beauty of life
But now...
This year, every day when I wake up
the first thing I do is
check the air quality on my phone
Because it will determine my whole day
I rely on a wind from the North West to live my life
I wear a mask when I go for a walk
I wear a mask when I go shopping
I wear a mask when I go to see my friends
I use tape to cover up
every crack of the windows and doors in my house
When I took my daughter to get vaccinated
I was afraid even when she smiled at me
Actually, I not really afraid of death
I just don’t want to live like this
So whenever someone asks me
what are you doing this for?
I can only tell them
This is a battle
between me and air pollution
Where does air pollution come from?
I want to know where it comes from
I want to understand what is really going on
I examined a strip of sampling film
under a scientist's microscope
and I saw what it looked like
Pollution was not the collection of identical particles
that I imagined it to be
It is a mixture of all sorts of things
and being a mixture makes it more poisonous
as well as allowing it to spread more rapidly
Pollutants can chemically react with each other
The Chinese Academy of Sciences explained the pollution sources to me
burning coal, burning oil, burning organic materials
industry, farming, chemical fertilizers, dust emission
Most of these causes are anthropogenic in nature
If you analyze these factors
you will find where most of pollution comes from
This is the conclusion
60% of the PM2.5 in China comes from
burning coal and oil
That is to say, the burning of fossil fuels
PM2.5 has existed
long before humans
Volcanic eruptions
and forest fires would emit large amounts of fine particulate matter
Starting from when we discovered how to make fire from wood
human activities have contributed to PM2.5
In the past, the use of coal in large quantities
led to serious pollution
in England and Germany
and when we entered the age of oil,
burning oil led to serious pollution in America and Japan
At this moment there are still many
developing countries in the process of industrializing
India
Iran
Pakistan
Afghanistan
All face problems with pollution from burning fossil fuels
as does China, the country
that has developed fastest in the world
It's large size
has led to burning large amounts of both types of fossil fuels
How much fuel are we actually burning?
We can see in 2014
This figure represents
the quantities of fossil fuel being burned around the world
You can see how bright China is
That bright white and red area,
that’s our country
From the image we can see
China burns from 3-4 times more fossil fuel than Europe
We have burned so much fossil fuel
But the thing that surprised me most was
that the pollutants from coal and oil can have
large-scale chemical reactions
Wang Yuesi, Du Jiming and Tang Xiaoyan
We haven't yet dealt with coal pollution
and now vehicle pollution has been added to the mix
The pollution in China right now
is basically an overlap of these two types of pollution
All kinds of particles
react with each other in the air
Air movement has decreased
but the same quantity of pollutants remains
The unfortunate thing is that
these pollutants haven’t spread out
but are instead reacting with each other
this is what we call secondary particles
Complex pollutants
absorb
adhere
collide
merge
They all mix together
There’s no way for us to change natural conditions
we can only change ourselves
and the way to do that
is to reduce emissions
The whole world needs to burn coal and oil, right?
So what’s wrong with our coal?
Do you know how much coal China has burned?
In 2013
we had already burned 3.6 billion tons
But do you know how much
all the other countries in the world have burned?
We have burned more coal
than the rest of the world combined
The last time a country had this kind of consumption
was England in 1860
But as a result
they paid a heavy price
Deep in an abandoned mine in South Wales
lies the heart of England's industrial age
It used to drive
the most powerful empire in the world
But as a result it also brought this country
a frightening black disaster
These 4 smokestacks are 103 meters tall
They are the symbols of the industrial age in England
When the Battersea Power Station was completed in 1930
it would burn approximately 10,000 tons of coal per week
to supply one fifth of the electricity for the entire city of London
You could say that London was eating coal to survive
trains, boats,
iron, steel, everyday items
In all of London, it was like
millions of micro-volcanoes were all erupting at once
Since they were burning large quantities of poor quality coal
and emitting pollution at low elevations
the amount of pollution from family chimneys
was double the amount of pollution from industry
Slowly with time
London became completely covered in soot
People wore face masks to go to school
Wore face masks to go shopping
Wore facemasks to walk their dogs
Wore face masks to kiss
The day of the disaster
was December 5, 1952
a cold front stretched across the English Channel
and covered the entire river valley of the Thames River
This kept the smog under the clouds,
preventing it from dissipating
Poison smoke has closed down
Residents have difficulty in breathing the murky air
People walking down the street couldn’t even see their own feet
You needed a blind person to lead you home
Traffic police used large lamps to light themselves up
so they wouldn’t get hit by cars
All of London was completely silent
You could only see ambulances, because they had to bring
those whose lives were in danger to the hospital
But when they were on the road they had to rely on
people holding torches to show them the way
In the end 12,000 people died in the smog
The lungs of the dead were sampled
and close examination confirmed that they died due to
prolonged exposure to black carbon, a by-product of burning coal
and a short-term overexposure to a high concentration of
fine particulate matter containing heavy metals
The Coalition for Clean Air calculated that
the concentration of pollution in London at the time
might have surpassed the current pollution in China by a large margin
Even though PM2.5 was not measured at the time
But during the Great Smog
the concentration of sulfur dioxide
was 190 times the WHO standard
and exceeded China's PM2.5 standard
by an order of magnitude
In the 1960s, after the Great Smog in London,
other countries began to reduce and control their use of coal
But that was also the time when China started its economic reform
A country that had been closed and left behind for so many years
desperately needed massive amounts of energy to develop
And it chose to get that energy from coal
This curve shows coal's growth as an energy source
India is also on a similar path
In near future, India will be the world's second largest consumer of coal
But as of today, India has not yet set standards
for emissions of important pollutants in its industries
India is also a country suffering from severe air pollution
So where does all this coal end up being used in China?
Let's take a look at the 3.6 billion tons of coal consumed in 2013
380 million tons was burnt in Beijing, Tianjin and Hebei
Of that 380 million tons, 300 million tons
was burnt in Hebei
I was really surprised because
I always thought it was us Shanxi people who burnt the most coal
When did Hebei start burning so much coal?
Dr. Hao Jiming from Tsinghua University asked me
Have you seen the world coal and steel production rankings?
He said that China is in first place
Hebei is second
Tangshan is third
US is fourth (laughter)
He also added that originally
Tangshan lied in order to be fifth (laughter)
Does more coal use and industrialization necessarily mean more pollution?
Other countries also produce steel
He said
you will understand what I mean if you go to Tangshan
So, last October
together with the MEP North China Supervision Centre
we went to Tangshan equipped with drones
to take a look at the actual conditions
Zhang Dawei - MEP Bureau of Environmental Supervision
Can you see that smoke over there?
It’s not that clear because of the big smoke
Visual inspection of emissions from the factory was impossible
The weather now makes it difficult to see clearly
Drone inspection failed due to intense smog
Have a look behind to see if anyone is following us
The MEP paid an unannounced visit to the factory
This choking smell of sulfur dioxide must be the smoke
We can now see that
a lot of smoke is leaking around the edges
This smoke
is being emitted without any controls
and released into the atmosphere
Why aren't you using the dust filters?
We are using them
Then why is there so much smoke?
They are operating, see it's being sucked up
Oh my god, have a look underneath
I'm going down to see
This has to be the most dangerous thing I've done in my career, my life
Oh my god, it's too terrifying
Stop, stop, stop
Someone fell
The person who fell was Inspector Zhang Dawei
from the MEP North China Bureau of Environmental Supervision
We were all scared at the time
because there weren't any lights or warning signs in the factory
There was a pit about 3 meters deep filled with steel and cement
Dawei wanted to go down and check for emissions from this place
and he fell in
Fortunately he wasn't injured seriously
so we took him to the hospital and then back to Beijing that night
But what surprised me most was we put in so much effort,
had so much trouble, and despite finding clear evidence of pollution
in the end, this company was not penalized in any way
I asked Dawei why
He said, “You should ask my boss”
Xiong Yuehui - MEP Department of Science, Technology and Standards
Over 60% of steel firms
have not completed the approval process
They did not bother to consult environmental protection law
but only tried to stop the approval process
They stopped the approval process whether production is legal or not
They know there is no chance, so they act with utter recklessness
Their operations are completely unlicensed
The inspectors don't even want to go or touch this industry in any way
Can you really shut them down?
Can you really stop them?
Why can't we shut them down?
You must be kidding
How many jobs do you create when you produce ten million tons of steel?
One hundred thousand jobs
How important is the steel industry in Hebei?
It's so important that you can’t simply shut them down
This province has a huge amount of heavy industry scattered throughout it,
consuming large quantities of coal,
without effective pollution controls
and the industries can not be forced to shut down
What are the consequences of this?
I have a good friend, Hao
who was also colleague of mine on News Investigation
She was the one who went with me ten years ago
to Shanxi to report on the local pollution
She knew I was from Linfen (in Shanxi) and
sometimes she would jokingly send me pictures
She would say, “I heard your hometown is now
the most polluted city on the planet.”
I was speechless
But after 10 years I sent this picture to her
Let’s take a closer look
Celebrating the fact that our city's air
is no longer the most polluted of 74 cities in China (laughter)
This was a real banner in Hebei
Unfortunately, this city was once again the most polluted city on the list (3 months later)
But this kind of joke really makes me sad
And for people living in Beijing
every time the wind blows from the south
the pollution from Hebei moves towards us like this
You can't keep the air out with a wall
So this what they mean when they say
“Breath together and live together”
I have another friend, called Fan
She is from Jiangsu
I used to argue with Hao
about which province is more polluted, Hebei or Shanxi
Fan used to say, offhand
“Well, we southerners don't really have any pollution”
Now Eastern China also experiences severe pollution
But Fan was quite surprised
She said, “It’s impossible,
at least Eastern China’s pollution can't have anything to do with coal
because I’ve never seen coal in my whole life”
Right
I showed her this image
These are the iron and steel factories near your house
These are power plants near your house
These are cement factories near your house
In Jiangsu there’s one power plant for every 30 square kilometers
And what is the current state of emissions from these companies?
Here we can see their emissions in real time
The red spots indicate emissions exceeding the standards
As we zoom in,
you can see how many firms in the east
are emitting pollutants in excess of the limits
Among them, Shanghai
which burns a lot of coal itself,
is burning the largest quantity of coal per unit of area
of all the metropolitan cities
10 kilograms of coal are burned
for every square meter of land
What are the consequences of burning more coal?
One problem I never thought about
is that high quality coal will become increasingly scarce
Right?
So what should we do?
So lower quality coal will become more common
How low can the quality be?
This is common coal
What about this, is this coal too?
At first I did not think this was coal
this must be wood,
you can still see the texture and fossils on top
But people from coal washing factories told me that
this is really coal
It's called lignite, or brown coal
It’s the youngest coal in the world
It’s so young that the level of coalification is extremely low
When it is burnt, half of it
will turn to black smog, floating in the air
How much brown coal have we used?
This is a graph of brown coal production in recent years
And these are the consequences
On October 21, 2013
on the first day the district heating was turned on in Harbin
There was so much smog that
that PM2.5 index exceeded 1000
This was how Harbin people spent that day
I talked with people from Harbin’s environmental protection bureau
and mentioned that I heard buses got lost over those two days
He smiled bitterly and said
Never mind the buses, even our own bureau director got lost (laughter)
He said when he was inspecting sites on that day
nobody recognized him because of the smog
The smog in Harbin
was caused by burning
over 20 million tons of brown coal
Plus, in 2013, several hundred thousand coal burning boilers like these across China
did not comply with any environmental standard
and were not regulated at all
The coal was burned
and pollutants were emitted
and released into the atmosphere
When you look down from above
it was as if 12 million people were
buried under cement
Coal itself does not mean pollution
Germany also uses brown coal
But in Germany they first clean and wash the brown coal to improve its quality
Coal can be cleaned
The British wash 95% of their coal
And what about China?
We wash less than half of our coal
The other half, nearly several hundred million tons of coal
contained the practically useless and highly polluting and inefficient
material called ash
But we transport it with trains, with trucks
around the world and burn it in cooking stoves
Completely useless
The result is
that most of the brown coal is burnt in people's homes
Even in urban areas in China,
one quarter of people burn brown coal
They don't burn a lot of coal
only 20 percent of the country's total
but the sulfur dioxide emitted from this burning
is equivalent to the emissions from all the power plants together
That's how much of a difference washing coal can make
The most terrifying thing is, it’s highly toxic
In Beijing, the toxicity of PM2.5 during winter
is far greater than it in summer
The carcinogen content in winter
is 25 times higher than in summer
Why is PM2.5 so toxic in winter?
Mostly because people are burning scrap coal
This type of coal emits an extremely large quantity of carcinogens
For many years Chinese people
have been suffering from the consequences of burning scrap coal
In Xuanwei (Yunnan) there’s a town called Hutou
Burning scrap coal means it now has
one of the highest incidence rates of lung cancer in the world
This person is in the late stages of lung cancer
He was coughing up blood
He was too weak to brush away the mosquitoes
so he asked someone to put flypaper on his body
This old man was photographed with all the people close to him
whose lives were taken by lung cancer over these years
There are even entire families that have been wiped out
We always hear that that China is still a developing country,
and that environmental protection is a luxury we cannot afford
But it’s often the poorest people
who suffer the most from pollution
They are the most likely to be hurt
They are the ones whose voices need most to be heard
They need help the most
These past few years, our coal consumption has been extremely high
As a result, the quality of the coal we use has decreased
We also don't wash our coal
and there are almost no controls on emissions
This is the result
The places in China
with the most coal consumption
also have the highest concentrations of PM2.5
I mean, the easiest way to clean up the environment
is to lower our consumption of coal to below 2 billion tons
This will guarantee blue skies
If we can’t reach this goal,
we can try to centralize the burning of coal
and replace scrap coal burning with use in coal power plants instead
As a next step,
if we still can’t accomplish this,
we can try to wash the scrap coal we use
If all the scrap coal is washed, how would that affect emissions?
It would halve our emissions at the very least
We can make two changes at present
First, we must reduce consumption of coal
or we can wash our coal
Article 23 Atmospheric Protection Law
The government promotes washing and upgrading coal
Reduction of the sulfur and ash content in coal
Restrictions on extracting coal with high sulfur and ash content
Article 1 of the Ten atmosphere protection articles
Overhaul small-scale coal burners
Accelerating de-sulfurization and reducing nitrogen compounds and ash
In 2014, PM2.5 has been reduced 11.1% from its original level in 74 cities
but only 8 cities met the standards set by the government
If we could effectively carry out all of the current environmental protection measures
Just the ones we already have right now, have them 100% enforced,
our ash emission and sulfur dioxide emission
would be 60% lower than current levels,
our nitrogen oxide emission would be 35% lower
In order to solve the environmental problem in China
first, we need to have better management
Second, we still need better management
Third, is still better management
President Xi Jinping said
“The dignity of the law depends on its enforcement.”
China took only 30 years
to complete an industrialization process
that took a hundred years in other countries
Therefore, on top of the pollution from coal
we have to account for
the pollution from oil as well
So what happens to our oil?
Most of our oil is burnt by vehicles
In ten years, the number of vehicles in China
has increased by about 100 million
Looking specifically at Beijing in 2010
how many cars were added in that one year?
800,000 more
What does 800,000 cars mean?
If all these cars were placed end-to-end, they would stretch from Beijing to Shenzhen
and then back to Beijing
That's one year's increase
The result is as follows
The primary source of PM2.5 within Beijing
is these vehicles
But there is another city that surprised me
This city is under haze for over 200 days per year
You can guess which city that is
Which one?
Let's try another picture
Qinghai you say?
Qingdao?
Hangzhou
To be honest I am as shocked as you are
because I always thought
These were the scenes of misty rain described in all those famous poems.
Later I made a call to the Hangzhou MEP
and they confirmed this
Because the rate of vehicle ownership per capita in Hangzhou
is the highest among all cities in China
On average, there is one car for every two people.
So the vehicles of Hangzhou
contribute nearly 40% of its air pollution
Do more cars necessarily mean more pollution?
Here’s a question we often hear
Aren’t there more cars in Tokyo than in Beijing?
Why don’t we see such severe pollution in Tokyo?
This is the explanation given by the Beijing Municipal Commission of Transport:
More than 90% of Tokyo's residents commute by rail
Less than 6% of them drive
What about in Beijing?
34% of Beijing residents drive cars
And they drive in the city center, usually stuck in traffic jams
When they are stuck their cars are idling
which doubles the rate of emissions
And when they brake, even more heavy metals are released
So every day during rush hour in Beijing
how much PM2.5 is emitted in one hour
within the 6th ring?
One ton
How many Beijing residents would choose to drive
if they are going somewhere within 5km?
Close to half
12% of all residents
would drive within 2km
And 7%
would drive within 1km
How far is 1km?
That’s a trip to the supermarket
or greengrocer's
Do we really love driving so much?
Perhaps a few of us do
But there can’t be so many irrational people, right?
My family owns a car, but after our child was born we made a rule
basically we would only drive for our parents, our kid
or when we go to the airport or hospital
When my husband goes to work every day, he rides a bicycle
This is how you ride a bicycle
in front of our apartment building
That’s the only way to ride
Why?
This is our bicycle lane
It’s almost always full of cars
Beijing has over 5 million vehicles
but only half of them have a parking space
But no car can park in the air
so you find them in bicycle lanes
and on sidewalks
That’s how they park
Of course, humanity is the same throughout the world
Without regulations, this can happen anywhere
Let’s check London
It seems they also parked like this in the old days
then the parking meters were installed
and they parked like this
Then London raised its parking fee and congestion charge
so they parked like this
A few days ago, I heard that people are trying the same thing in Shenzhen
they started to charge high parking fees
Then the folks in Shenzhen parked like this (laughter)
The same thing happened in Tokyo 50 years ago
It’s not that easy
It took them a long time
to clear the cars out of the way one by one
This is a test of meticulous city management.
Car-lovers have another question
As this photo shows
there are no vehicles in Beijing at midnight, are there?
Why is the pollution still so severe?
Is it really caused by cars?
This question also troubled me for a long time
Until the Chinese Academy of Sciences showed me this chart
Before every dawn in Beijing
There’s always a peak in pollution
It shows up consistently every day
At this peak, carbon emissions are about twice as high
as the peak in the afternoon on the same day
So what exactly is this?
I wanted to know the answer as well
So we went to Yanqing district of Beijing
Yanqing - Kangzhuang Toll Station, 2:30am 11 October 2014
Inspector: Halt!
Vehicle type: Futian Aoling
Displayed emissions standard: National Standard 4
This truck doesn't have the basic equipment for a Standard 4
Chai: So in fact it's not a Standard 4 vehicle
Driver: So what should I do?
Driver: I just bought this new truck
This is my environmental protection label
It was issued this year
Random inspection of another vehicle
Vehicle type: Chang'an Kaima
Displayed emissions standard: National Standard 3
What does 3.29 mean?
It’s above the limit
This is even beyond Standard 1
So it has no emission control device at all?
No, basically no emission control at all
He has the green label
It says Standard 3
Who issued it?
Hebei Province Department of Environmental Protection
When I bought it they said it was Standard 3
How could I know? I was just buying a truck
Finally, the car was not given an on the spot fine
His truck is on the green channel
It's carrying eggs, milk, and oil
It’s part of the city’s supply system
According to the regulations, we should not penalize this truck
Li Kunsheng, Director of Beijing Municipal Environmental Protection Bureau, Vehicular Emissions Department
Fake cars are common
Or if we put it in more serious terms, fake cars are everywhere
It's a secret kept within the automotive industry
90% of basic environmental protection devices are not installed
So how does that play out in terms of emissions?
If 30,000 [noncompliant] vehicles enter the city
It's equivalent to several million [compliant] vehicles on the road at night
What kind of emissions result if emission control devices are not used?
The quantity of particulate emissions
from just one vehicle [with no safeguards]
Is 500 times the emissions from a vehicle of National Standard 4
Diesel cars do not make up a big proportion of vehicles
It’s similar to the case of scrap coal
There are not many
Only 17% of all cars are diesel
but their emissions of nitrogen oxides
make up 70% of all vehicle emissions
and as for their emission of primary particles
relative to all vehicles?
99%
There's an even scarier aspect to this too
The particulates in diesel vehicle emissions
have exceptionally high toxicity
PAHs are carcinogens
But diesel vehicles emit PAHs on steroids
Nitro-PAHs, which are an order of magnitude more carcinogenic
When I saw those drivers of diesel vehicles in Yanqing
I realized that they themselves are the biggest victims of their own diesel emissions
They are a group at very high risk for cancer
Besides, it seems fairly unreasonable to punish these people
They spent their own money
They bought vehicles with legal certificates
issued by the government
What reason do we have to fine them?
If we want to blame someone
shouldn’t we start with those
responsible for manufacturing these fake vehicles?
Chai: Could you explain why
the emission devices weren't installed during production?
Boss: Well, there are trucks for export
exporting to Africa and other places
There are also National Standard 1 and 2
and European Standard 1 and 2 and 0 as well
And some African ones
But your trucks have National Standard 4 labels on them
Well... perhaps they... export... like if they export
They are sold for export
Ummm... so that's how it happened
You mean you put the wrong labels on by mistake?
Yeah, maybe they stuck, stuck, something of their own
Someone wants the cars
So, so, so, we sold them (laughter)
I don’t know how our African brothers would feel after hearing this
A business always has its rationalizations
and reasons
But what makes me curious is
for more than ten years
if such fake manufacturers are so common and widespread,
and are known by the supervisory departments
why aren't they dealt with?
Don’t we have laws?
Don’t we have regulations
to recall defective automotive products?
Such products can surely be recalled, can't they?
However, from 2004 to today
how many times has this law been applied
to these kinds of vehicles?
Not even once
Why?
This is the answer I got
only when the defects pose unreasonable danger
towards the safety of people or their property
can the product be recalled
They say
leaving environmental protection devices out of manufacturing
has nothing to do with safety
It won’t kill anyone
so there’s no reason for a recall
Then do we have the right to fine the manufacturers or make them destroy their products?
We do
The “Atmospheric Pollution Prevention Act” states that:
You can make these factories stop their illegal production
You can fine them
You can also confiscate and destroy their products
More than ten years have passed since 2002
How many times has this law been used?
Not even once
Why?
This is the answer I got
This law can only be enforced by the departments with the legal right of supervision
Everyone says
I don’t know which department that is
Since there are only a few departments related to automotive management
I just called them one by one
First I asked the Ministry of Environmental Protection
They said:
As far as we know, it’s not us
Then I asked the Ministry of Industry and Information Technology
They say: It’s definitely not us
Then I asked the General Administration of Quality Supervision and Inspection, they said:
It should be all three of us
I think they do have a reason to be confused
Why doesn’t the law
just clarify who is in charge of this management?
I had to turn to the National People’s Congress
So I called the NPC
And this was their reply:
The issue of this law's execution is indeed unclear
This is a very rare case in our legislative process
Why would it exist nowhere else but in Article 53 of the Law on Atmosphere?
Ding Yan - Director of MEP Vehicular Pollution Research Institute
We asked them (NPC) back then
Why did you write the Law on Atmosphere like this?
Why don’t you just let us take charge of it?
They replied that because when they were making this law
many departments opposed it
saying that the MEP should not be in charge
so the bill could not pass
In the end the NPC had to use a vague term to make it pass
So it says that only departments with executive authority can enforce this law
It sounds like all three departments are responsible for supervision
But in reality we cannot control it
Their certificates are all valid
so are the vehicles' types
The MEP issues them green labels
of National Standard 4
but not a single department actually goes out and looks at the cars
which are in fact only up to Standard 1
If you (at the MEP) assert you have legal authority, no one can deny that
So why don't you just execute the law?
The MEP is indeed suspected of not doing its best, I admit this
The situation is that we didn’t pursue this issue further
So after so many years your law enforcement powers are still completely toothless?
Nowadays I don't dare open my mouth out of fear that people will see I have no teeth.
That’s the awkward thing about the MEP's situation.
This isn't just awkward for the MEP
Truck companies are also in an awkward position
The truck company with fake emissions stickers said
If the MEP can enforce the law
and impound those “fake” trucks
I guarantee we would build “real” trucks the very next day
Otherwise, if we build "real" trucks
and others build "fake" trucks
we would be bankrupt tomorrow
So I asked Ding Yan, do you think this perspective is reasonable?
He said “Yes”
Not enforcing the law forces people to cheat
The truck company owner also said
National Standard 4 has already been set and it applies to all new vehicles
But National Standard 4 compliant fuel is still scarce
and the fuel quality is not as high as it should be
When we were in Yanqing
and randomly checked this diesel truck
The diesel gas came from Beijing
and was expected to be of high quality, the highest level in China
But when the diesel test results came out,
the (sulfur content) was 25 times higher than European, Japanese, and US diesel
That's the top level of quality
What about the quality of our gasoline?
This is a table I got from Chinese Research Academy of Environmental Science
This table pains me every time I look at it
because I cannot understand it at all
Fortunately they gave me the conclusion
This shows our national fuel quality is
normally two or three grades lower than fuel found in developed countries.
If we can raise our national fuel quality by just one grade
we can reduce emissions by 10%
It seems like we have some good fuel available in China
We have Standard 4 and higher quality fuel
but these only make up 3% of China's total fuels
This is Hangzhou's problem
Hangzhou has money and
wants to buy high quality fuel
But until 2013 there was no high quality fuel available
Even after a huge effort
the best you can manage is Standard 3 fuel
Even in Beijing, it looks like our sulfur content
is on the same level as Europe's
on the same level as America's
But look at the four items in this box
These cryptic figures carry a hidden danger
They either
increase oxidants in the atmosphere
creating more fine particulates
or increase toxicity
The last item is increasing evaporative pressure
It increases the rate of gasoline evaporation into the air
I originally thought, really, how much can it possibly evaporate?
Then the CRAES expert told me
look at this clip
This is filmed with an infrared camera
If gas stations don’t install
a part on the nozzle to recapture gasoline vapor
then this is how much can evaporate
1.5 grams for each liter of gasoline will go into our atmosphere
The gas in the tanks of the cars we all drive also evaporates in the same way
How strong is the evaporative power?
In Beijing, more airborne hydrocarbons come from evaporation
than from car emissions
And these substances are a major component of PM2.5
So why don’t we make the fuel cleaner right away?
The petrochemical industry told us this
“The national standard is set too low.”
This sentence seems reasonable
How could you reasonably require companies to produce
fuel that's better than the official standard? Right?
Then I asked the MEP and CRAES
the people involved in setting the standard
Why don't you set the standard higher?
This is the answer he gave me
The standards subcommittee (Petroleum Fuel and Lubricant Technology Committee)
Is actually mostly... yes, mostly made up of
people from the oil industry
About 67%
The full standards committee (National Petroleum Fuel and Lubricant Technology Committee)
has even more, in the full committee, it's almost...
over 90%, as I recall are people from this industry
The secretariat of the full committee is also located in the petrochemical industry
Then the head of this standards committee
He's also a member of the petrochemical industry
I used to think
you guys (in Environmental Protection) had a veto right
Yeah, you'd think so, right?
(Since we're in) environmental protection?
This dark joke from Yue Xin
left a very deep impression on me
He said, “The only time I felt like I even existed
was when I came in the door
and I wrote my name on the sign-in sheet
Because before, I didn’t even have a vote.”
He said he and his colleagues will do everything they can
to push for better fuel quality
But the oil fuel industry has always explained it like this:
Most of the fuel in our country
is imported from the Middle East, right?
Well then, most oil from Iran, for example, is high in sulphur
In Tehran, they themselves are also facing
problems caused by poor-quality fuel
The smog there is severe
But Iran's problem is
they don’t have the skills to improve fuel quality
Chinese companies, on the other hand, do have these techniques
Where is the split between government and industry?
Money
From Standard 3 to Standard 4
the MEP says 7 cents per liter is enough
The industry says: no
Give me 50 cents
I say, both of you can sit down and show the expenses
and calculate it
Calculate how much it would be, it's a simple thing
He had another wry smile
Don’t say it's me, go ask the National Development and Reform Commission Economic Department
and see if they know
(Source: Anonymous NDRC official)
You can't control it.
Say you have an only child
And this child is learning bad behavior
As his mother, what can you do?
All you can do is give him one good beating
You can't  beat him everyday
Somebody else may have 10 kids
they won't make trouble
They are right in front of you
They don’t pay us any mind
These deputy-level units
What can you do about it?
Are they going to pay any mind to you?
If your price department doesn't raise the price this year
next year they'll be at your door
Are you going to raise it or not?
If you don't, I'll cut off the supply
That's what they say
I didn't know whether to trust these things the MEP and NDRC said
Is it the truth?
Does it have any basis in reality?
So I had to verify it
I reached out to the Head of the National Oil Fuel Standard Committee
and former Chief Engineer at China Petrochemical Corporation (Sinopec)
Mr. Cao Xianghong
Asking if I can meet him to chat
And ask a few questions
He agreed
First Question: Why has the process of setting fuel standards been led by the oil industry?
If the majority of participants come from industry
This might be against the best interest of the public
When convening a committee to set petroleum product standards
You shouldn't be looking for
someone who doesn't understand the oil refining business
People from the MEP don’t understand it?
The MEP, no, I don't believe they understand
Second Question: Who should set the standard?
If you set a standard
then when the time comes to improve it, you say it's impossible
Then when the deadline arrives, you say you cannot provide fuel
Now you may have all sorts of reasons for this, but people may not believe you
But if Sinopec doesn’t take the lead in drafting this
who else is there to draft it?
Well, for example, in some countries
first, their environmental protection agencies have people who understand the industry
Yes
Second, before they submit the draft
they take plenty of time with industry people to understand, communicate and debate
At the very end, their health reports, economic reports, these are all provided in full to the committee
And then through an open, public process
They let everyone judge it for themselves
And they all have opportunities to express their opinions and debate with one another
If it's done with this method, do you think you could consider accepting that?
I could accept that
I've wanted to give up this Standards Committee chairmanship for quite a long time
Really?
Really
People on the outside say, “You're too partial to Sinopec.”
But then Sinopec says, “Stop biting the hand that feeds you.”
You can't satisfy everyone
Third Question: Why won't you publicize the costs of upgrading our fuel?
Can you publish either your input costs or upgrade costs?
Show it to the public?
In society nowadays, naturally when it comes to
Sinopec, or the China National Petroleum Corporation
People have a feeling of mistrust
Do you feel this mistrust–
Many people don’t bother with rational discussion
If there is some tiny flaw, they will blow it up into something huge
It just makes matters worse
It's better to not say anything at all
Fourth Question: Can we raise the standard and force a fuel upgrade?
Many people will say why don’t we raise the standard a bit
and force improvement in the fuel quality?
If there were an interruption to the fuel supply
resulting in social instability
There would be turmoil in our society
Then would it be possible to fully open the market for finished petroleum products?
That would eliminate the possibility of interruptions to the fuel supply
If it wasn't done right, it could be a disaster
Not every Tom, Dick, and Harry can run a fuel company
Then he might think
why can only Sinopec and CNPC make money?
Everybody else can make money too
Yes, everybody can make money
So I agree with deepening reform and gradual opening up
If the government wants to decide
and push through this kind of reform
Then the government should go do some research first
and find out what kind of risks there might be
Fifth Question: Can [oil companies] take on more social responsibility?
Many people will say
Sinopec is already a Fortune 500 global company
It's just announced an income of 2 trillion RMB ($319 billion) last year
It's a large state-owned company
So, when it comes to environmental issues
why can't it take on more of its own social responsibility?
Sinopec is huge
Like a person
Very big
But it's all fat and no muscle
Petroleum companies all over the world
will try to protect the interests of their industry
That's the nature of a corporation
and it's not going to change
We wanted to know
in other countries, who sets the fuel standards?
This is our conclusion so far:
In Australia, Korea, Japan, Mexico, and Canada
Environmental agencies are basically in charge of setting the standards
Even in the European Union,
where it is decided by the European Standards Committee
they hear from industry associations
But there's never been a case when the petrochemical industry actually led the standards process
But why are fuel quality standards in China set by the oil industry?
Each country's choice is rooted in its history
In the 1960s, China was facing an extreme gasoline shortage
Buses on Chang'an Street, the busiest street in Beijing
had to carry a big bag of diesel fuel on the roof during operation
We were a long way from worrying about environmental standards for gasoline
At the time, the MEP didn't exist
so the Petrochemical Research Institute under the Ministry of Petroleum regulated fuel standards
In 1983 as part of institutional reforms
the Ministry of Petroleum was dissolved
and the Petrochemical Research Institute became a department of Sinopec
With that, the government ministry's role in regulating fuel standards
was handed over to a corporation
In the year 2005, the first Chinese Petrochemical Standards Committee was founded
and the oil industry naturally took on a leading role in the group
For the past ten years China has been faced with
soaring needs for both fuel quality and fuel quantity
China faces an unprecedented challenge
with pressing needs in both respects
As the Chinese economy develops further
environmental protection is receiving more attention
With the Chinese public calling for higher fuel standards
real changes have been made within the CPSC
Although members from the oil industries still make up over half of the committee
the number of members from outside the oil industry
has increased during the past two years
The committee has also set up a voting system
In the end, each country's standards for oil and gasoline quality
emerge from balancing the needs of the economy and the environment
Future changes to the CPSC will emerge from this balancing act
In China, in addition to the low oil standards
there is another problem that I could never have imagined before I started out
That is, half of the oil in China is completely unregulated
Out of the world’s top ten ports, seven are in China
Ocean-going cargo vessels cause so much pollution
that  within 400 meters of the coast
emissions from ships are equivalent to emissions from 500,000 trucks
So, in Shenzhen, 60% of the sulfur dioxide is from ships
Maybe you don’t live by a harbor, but you do live by a river
There are more than 200,000 boats like this in China
burning heavy oil of the lowest quality
How polluting can it get?
At some harbors, you can even pick up
grains of black carbon with your hand
Or maybe you live near an airport
When a plane takes off, that's one ton of kerosene burned
and when it lands, that's another ton
So at Baiyun Airport in Guangzhou
the daily emissions are equivalent to emissions from 600,000 taxis
Maybe you don’t live by a harbor, along a river, or near an airport
but you've certainly seen vehicles like this
These are construction vehicles
Once in Hebei province I saw one of these
and I thought something up ahead was on fire
When I overtook it on the road
I realized it was the source of that black smoke
Then we followed it into a village
The entrance of the village looked like this
(Sign: Diesel)
We saw a small room at the entrance with villagers playing mahjong and selling lottery tickets
They sold diesel and coal slurry, too
I had no idea where the diesel came from
I was with some officials from the MEP
and they suggested we should go investigate
So they bought a diesel can on the spot
and then went into the nearest privately-owned gas station
I was the last one out of the car and by the time I got out
the official's government ID had already been taken away by the owner
Station Owner: You… you guys… what do you want…
I’m… I’m not giving (your ID) back
Environment Officer: (We are from) the EPB enforcement.
EPB enforcement? What are you doing here?
This is a random inspection.
You… You want to inspect? Inspect what...?
No… What right do you EPB guys have to take samples for investigation…
EPB… do... do… do... do you even have...?
We're going to run a test.
No no no... You EPB guys have... what is this...
Yes, yes, of course we have the authority to monitor diesel quality
there is… the Technical Monitoring Authority…
Diesel Quality Monitoring Authority… governed by the (Oil) Union Authority
The EPB has [the authority] too
Environmental Protection… This is the first time I’ve heard of it, what does the EPB care?
Let me tell you… you… take… take… take the sample… take a prepared sample
Yes… there is this… Technical Monitoring Authority… there is this… that...
Yes… there's the “Air Pollution Prevention Act”
“Air Pollution Prevention Act?”
“The EPB has the authority and obligation…”
You… have the obligation… you have the obligation, but not the authority
When the owner finished that sentence
each of us was left speechless
All we could do was take our diesel can and leave
He'd put it so ruthlessly
From coal, to oil, and on down the list
We consume so much coal and oil
Our coal and oil quality is relatively low
We don't do enough to clean it
and when we emit, we don't regulate that enough either
All along, I have wanted to know why
until this gas station owner
Without even realizing it himself, in a single sentence
cut straight to the heart of the matter
Less than half of our coal is washed
There are no restrictions
There are no standards
There are no national regulations
Requirements for coal washing: none
What about the steel industry in Hebei?
It's reached the point where nothing can stop them
Polluting companies: unstoppable
The operators of this truck
have not been fined
No penalties have been applied in 14 years? No, never
Over-emitting vehicles: enforcement responsibility unclear, cannot be recalled
Over 90% are individuals from the petrochemical industry
I don’t think the environmental protection authorities understand
Petroleum standards: unregulatable
This is the conundrum of environmental protection
Now I don't dare open my mouth
I fear that people will notice I have no teeth
Environmental protection authorities have an obligation and the authority
You have an obligation, but not the authority
Petroleum product quality: no inspection authority
“Isn't that the conundrum of environmental protection?”
So one night there was an environmental protection professional
who sent me this photo
This is a photo taken in 1999
He graduated from university that year
He said he was motivated by a calling
So he went to work for the Environmental Protection Bureau
He wanted to make a difference
He said, “Sometimes, I feel like I'm nothing more than a mascot." (laughter)
So I tried to console him
I said, “Why do you think so?”
He said, “You are an investigative reporter
you must know this better than me”
2004 interview
(Suppose) you didn’t get the government approval for land use do you dare to build?
Ren Baoming - Legal representative, Hongta Coal Washing & Coking Factory
We wouldn't dare
Suppose you don’t get the approval from the Administration for Industry and Commerce
Or the approval from Taxation Bureau
Do you dare to build?
No, no
So why, when you don't have EPB approval, it's all fine?
We should have EPB approval
We ought to
Eventually, we will get it
Exactly
Did you know about these situations?
We have taken steps
Zeng Shumao - Bureau Chief, Environmental Protection Bureau of Xiaoyi City, Shanxi
On-site checking, inquiries and records
then impose a penalty
But the fact is he still went ahead and built, and even went into production
We finished the procedure that was required
We issued the Letter of Penalty that was required
There is nothing we can do if the enterprises do not stop
This is a kind of helplessness
Then what you've got here should be considered illegal construction
Oh well, it's hard to find factories that do not violate regulations
Zhang Xuguang - Mayor, Xiaoyi City, Shanxi
The government’s attitude towards coal coking
We are always cool-headed
after we took steps
Previous trends were stopped by us
They were stopped
If they stopped, why are there more than 30 projects still violating regulations?
As the Xiaoyi municipal government, our attitude is clear and firm
If your attitude is clear and firm
Then these unlawful projects should be
Not one should have started
Liu Xiangdong - Bureau Chief, Shanxi Provincial Environmental Protection Bureau
This cat, it's the local government's cat
Whether this cat can catch mice or not
and how many mice it can catch, is decided by the local government
It is not decided by the environmental protection authority
We walked for hundreds of meters along the coastline and saw the same black chemical silt
We could smell 4-5 different kinds of chemicals
The odor here is the kind of smell that stings your nose
What is that smell?
Chen Zhiming - Vice General Manager, Zhejiang Haizheng Pharmaceutical
My sense of smell may not be as sensitive as yours
You said that you cannot smell it
My sensitivity is not as good as yours (laughter)
One ton of steel
if you cut all the costs of environmental protection measures
you could save 100 RMB ($16) per ton
For one ton of coal, you could save 156 RMB ($25)
On one truck, if you avoid installing any environmental protection equipment you can save 20,000 RMB ($3,200)
If you avoid upgrading petroleum products by a single grade
you can save 50 billion RMB ($8 billion)
10 years ago
I asked what the smell in the air was
I received no answer
Now I know
It is the stink of money
In that interview I recorded years ago
the local secretary said to me:
“You absolutely must film my achievements in pollution management!”
So he made me film this clip
He was quite satisfied and said
Miss Chai, I demolished this smokestack especially for you! (laughter)
3 years later, I went there again
An even larger smokestack had been built in the same place (laughter)
Actually, environmental protection facilities were installed at the same time
But when I asked: "Have the facilities ever been used?"
The manager rubbed his hands together, and answered, "Yes… Soon, soon."
At that time the local secretary said to me:
“Everyone tells me, 'Environmental Protection, Environmental Protection...'
Let me ask you, who would dare slow down China's economic development?"
I am also keen to know the answer
So 10 years later, I visited a steel market in Hebei Province
When I went in it was quite empty
The raw steel was already rusting
hidden in the wild grass
Some of it had even become birds' nests
I asked this young steel salesman:
“How is your business?”
He replied: “Do you see any trucks coming to carry the steel?”
He said, “So many steel enterprises
all produce completely identical,
low–end products
They compete with each other only on the basis of quantity
At this point I'd rather be selling cabbages!”
When we produce one ton of steel
how many resources will we consume?
600 kilograms of coal
3 to 6 tons of water
And what pollutants will we emit?
1.53 kilograms of sulfur dioxide
1 kilogram of smoke and soot
And what is the profit for producing one ton of steel?
You can take a guess
How much?
RMB 1000 ($160)?
Not even enough to buy a pickled egg
One ton of stell, in 2014
was less than 2 RMB ($0.30)
What about when we burn one ton of coal?
How much pollution will we release?
1.53 kilograms of sulfur dioxide
3 to 9 kilograms of nitrogen dioxide
2 kilograms of carbon monoxide
9-11 kilograms of soot
Can you guess how much profit there is in one ton of coal?
Two pickled eggs?
You're still overestimating
You couldn't even afford a soda
Of our 36 different heavy industries
22 are in serious overproduction
Mr Cao Xianghong from Sinopec
said one thing that was very accurate:
“It's like a person who looks big
but it's all fat and no muscle.”
But these enterprises are still receiving  large subsidies
You can see here, between 2011 – 2013
the government has given these publicly traded steel companies
this many subsidies
In order to prevent one of the companies
from being taken off the stock exchange
the government subsidized it every other year
How much has it been subsidized?
Tens, thousands, ten thousands, billions...
2 billion RMB ($320 million)
Two years later, another 2 billion RMB
Another one of these companies which had already posted severe losses
hung a slogan in their office after receiving the subsidy
It reads: “With intense struggle and indomitable spirit,
we vow that our steel will be 100 RMB ($16) cheaper than XX Corporation's.”
That's why the Deputy Head of the Central Bank, Mr Liu Shiyu, has called these companies ‘zombie companies’
They are consuming huge amounts of financial resources
They are going to bring a huge amount of unforeseeable risk to our real economy
And these companies are still expanding, even now
Two days ago I received a letter from a little girl
She said to me, a coke plant near her home
is expanding and is going to demolish her family's house
Her dad refused to agree, and so he was beaten
She hoped I could help her
This is the same little girl I interviewed ten years ago
Little Wang Huiqing, who had never seen stars or white clouds
I asked her, “How is your health these days?”
She told me, “Auntie, I can't worry about my health now.
I just want my whole family to have a place to live.”
Thank goodness, when I gave her a call two days ago she said
the owner of the coke plant had just been taken away by the authorities (laughter)
But, as for these industries that are already considered to be excessively over-producing
in half of the provinces of China, they are still listed as ‘key industries’
in the 25th Five-Year Plan for economic development.
There is a simple underlying reason
If we urbanize and continue to develop we only need to increase urbanization by 1%
and all this excess supply could easily be consumed
Where there is housing development, there is demand for steel
Where there is road construction there will be cars
Right?
Mr Jiang from Tsinghua University told me
China's urban development is itself in a severe state of over-production
The situation is even worse than in industry
I didn't really believe it
because I feel like over the past 30 years
social changes in ordinary families such as mine
and improvement in general living standards
were all achieved thanks to urbanization
When I was young my little sister and I grew up in a traditional house
It had 300 years of history
It housed a dozen families
Later, our living conditions improved when we moved into housing provided by my mom’s work unit
The accommodation we were given was 12 square meters and housed five of us
When we slept at night we added another wooden plank
to the bed frame and put a chair underneath to hold it up
Then it became a double bed
This was the window of my bedroom
Wasn’t it nice?
In reality the bedroom was very small, there was no window
so I could only hang a picture on the wall
It represented the fantasies of a very young creative spirit
This picture was taken when I was about to go off to university
It shows what our county seat looked like
I used to walk to school along this road
This is what it was like back in those days
The changes in living standards my family saw over the years
proves that there are millions of households all in need of new construction
(Mr Jiang) asked me
“Hasn't it been a long time since you last went back to Shanxi?”
I said he was right
He said, “Why don’t you go back and have a look?”
This year I took my child to visit Shanxi
and took this video with my phone along the way
(Billboards advertising new apartment complexes)
I am happy to see some changes happening in my hometown
because people there need wealth, they need development
But what surprises me
is that I saw so many advertisements for real estate
within the city, and so many construction sites
But they're empty
I then asked a relative who has invested a lot in the local housing market
how many flats in this particular development have been sold
He said, only 20-30% have been sold
I asked, “How come they've sold so few?”
He hesitated and said:
“Since the real name policy was implemented
for government officials buying real estate, they haven’t been selling too well.”
(My relative) booked a local hotel for my family
I was so shocked when I arrived at the hotel gate
because it claims to be a “five-star hotel”
and I was booked into the “Presidential Suite”
I said, “No you don’t have to!”
He said, “Don’t worry
It only costs 200 RMB ($32 USD).” (laughter)
We drove our car into the parking lot
and it didn't have a single light, it was in total darkness
And then this middle-aged guy came along carrying a big flashlight
to light our way
He guided us into the hotel lobby
He then continued to use his big flashlight and led us down the corridors to our room
There were no lights in the entire hotel because nobody was staying in it
When I got back to Beijing
I brought this up with Professor Jiang
He told me, "The Shanxi that you witnessed is a microcosm of the rest of the country
In China we lose 80 traditional villages everyday
Houses have an average lifespan of a mere 30 years
There are more than 200 municipalities in China
184 of which have plans to become so-called “international metropolises”
We have a population of 1.3 billion
If we take into account the plans laid out by these municipalities
the population adds up to 3.4 billion
I came to Beijing carrying a small suitcase in 1998
I studied, worked and found, in this city
a sense of self-worth and belonging
If China hadn’t been urbanized, I’d still be back in Shanxi
Working a menial job that my parents found for me
Wearing blue overalls and spending the rest of my life using an abacus
Cities gave us our personal freedom and gave this nation three decades of prosperity
When there are 300-400 million people knocking on our cities’ doors
Urbanization becomes an unavoidable reality
and those who enter will bring unimaginable culture and wealth to this country
But if we don't change our current model of using capital
to fuel industry and urban development, what will be the consequences?
The Development Research Center of the State Council projects that in 15 years
our coal consumption will rise to 6 billion tons
while the number of vehicles will rise to 400 million
So what does that mean for us?
Professor Ni of Tsinghua University told me
“This means that even before we run out of natural resources,
we will have exhausted the capacity of our environment.”
This means that now in China
the pollution and traffic jams have just started
The needs of a country
Beijing
Nanjing, Xi'an, Chengdu
This photo was taken during the November 2014 APEC summit in Beijing
One morning, my husband took me to a place he often visited as a child
His father taught him ice skating, swimming, and fishing there
He said he loved to look at the texture of the ice in winter
It spread all the way to the corner turret of the Forbidden City
That was his memory of this elegant and ancient city
We looked at this scene together like a kid staring at the last piece of candy
You know that if you don't eat it, it will melt
But you also know that once you eat it, it will disappear
Now we felt that same sense of sweetness, anxiety and frustration
Wang Yuesi, Researcher, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Institute of Atmospheric Physics
I am a native of Beijing
When I was a child, the sky was blue and the clouds were white
The canal water was so clear we could see the bottom, we could catch fish with our hands
I also grew up here
I also remember what it was like when I was still a child
Standing on Chang'an Avenue, we could see all the way to the Western Hills
Having clean air is not an impossible task
It's completely achievable
It just depends how determined you are
I hope and believe that with dedication and hard work, we'll be able to keep our "APEC Blue"
When I got back, I asked the experts at the Chinese Academy of Sciences:
“Can you tell me, what would it take if we want to keep our APEC Blue?”
He said, we must cut emissions of sulfur dioxide by this much against 2013 levels
nitrogen oxide by this much
and PM2.5 by this much
In short, we would have to cut our pollutants by more than half in exchange for that blue sky
During the APEC Summit, China and the US issued a joint statement
China pledged that its carbon emissions will peak around 2030
and non-fossil energy sources will make up 20% of its energy infrastructure
Coal dominates our country's energy infrastructure
and is a source of both carbon emissions and smog
Reducing our carbon output and cutting toxic emissions go hand in hand
When I set the goal for 2030, I specified that should be our peak
It is actually a “reverse coercion system.”
So we will start moving on the green, low-carbon path
People may ask, to protect the environment, do we really have to sacrifice economic development?
That's a debt you have to settle
If you've acted wrongly before, you have to make up for it now
The real problem now becomes, how do we increase the employment rate and the average income?
Through transformation
What if during this transformation some workers in some industries lose their jobs?
Right now, China's energy-saving and environmental protection industries generate over 3.7 trillion RMB ($590 billion) a year
and employ around 39 million people
Don't forget, this is an industry too
But many people may wonder, will the Chinese government keep investing in economic growth?
If we want to maintain the rate of economic growth
the way to do it is precisely through green, low-carbon, recycling-focused programs
Consider the Great Smog of 1952 in London
or the smog crisis in Los Angeles
It took them six to seven decades to solve their problems
We can learn from their experience
We will get through this stage much more quickly than they did
Before, I was worried that
Beijing is still expanding
The number of cars is still increasing
Can pollution there really be reduced?
But this is Los Angeles
A place very similar to Beijing
It also has mountains on three sides
So it's hard for polluted air to disperse
That’s why LA has also experienced large-scale photochemical smog
You can look at 1950
These cans were sold in shops in Hollywood
They contained Los Angeles air
The can has a slogan on it
“Buy one for somebody you hate!”
You can imagine the feelings and resentment of those who lived in LA at the time
However, since 1970
The number of cars in LA is still increasing
It has actually tripled
But what about emissions?
They have decreased by 75%
How did they do it?
I went to LA to find out
We are now in the air over Santa Monica
You can see a layer of haze over there
That's the smog
We've often seen these tall buildings in Hollywood movies
But Los Angeles is not really a city of skyscrapers
All around those skyscrapers is a  flat expanse of one- and two-story buildings
This low-density urban development means you have to drive to get around in LA
Los Angeles’ sprawl is considered a classic case of failed urban planning
Its public transportation has not been developed or utilized to its fullest potential
This has caused an inevitable increase in car ownership
In a city of 1.7 million people, there are about 1.3 million cars
That's almost one car per person
In the whole of California
850 million trips are made every day
If you add up all the fuel
It's enough to travel to the moon and back 1,600 times
Over there is a beer brewery,
and over there are huge warehouses
This truck just came from the port of Long Beach
Take a look at this big Optimus Prime-looking guy
18 wheels
Over 20 meters long
Its quality is like a tank or armored vehicle
CARB estimates that
71% of the carcinogens in Southern California’s atmosphere come from diesel vehicles
So all diesel vehicles are required to install a diesel particulate filter (DPF)
This is a special type of filter
It's like putting a dust mask on your truck
It can filter out 99% of particles
This driver is from Mexico
He drives an old 2005 model truck
The law says he must install a DPF
But he hasn't installed one
Although his truck's emission level is within compliance
He will be still be fined $1,000 US dollars
Why didn't you install the DPF?
Not much money
He was waiting till the last minute
He makes around $4,000 a month
Now he has to pay a $1,000 ticket
That's a pretty high price
Sir, how many kids do you have?
Six
What if he still doesn’t install the DPF?
We'll keep ticketing him
If you still don’t comply,
We'll report you to the DMV
And not allow you to renew your license plates
If you can't renew your plates,
You can't drive, so you can't make money
To manage its pollution,
California had to enact the strictest standards for new motor vehicles
The Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) has the authority to inspect any new vehicle
It has the right to inspect any car in use with up to 12,000 miles on it
If it finds a factory has been violating the regulations
It will fine the car manufacturer $25,000 for each day since the vehicle left the factory
The EPA has the authority to require car manufacturers to recall all affected vehicles
Paul Jacobs, California Air Resource Board, Branch Chief
45% of the citizens want to comply and be good corporate citizens
Another 45% say, “Well, I don’t really want to, but I’m going to because I might get caught.”
And 10% say, “Catch me.”
“I'm gonna go 100 miles per hour in the left lane of the freeway, come and catch me.”
This court settlement particularly interests me
I only realized afterwards that
The vehicle that was fined was imported from China
It was because of environmental labeling fraud
But this time, once they were caught,
They were fined about 400 million RMB [64 million USD]
Two of the people in charge went to jail
Human nature is the same all around the world
In the US, you can also find people
who want to avoid punishment
or break the law
But you can control 90% of them if you strictly enforce the law
If you do not enforce the law
It will be like the Beijing Environmental Protection Bureau said
90% of vehicles will continue to commit environmental fraud
This year, the government is finally revising the “Atmospheric Pollution Prevention Law”
In the current draft,
it authorizes the Chinese environmental
protection agencies to fine or recall fraudulent vehicles
However, it won't take effect until September 2015 at the earliest
So before then
Every night,
at this very moment
millions of trucks are traveling across
and polluting China's vast landscape.
How many of these trucks have fake environmental credentials?
How many of these trucks are emitting particles and pollution?
This is what we're all enduring
So before our [original] “Atmospheric Pollution Prevention Law of the People's Republic of China” expires
Can we use it at least once?
Can we keep it from being viewed in our history like this?
Back then
When the U.S. wanted to establish strict standards
Once the U.S. car manufacturers heard this, they immediately made the effort and caught up
They constantly sued the EPA and did not want to change
Then,
some foreign car manufacturers said
“I can do it, I can comply!”
Once the U.S. car manufacturers heard this,
they immediately made the effort and caught up
But sadly,
by then they’d lost half of their market share
So I asked the officials in the U.S. environmental protection agencies
“Are you afraid that you're hurting your national auto industry?”
They said
“Environmental protection isn't a burden”
“It’s innovation”
Safeguarding the past is no way to promote innovation
The government's role  is to set standards
and then ensure fair competition in the market
Fair competition will win in the market
But in China, coal  accounts for 70% of our energy consumption
Within the energy infrastructure we have,
how can we reduce coal?
Let's look at this graph of how London did it. (Graph: London Air Pollution Density, µg/m3)
Many people argue that it took London 40 or 50 years to get its air pollution under control
So we have to wait just as long
But is that true?
Look at this
In just the first ten years after they started to manage pollution,
they reduced pollutants by 80%
That's a huge improvement
Let’s see how London accomplished this
When the Great London Smog of 1952  happened,
90% of England’s energy consumption was coal
In 1953,
the average density of black particles
was 10 times higher than the European Union's standard
The pressure to control the smog
was even greater than ours in China now
The English passed the “Clean Air Act” in 1956
At every colliery we used to run waterers on the surface
so the coal would’ve been washed
before being sold on to customers
To use ordinary coal or to to use it in an open grate would be illegal
And that by the way is the grate
Do you still use it?
We do sometimes
It's smokeless coal. And this is called “home fire.”
The government funded 70% of the cost of furnace renovations for citizens
But punishments were strict as well
Violation could result in a £100 fine
Or even jail time
Installation of any apparatus emitting smoke is strictly prohibited
Smoke wardens could inspect a shop and decide that it was selling illegal materials
This is the last cart of coals from a former coal mine in South Wales
It stopped on this track in 1983
In the 20 years following the Great Smog of 1952,
oil replaced more than 20% of coal
Natural gas replaced more than 30% of coal
Across the whole country's energy infrastructure,
coal dropped from 90% to 30% of total consumption
And heavy industry's share of the GDP also dropped 10%
Many coal mines and coal factories closed down
“And that's another London landmark gone.”
Millions of people used to work for the coal industry
How do you (miner) make money today?
Well, you have to find alternative employment
I’m not a rich man,
but at least I don’t have to worry about paying the bills
Mining to me, it was just a job
100 years ago
We had a million miners in the United Kingdom
We’ve just got tens of thousands now
But we've got more people in jobs than ever before in our history
If an industry is on its way out
There is another industry coming up
From 1960 to 1970
In the first ten years after England began controlling its air pollution
Not only did the economy not shrink,
GDP actually doubled
Ten years after that
The U.K had entered the age of oil and natural gas
Its economic power quadrupled
Once the U.K. used  cleaner energy sources,
oil and natural gas
Natural gas, in particular, replaced coal
They achieved blue skies and white clouds
The interesting thing is,
when we were in London looking for historical sources
on how coal contributed to air pollution
The best, most thorough,
and most authoritative source is this one
we could find was from a natural gas company
The name is simple
“Guilty Chimneys”
Natural gas quickly gained market share through competition
And replaced its opponent
The U.K. Secretary of State for Energy and Climate Change asked me
Do you know what London's economic level was at the beginning of the environmental reforms?
Their per capita GDP was the same as China's
Most importantly, the government shouldn't subsidize backward-thinking, polluting, unprofitable businesses
The government needs to give new,
innovative companies a fair chance to compete
If you do, they will surprise you
London’s success story tells us
China needs to leave the era of coal and enter the era of oil and natural gas
Only if we do that can we have cleaner air
Today in the world,
the share of natural gas in energy consumption is fairly high
Natural gas accounts for around 24% of the world’s energy consumption
because natural gas is a relatively clean energy source
How about China?
Just 5% of our energy comes from natural gas
Why is this number so low?
The standard answer I've heard since I was young is
It's because we're a country
with lots of coal
insufficient oil
and not enough natural gas
Is that really true?
It's true
But is it the whole story?
So I wrote to hang Dawei,
which is the Director of Mineral Resources Reserve Center in the Ministry of Land and Resources
He sent me a few numbers
How much of our potential natural gas reserves have actually been investigated?
22%
That means we have a lot of undiscovered natural gas under us
How about oil?
38%
For the resources we have verified
let’s say natural gas
We’ve found 900 billion cubic meters of natural gas
How much have we started to extract?
100 billion cubic meters
We have so many resources that we know are there
But we aren't taking advantage of them
Why is that?
Director Zhang Dawei sent me another reply
Very simple
Just a few numbers
For instance, the United States is the biggest natural gas producer
They have 6300 natural gas and oil companies
How many do we have?
70% of them are under one company
China National Petroleum Corporation
America has 160 natural gas pipeline companies
How many do we have?
70% of them are under one company
China National Petroleum Corporation
This is the answer he gave  me
If we open up this market
Our annual production of natural gas will double yearly
Our verified reserves will double yearly
Why have we been so slow to join the oil and gas age?
Why can’t we develop more natural gas?
The petrochemical industry is not open
and each sector of the industry
is basically a monopoly
and a monopoly can't innovate，
People outside of the industry can't get into it
It’s like an only child
with a toy that only he can play with
and he can play with it until he’s sick of it
or just throw it away
You just have to listen to what they tell you
The oil business is related to security
and if it’s not managed well the consequences can be serious
It depends on how you understand energy security
So, energy security is important
But, the new technology will be welcomed
I’m answer this question
As long as there is competition
Then the industry will try its hardest to innovate and change
You may be interested to know that
the company that controls electricity distribution
around this city, London, is Chinese-owned
Only if we bring down the price of energy
will there be competitiveness
I think,
by being open,
you share ideas,
you innovate, you get the best from the world
What is the key to controlling China’s smog?
Reform of energy systems and policies
In preparing for this documentary
I encountered for the first time
China’s energy problems
I only had a rough feeling for the problem
China’s reform and opening up
was not how I had originally imagined it
Like the process of a chick hatching from its egg
As soon as it hatches it is already complete
and alive
But it’s more like the process of a cicada shedding its skin
little by little
emerging from the skin it originally had
And energy is the last part that remains in the shell
It has always been considered
important to national security
and economic security, so it has not been treated as a commodity
It has been impossible for it to be exposed to real market forces
But the shell itself is also paying a price
This is a diagram showing a network of corruption
in the energy industry over the past two years
Energy is a sector with a high rate of corruption
The former director of the National Energy Administration, Liu Tienan
during his court hearing said that
in order to curb high rates of corruption
those rights that should have originally belonged to the market
should be given back to the market
So in June 2014
China’s national energy security strategy
stated that
energy is a commodity
We need to build an effective market structure
and market system
and we need to change the method of supervision that the government uses for energy
But as we’re waiting for the country
to build and improve
a massive energy system
what can we do?
Even the world's most powerful government
can't control pollution by itself
It needs to rely on
ordinary people like you and me
Our choices
and our determination
In 2003, when I was reporting on SARS
the most important lesson I learned was that
only with information disclosure
can there be a basis for public participation
Over the past three years
at the same time as providing
air quality forecasts
the government has also established
the largest
online monitoring network in the world
to monitor polluting enterprises
What we need to do is to use this data
and not waste the money spent on it
Let everyone see the data
Put it out in the sunlight
This is a mobile app
After downloading this software
you can see on your phone
in an area about 5 kilometers around you
which enterprises are emitting pollutants
These red circles
all show enterprises exceeding emissions standards
China’s 6000 key enterprises
discharge 65% of China’s waste emissions
You can submit a report to the environmental protection authorities
You can also share these details on Weibo
All these with traces of blue
are enterprises reported by the public that have promised to
take corrective actions by a certain time
Of course the shame is that
if the data for some places
Is not disclosed at all
what can we do?
So last year
I attended
a forum which was the first time local environmental legislation had been drafted with public participation
During this forum
I heard lots of disputes
The main dispute was around
whether to force key enterprises
to disclose information
In the end
Hebei Province published the first
regulations with public participation
The regulations required that
key polluting enterprises
must publicize their information
If they don’t publicize this information
citizens can file lawsuits
requiring the enterprises to pay a daily fine,
with the maximum being 100,000 RMB (16,000 USD) per day
But
who is going to file these lawsuits?
Only 1% of major environmental disputes
go to court in China
What’s the reason for such a small number?
Can you guess
before this year
how many NGOs in China
were allowed to file law suits?
None
This is because at the time
regulations in the Civil Procedural Law stated that
only “relevant organizations” can file lawsuits
As to who these relevant organizations are
no one knows
But from January 1st this year
the new Environmental Protection Law ruled that as long as an organization
has been carrying out environmental protection work for 5 or more years,
and has not broken the law in any way,
then they can qualify to file lawsuits
At present
some people from among the more than 700 environmental protection organizations
are already trying
The slogan proposed is
“Does the new environmental law have what it takes?
Our partners are testing it right now.”
As for ordinary people like us,
if you don't have time to
join an environmental protection organization
then what else can you do?
In cooperation with Friends of Nature we
have made a short animation
If you're going less than 5km
please take public transportation, ride a bike, or carpool
If you drive a car
Don't let the engine idle longer than 30 seconds
If you see a diesel vehicle belching black exhaust
Try calling 12369 to report it
Those “black tails” behind diesel trucks are full of PM2.5
they endanger public health.
If you see a restaurant releasing cooking smoke
Ask them to install a filtering system
Or leave them a negative review online
If you see dust blowing from uncovered piles at construction sites
If you think there might be a leak at a gas station
Try calling 12369
If you burn coal at home
As much as you can, try to avoid low-quality coal
Ask your mom to clean the kitchen range and hood
to keep the family healthy
And you can try taking pictures to help locate industrial pollution sources
supervise and report illegal activity
and tweet @ your local environmental bureau on Weibo
Check out the list of polluting manufacturers
and boycott their products
When our air quality laws are being written and revised
participate in the public commenting process
and make your voice heard
With  a little thought and care,
the smog will start to clear
Before,
When I walked by the uncovered construction site near my home
I usually just covered my nose and went on past
But now I know
At lease 15% of Beijing's PM2.5 pollution
comes from blowing dust
I decided I had to try
(Chai) We live nearby
(Chai) Why haven't you covered this dirt?
(Worker) Ask our boss
(Chai) Okay, where's your boss?
(Worker) Over there, go look over there
(Chai) You haven’t covered that huge dirt pile alongside the road
(Chai) As soon as the wind blows, the dust flies everywhere
(Boss) I know, I know, I know, I know
(Boss) It’s our fault
(Chai) So when are you going to cover it?
(Boss) Right away
(Chai) Okay
(Workers) Sorry, sorry.
The whole process took less than five minutes
Right before I left
The worker who told me where to find the boss
said,
“Do you know why he's afraid of you?”
He pointed at the mobile phone in my hand
He's afraid you'll expose him
In my building there is a restaurant downstairs
It serves meat pies
And every mealtime
Everywhere in the building
smells like smoke
Before, I didn’t think this is was a problem
Isn't every Chinese restaurant in the world like this?
But now I know
Beijing's food service industry creates
at least 6% of our PM2.5 pollution
And Beijing is home to
12% of the country's food service industry
For such a high-volume restaurant,
I used to think there was nothing to be done about it
until I went to London
and had a meal in a Chinese restaurant there.
I discovered there was no smoke smell there at all
Why?
The boss took me
up to the roof
And I saw this
which is called a soot purifier
The London city government required them to install it
And the city inspects it regularly
I thought it must be pretty high-tech
until I came back to Beijing
I found that not only does Beijing have them too
installing them is actually required
I called 12369 to make a report
And a week later
this item was delivered:
It all took less than half an hour
When I was taking this video clip
The restaurant boss came over
and said, “Thank you for your supervision as a resident here
We hope to see you in our restaurant in the future”
For the past year, our office lunches have been nothing but meat pies.
Sometimes when I walk by the neighborhood gas station
(here's a gas station downstairs)
I can smell the very strong scent of gasoline
But I thought that all gas stations worldwide are like this
until I went to the United States
I saw this thing on their gas pump nozzles
it's called “gasoline vapor recovery equipment”
I thought it was another high-tech thing
until I came back to Beijing and discovered
We've had these things for ages
and they've been required since 2008
but many people don't maintain them properly
so they release a lot of gasoline vapor
Then
I called 12369 again
If you look at it facing the sun,
there’s a lot coming out.
That means there’s definitely a problem.
It's not normal to smell this kind of odor when you are filling the tank.
Do you see these gasoline vapors?
There shouldn’t be gasoline here.
Right.
It’s wet here.
That means extra gasoline was spilled.
Right, fewer vapors went in.
Part of the gasoline vapors
escaped and went into the atmosphere.
We will stop using it and
it will be fixed immediately.
This requires that the gas station
must every year
conduct one compulsory inspection
of its gasoline vapor recovery equipment.
You can call 12369.
That’s our complaint hotline.
Will you definitely go check it out?
Absolutely.
We go 100% of the time.
They promised that they would come 100% of the time.
Will they really come?
I don’t know,
but by putting this sentence up here
We’ll see it as a kind of test
We can remember this number
If you don’t call that number
Then it will forever remain just a number
I’ve said that this wasn’t a happy year for me
I’ve felt like my life has been uncertain from day to day
That’s true
Whenever the pollution was bad I didn’t know where I’d be tomorrow
or where I’d be in the future
But still
The moment the restaurant owner
finished installing the smoke filtering device
I suddenly felt like my feet had landed on solid ground
It’s a hard feeling to describe
You know perfectly well
that the effect on improving air quality
is completely minuscule
but if one person
knows that because they did one small thing
the situation actually improved a little bit
that person can feel more at peace about things
So when you look back
at the war between people and pollution
you see this is how history is made
It’s tens of millions of ordinary people
One day they say “No.”
I’m not satisfied
I don’t want to wait
I’m not going to shirk the responsibility
I’m going to stand up and do something
I’m going to do it
Right now
Right at this moment
Right here
I am going to do it
Unless we bring these chemicals under better control
We’re certainly headed for disaster
This whole system
that we call home
People in Tokyo suffering from asthma are suing for compensation from
the car factory owners of Tokyo and Japan
for the harm caused by tailpipe emissions
We have the right to know, the right to participate,
the right to sue for damages
Everyone join together
Together we will make
our generation’s
choice to go green successful
If you don’t know how to fix it, please stop breaking it
You grown ups say you love us
Please, take action
And for me,
it is absolutely my responsibility to do whatever it takes
to protect my child
When the haze gets serious,
there is at least one thing we can do.
That is to protect yourself
and your loved ones.
When I drew this little bear on paper,
I was reminded of,
when my daughter got sick,
all my fear of losing her
and all my hope of protecting her.
I wish that all other mothers in this world
would not have to feel the same.
Now, she has grown up,
healthy and recovered,
sturdy and lively,
and as chubby as before.
She is particularly fond of the nature and the small animals in it,
but many times I cannot take her outdoor.
So in her own little pot,
she has been raising a snail.
When she wakes up every morning,
she runs to the pot and gives a puff to the snail,
hoping to help it grow up.
She is so much in love with this world.
Tens of thousands of mothers are being pregnant with
or giving birth to their children,
to whom these rivers,
skies
and lands
should belong.
We have no right to consume
without controlling.
We have no right to complain
without constructing.
We are responsible to prove to them
that a world lit by energy
can meanwhile be clean and beautiful.
Every time I look into the night sky,
seeing this planet rotating lonely,
I sense a kind of
indescribable attachment and warmth.
Someday in the future,
I’ll leave this world,
but my child will continue to live in it,
so I’ll still be involved.
And so I stare at it,
just like I stare at you.
And so I protect it,
as much as I protect you.