This graph shows the Beijing PM2.5 index during January 2013
In just one month, there were 25 days of smog
I was in Beijing at that time, and as I looked back on this graph over the course of the year
I tried to recall the senses and emotions
But I couldn't
At that time everyone said the haze was caused by random weather patterns
Hardly anyone took it seriously
In that month, I made four business trips
To Shaanxi, Henan, Jiangxi and Zhejiang
Looking back at the sky of these trips
it seems like China at that time was immersed in smog, blanketing 25 provinces and 600 million people
I was right in the middle of it, but I didn't even realize it
But the sensation in my throat remained
When I was in Xi'an, I was coughing so badly that I couldn't even sleep
so I cut up a lemon and put it beside my pillow
When I returned to Beijing, I discovered that I was pregnant
This is what she looked like the first time I saw her
At that moment, I knew she must be a girl, because it looked like she had a girl's haircut
When I heard her heartbeat for the first time, there was nothing I wanted more than for her to be healthy
But
she was diagnosed with a benign tumor, which would require surgery immediately after birth
Before the anaesthesia, the doctor told me
"Your baby is so young that there is a possibility she won't survive the general anaesthetic.
You need to be mentally prepared for it."
Before I could even hold her, she was carried off to the operating room
After that, the nurse gave me this toy bear which she used to comfort children
Instead, she used it to comfort me
When I saw my daughter after the surgery, she was still unconscious
The doctor said,
"The operation was very successful. But there is one thing you have to forgive me for:
She is so chubby that it took several attempts to find a vein for the anesthetic."
I took her tiny hand, full of needle marks, and I held it to my face
I called her name until, she opened her eyes and looked at me
I'm a very lucky person
After that, I quit my job so I could spend my time keeping her company and looking after her
As long as we were all together, safe and sound, nothing else mattered
But already on our way home from the hospital, I started to feel scared
The smell of black smoke and burning fire was everywhere
I covered her nose with my handkerchief
I know it seems stupid, since in her struggle to breathe through it, she would just inhale more smog
Before that moment, I'd never been afraid of air pollution and I'd never worn a filter mask
But now, there is a little life in your arms, her breathing, eating and drinking are all on your shoulders
That's when you begin to feel afraid
That severe smog at the end of 2013 lasted about two months
The continuous smog made me feel like it wasn't just random and that it couldn't possibly be over quickly
It was the same as a sky I saw ten years ago, in Shanxi
2004 interview
Chai: "Is it like this every day?"
Boy: "Every day of every year, it's like this! It's lasted for three years now, not just a day or two."
"Benzopyrene is a powerful carcinogen. As time goes on, it accumulates in one's body
Once enough of it accumulates, it increases a person's risk of getting cancer."
Rivers in Shanxi: 88.4% are polluted, 62% are no longer usable
Chai: "Sir, do you think this is still a river?"
Wang: "It's not river water, it's wastewater.
Tests show that the annual average benzopyrene level here is 290 times above the regulatory limit."
Abandoned mining area: Ground water levels have fallen; environmental crisis is imminent
Person: "All of the trees over there died. Those two big trees there have completely split open."
Chai: "Have you ever seen a real star before?"
Wang Huiqing: "No, I haven't."
What about blue sky?
I've seen one that's a little blue
What about white clouds?
No, I haven't.
When I interviewed this six-year-old girl in 2004,
it didn't cross my mind at all, that what she said could be the same experience my daughter would have
These photos show each day of 2014 in Beijing
Only when the air quality was good would I dare take my daughter outside with me
But how many good days were there?
175 were polluted
That means that in one year, half of the time I had no choice but to keep her at home like a prisoner
Ten years ago, the director of the Environmental Protection Bureau told me
"Xiaoyi is a microcosm of Shanxi; Shanxi is a microcosm of China."
In just a decade, I've looked on helplessly as this has come true
In March-April 2014
46 photographers
recorded images of the sky for 40 consecutive days
Tianjin - 197 polluted days in 2014
Shenyang - 152 polluted days in 2014
Chengdu - 125 polluted days in 2014
Lanzhou - 112 polluted days in 2014
Shijiazhuang - 264 polluted days in 2014
I once watched a TV series called "Under the Dome"
It was about a small town suddenly enclosed by a dome that appeared out of nowhere
Cut off from the world, no way out
But one day, I realized that we're all living in the same reality
Sometimes, when I get up in the morning
I see my daughter standing at our balcony window, smacking on the glass
This is her way of telling me that she wants to go outside
I think, one day, she will ask me
Mama, why do you keep me shut inside?
What is really out there?
Will anything hurt me?
Everything I have done throughout this year is to answer the questions she will ask me in the future
What is smog?
Where does it come from?
What can we do about it?
So, what is the smog?
Sometimes, I turn off the light
I want to see it, I know the PM2.5 is there
They're airborne particles with a diameter of 2.5 micrometers
So they reflect a large amount of visible light
leaving us in a world with very low visibility
However, I can't see them because the smallest particle the naked eye can see is twenty times bigger
In other words, this is a war against an invisible enemy
There's only one way to see them
It's this
This is a PM2.5 sampling device
I put a very clean sampling filter into the machine
and carried it for 24 hours
November 26th, 2014 - Air Quality Index: 282
This is what the filter looked like at the very beginning, right?
After 24 hours it looked like this
If I don't do anything to protect my child she will breathe in all of this stuff
How much will she breathe in?
305.91 micrograms per cubic meter
But who can understand a number like this, right?
We can only compare it
This is the WHO standard for maximum PM2.5 per day
This is the standard in the United States
This is the standard in Europe
and this is the standard in China
How much did we breathe in on that day?
Almost 5 times China's maximum limit
Although it sounds like that was just one slightly alarming number
I really wanted to know what substances were actually in that sample
Prof. Qiu Xinhua from Peking University was kind enough to run this test for me
Here are the results of his analysis:
It contains 15 types of carcinogens including benzo[a]pyrene, one of the world's strongest carcinogens
How many times the standard was there?
14 times
I couldn't believe this number
Do you remember, in that clip, when I was standing in Xiaoyi, surrounded by coal plants?
The amount of Benzo[a]pyrene I was breathing there was only 9 times the legal standard
Nowadays, I live in the center of an international metropolis
When I look around, I can't see a single factory or chimney
So how can it possibly be 14 times the legal limit?
Professor Qiu doubted the results too
He said "It doesn't seem possible to be that high. I'll run it again."
He called me the next day and told me: "No mistakes - it is 14 times the limit.
Our wider sampling showed there are some people whose exposure was even higher - 20 times the limit."
All these carcinogens were stuck to the sampling filter you saw before
attached to a substance called black carbon
It's tiny, only 0.2 micrometers
But it has a chain structure, so if it's unraveled, two grams is the size of a basketball court
Because of this, it can absorb many carcinogens and heavy metal particles
How much black carbon is there in China?
This is NASA's estimate from 2009
That bright purple and white spot is China
It drifts above us like a ghost
So I went to Peking University, I know that they have a lab for these experiments
I asked an expert if I could volunteer
"If you put me in a closed chamber with a high concentration of black carbon
and observe and test my physical reactions, I can show everyone the results."
He hesitated for a while and answered
"I'm sorry. I cannot do this experiment."
I asked why.
He said, "Every experiment requires academic ethical thresholds.
The thresholds should prevent extreme harm to the participants.
I cannot run an experiment with these thresholds
even if the concentration in the air outdoors is higher than in the test chamber."
To put it another way, each of us is living our entire life in an experiment chamber
and we don't know what the outcome will be
Peking University used a different approach
They logged how people physically react to polluted air directly
For one year, I participated in this experiment
This is what I found:
I have chronic respiratory inflammation and belong to a sensitive population group
Fine particles impact the respiratory system, exacerbate inflammation of the respiratory tract
and affect the entire cardiovascular system
Tiny particles correlate with a higher chance of heart failure due to reduced cardiac blood supply
I don't really understand what the medical jargon means
Therefore, with the help of the scientists, we made an animation to explain the effect
I am PM 2.5
I have lots of brothers and sisters
Polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons and other heavy metal particles
Each of us bearing weapons
In the game of attacking human bodies
I rarely miss
Scene 1: Nostril
Nose hairs and mucus can block large particles
90% of particles are bigger than 10 microns and are stopped in their tracks
But they cannot stop me
Scene 2: Throat
The upper respiratory tract has cilia that are only 10 microns long
beating 20 times a second, but I pass through them with ease
The smooth muscles of the trachea become irritated
they contract and try to block me, but this bullying can't stop me
Scene 3: Lower respiratory tract
Here the bronchi branch out like a tree into small bronchioles
These are the best ski slopes for us
We fight with leukocytes and lymphocytes along the way
These fights will cause all kinds of inflammation in the human body
Our troops finally reach our destination: the tree-tip like alveoli
The human lung has more than 300 million alveoli
If we block the alveoli, the human won't be able to breathe anymore
However, our most ferocious enemy is here: the macrophages
Their specialty is gobbling up foreign material, and they are known as the body's street sweepers
This is going to be a tough battle
However, we outnumber them
our core is difficult to break down, and and we contain toxic heavy metals
Macrophages cannot kill all of us, and die easily from over-consumption
This is how the human immune system breaks down
We also have special forces: particles less than 0.5 microns
Once in the alveoli, they are small enough to pass the membranes into blood vessels
which causes high blood pressure and thrombosis
We can even enter the core of human bodies through the pulmonary circulation system
and attack your heart, causing myocardial ischemia and irregular heartbeat
which leads to heart attacks
Be terrified, humans
We're in every breath you take
These measurements were provided by the Chinese Academy of Sciences
This complex graph demonstrates that as the concentration of PM2.5 increases
the human mortality rate also increases
Many other scientific research institutions have observed the same trend
The former Chinese health minister Chen Zhu has calculated that the number
of premature deaths caused by air pollution in China each year is
500,000 people
In this battle against human beings
the most fragile and vulnerable populations are our children and parents
These babies are about 2 months old
They have never been outside, but they have been diagnosed with pneumonia
Here they are receiving nebulizer therapy
The parents of these babies asked me to photograph their children
they suspected their children became sick due to lack of protection during heavy smog
The doctor told them:
"I can only render a diagnosis of 'Pneumonia of unknown cause'
because of the lack of current epidemiological studies. But I can tell you this statistic:
In January of 2013 during the heavy smog, throughout the entire country
27 cities showed exponential increases in emergency department visits."
The mothers in my community discussed this event once
One mother asked me
"How should we deal with the smog?
Should we expose our kids to the smog as soon as possible to train them, so they adapt
and aren't disadvantaged from the very beginning?
A medical expert from Los Angeles, a city that once suffered from extreme air pollution, informed us
about the risks of exposing our children to air pollution in hopes that they would be able to adapt
I don't think we have any information
that suggests that exposing your child to air pollution
is going to help them to adapt
If we expose them on day one, they lose some function
If they expose them on day two, they don't lose the same amount
But that's because, not that they have adapted
but because they've already lost the function and they already are injured
It has been shown in several studies around the world now
that children in cleaner places grow faster than children growing up in a more polluted area
Poor lung function early in life is a predictor of lung problems later on in life
And so, doing something about the air while a child is growing
You can make a change in that child's life
This is downstairs from where I live, I took this photo two days ago in severe smog
The AQI (air quality index) on that day had exceeded 500, above the "hazardous" pollution level
However, the kids in the adjacent elementary school
were still outside playing ball games, running and playing around
When people exercise they breathe five to ten times more deeply than usual
When I saw this, I became aware of the fact that I couldn't protect my child under all circumstances
Someday she will have to go into society
and breathing is something inevitable that she will always do
And it (PM2.5) is there in every breath you take
Adult's like ourselves breathe roughly 25,000 times per day
Over time, as it continues to accumulate, what are these substances like in our lungs?
We are grateful to a patient and doctor at Beijing Cancer Hospital who allowed us to film this surgery
This is a female patient in her early fifties with early stage lung cancer
She works in the hospital's accounting office
She and her family have no history of smoking
The following clip was filmed with the permission of the patient's family and the hospital
The following scenes might cause discomfort for some viewers, please use discretion
Inside the lung cavity
Everyone will breathe in these black spots
Including ourselves
Does this person smoke?
No, she doesn't smoke
But she's from (censored) city
From your hometown
The air quality is really bad
Yeah, it's not clean
So this (might be) the stuff that's in the air
Pulmonary lymph node color - carbon particle build up over time has turned it completely black
In her entire body only the lymph nodes in her lungs are black
This is because she has inhaled a lot of dust
The lymphatic system is crucial for immune system functionality
Which means it helps our immune system fight disease
When the black stuff on top accumulates does it affect our body's ability to fight cancerous cells?
It may be the case that it has overburdened the lymphatic system
So this year the World Health Organization (WHO) has reported that
chronic lung diseases are one of the highest risk factors for lung cancer
It's nice to know that this type of surgery is very successful
and the patient can make a full recovery after the tumors have been extracted
After extracting the black lymph nodes, the doctor presented them to the patient's family
They asked: "Can you tell me why my wife got cancer?"
He said, "I can only say that according to my clinical experience, I suspect it was because of air pollution."
The WHO has stated that particulate matter is classified as a human carcinogen
When he told me this I had a question
Doesn't lung cancer have an incubation period of at least ten years or so?
But we only started hearing about air pollution two years ago, right?
Then how could it lead to lung cancer this quickly?
So I asked NASA if they could send me satellite images of the air over North China from the past 10 years
This is what I got
The air over Beijing
Beijing in December
The air over North China
Let's look at 10 years ago
North China in 2005
But I couldn't believe it
I was living under these skies in North China at that time
How could I have been unaware of any air pollution for 10 years?
So I sought out the head of China's Olympic air quality assurance group
An academic named Dr. Tang Xiaoyan
She gave me this graph
This is 2004
Eleven years ago
Back then, we hadn't started monitoring PM2.5 levels
But we have the levels of PM10
She said according to estimates at the time
At that time when it was very polluted, PM2.5 could have reached 300-400
Today we would classify that as very unhealthy pollution
I asked her, could it really be that I was that blind? I was in Beijing in 2004!
She said, look at this picture
What is that?
I said, that's probably smog, right?
Then how come I didn't know at the time?
She said, you should look up the news headlines on that day
"Beijing Capital Airport Experiences the Most Delays in Recent Years Due to Fog"
December 2, 2004, Sina News
Back then we thought it was just fog
We kept calling it "fog"
So after I saw this picture
as a former reporter, I was full of remorse because all those years I was reporting I always thought that
I was reporting on pollution across the country
But I always thought
it was only called pollution when I heard explosions in mines
it was only called pollution when I saw smoke from factory chimneys
I never thought that for those of us who lived in a metropolitan city center
the sky we saw everyday was also pollution
At that time I wasn't a reporter anymore, I was already involved
But I still had a question
If it really was like this when I was young, every family was burning kerosene stoves, right?
Every night we would sleep and awaken to the smell of smoke
How come I never heard about people back then getting lung cancer?
I kept asking this question
until I met professor He Xingzhou, who has been researching this topic for over 30 years
He gave me a book of data
This
A Survey of the Relationship Between Air Pollution and Cause of Death for 26 Chinese cities 1976-1981
So everyone can see clearly, I've put the conclusion up on the screen here
It's very simple
The air pollution from back then already correlated with death rates from lung cancer
The air pollution back then was the result of burning coal
It just happened to be the case that this data was considered internal information at that time
It wasn't that people at that time couldn't smell the suffocating smoke
But the warmth and energy that coal brought was more important at the time
Around 1980 there were 3,700 factories inside Beijing
for a large agricultural country eager to develop, smokestacks were a sign of progress
For some people, they are just two smokestacks
For some people, they are reference points to direct you home
We had absolutely no experience or consciousness of pollution, nor the ability to control it
Major pollutants did not have any set standards
Even though the amount of coal burned wasn't near today's levels, the pollution discharged was enormous
In terms of PM2.5 levels, in 2006, the average concentration of PM2.5 was higher than it is today
It was this year that China proposed saving energy and reducing emissions
and setting standards for sulfur dioxide and other major pollutants
Afterwards, air pollution started to decrease
but the amount of fine particles affecting visibility increased
The amount of days with extremely high pollution increased
and people started feeling strongly about pollution
Economic development has increased life expectancy in China
and has brought more ways to recover from illness
But the risks that come from air pollution have become obvious
In the past 30 years, the death rate from lung cancer in China has increased by 465%
Even though smoking and an aging society are major factors in this statistic
The risk of developing lung cancer associated with particulate matter is receiving increased attention
Monitoring of PM2.5 levels started in 2012 and China implemented its "Air Pollution Prevention Plan"
As wages increased and information became more transparent
people's expectations on the environment rose as well
A person
Or not even a person, how should any living organism live?
When spring arrives, you open your doors the wind blows in
The smell of flowers fills the air and colors come back to life
Sometimes when it rains or when it's foggy out
You can't help but breathe the air deep into your lungs and
experience the feeling of small water droplets filling them up
Both piercingly cold but also pure and fresh
In autumn, you would spend a whole afternoon
with a loved one doing absolutely nothing, just basking lazily in the sun
In the winter, you would go outside with your kids
when it's snowing, she sticks out her tongue to catch the snowflakes
You would teach her about nature and the beauty of life
But now...
This year, every day when I wake up the first thing I do is check the air quality on my phone
Because it will determine my whole day
I rely on a wind from the northwest to live my life
I wear a mask when I go for a walk
I wear a mask when I go shopping
I wear a mask when I go to see my friends
I use tape to cover up every crack of the windows and doors in my house
When I took my daughter to get vaccinated I was afraid even when she smiled at me
Actually, I'm not really afraid of death
I just don't want to live like this
So whenever someone asks me what are you doing this for?
I can only tell them
This is a personal battle between me and air pollution
Where does air pollution come from?
I want to know where it comes from
I want to understand what is really going on
I examined a strip of sampling film under a scientist's microscope and I saw what it looked like
Pollution was not the collection of identical particles that I imagined it to be
It is a mixture of all sorts of things
Being a mixture makes it more poisonous as well as allowing it to spread more rapidly
Pollutants can chemically react with each other
The Chinese Academy of Sciences explained the pollution sources to me
burning coal, burning oil, burning organic materials industry, farming, chemical fertilizers, dust emission
Most of these causes are due to human activity
If you analyze these factors you will find where most of pollution comes from
This is the conclusion
60% of the PM2.5 in China comes from
burning coal and oil, that is, the burning of fossil fuels
PM2.5 has existed long before humans
Volcanic eruptions and forest fires would emit large amounts of fine particulate matter
Starting from when we discovered how to make fire from wood, human activities have contributed to PM2.5
In the past, the use of coal in large quantities led to serious pollution in England and Germany
and when we entered the age of oil, burning oil led to serious pollution in America and Japan
At this moment there are still many developing countries in the process of industrializing
India
Iran
Pakistan
Afghanistan
All face problems with pollution from burning fossil fuels
as does China, the country that has developed fastest in the world
It's large size has led to burning large amounts of both types of fossil fuels
How much fuel are we actually burning?
We can see in 2014
This figure represents the quantities of fossil fuel being burned around the world
You can see how bright China is
That bright white and red area, that's our country
From the image we can see China burns from 3-4 times more fossil fuel than Europe
We have burned so much fossil fuel
But the thing that surprised me most was that
the pollutants from coal and oil can have large-scale chemical reactions
Wang Yuesi, Du Jiming and Tang Xiaoyan
We haven't yet dealt with coal pollution, and now vehicle pollution has been added to the mix
The pollution in China right now is basically an overlap of these two types of pollution
All kinds of particles react with each other in the air
Air movement has decreased but the same quantity of pollutants remains
The unfortunate thing is that these pollutants haven't spread out
but are instead reacting with each other, what we call secondary particles
Complex pollutants, they absorb, adhere, collide, merge
They all mix together
There's no way for us to change natural conditions we can only change ourselves
and the way to do that is to reduce emissions
The whole world needs to burn coal and oil, right?
So what's wrong with our coal?
Do you know how much coal China has burned?
In 2013 we had already burned 3.6 billion tons
But do you know how much all the other countries in the world have burned?
We have burned more coal than the rest of the world combined
The last time a country had this kind of consumption was England in 1860
But as a result, they paid a heavy price
Deep in an abandoned mine in South Wales lies the heart of England's industrial age
It used to drive the most powerful empire in the world
But as a result, it also brought this country a frightening black disaster
These 4 smokestacks are 103 meters tall
They are the symbols of the industrial age in England
When the Battersea Power Station was completed in 1930
it would burn approximately 10,000 tons of coal per week
to supply a fifth of the electricity for the city of London
You could say that London was eating coal to survive
trains, boats, iron, steel, everyday items
In all of London, it was like millions of micro-volcanoes were all erupting at once
Since they were burning large quantities of poor quality coal and emitting pollution at low elevations
the amount of pollution from family chimneys was double the amount of pollution from industry
Slowly, with time, London became completely covered in soot
People wore face masks to go to school
Wore face masks to go shopping
Wore facemasks to walk their dogs
Wore face masks to kiss
The day of the disaster was December 5, 1952
a cold front stretched across the English Channel and covered the entire Thames River Valley
This kept the smog under the clouds, preventing it from dissipating
Poison smoke has closed down
Residents have difficulty in breathing the murky air
People walking down the street couldn't even see their own feet
You needed a blind person to lead you home
Traffic police used large lamps to light themselves up so they wouldn't get hit by cars
All of London was completely silent
You could only see ambulances, because they had to bring those whose lives were in danger to the hospital
But when they were on the road they had to rely on people holding torches to show them the way
In the end 12,000 people died in the smog
The lungs of the dead were sampled and close examination confirmed that they died due to
prolonged exposure to black carbon, a by-product of burning coal and
short-term overexposure to a high concentration of fine particulate matter containing heavy metals
The Coalition for Clean Air calculated that the concentration of pollution in London at the time might have
surpassed the current pollution in China by a large margin
Even though PM2.5 was not measured at the time
During the Great Smog the concentration of sulfur dioxide was 190 times the WHO standard
and exceeded China's PM2.5 standard by an order of magnitude
In the 1960s, after the Great Smog in London, other countries began to reduce and control their use of coal
But that was also the time when China started its economic reform
A country that had been closed and left behind for so many years
desperately needed massive amounts of energy to develop
And it chose to get that energy from coal
This graph shows coal's growth as an energy source
India is also on a similar path
In the near future, India will be the world's second largest consumer of coal
But as of today, India has not yet set standards for emissions of important pollutants in its industries
India is also a country suffering from severe air pollution
So where does all this coal end up being used in China?
Let's take a look at the 3.6 billion tons of coal consumed in 2013
380 million tons was burnt in Beijing, Tianjin and Hebei
Of that 380 million tons, 300 million tons was burnt in Hebei
I was really surprised because I always thought it was us Shanxi people who burnt the most coal
When did Hebei start burning so much coal?
Dr. Hao Jiming from Tsinghua University asked me
"Have you seen the world iron and steel production rankings?"
He said that China is in first place
Hebei is second
Tangshan is third
US is fourth
He also added that originally, Tangshan lied in order to be fifth
Does more coal use and industrialization always mean more pollution?
Other countries also produce steel
He said, "You will understand what I mean if you go to Tangshan."
So, last October together with the MEP North China Supervision Centre
we went to Tangshan equipped with drones to take a look at the actual conditions
Zhang Dawei - MEP Bureau of Environmental Supervision
Can you see that smoke over there?
It's not that clear because of the heavy smog
Visual inspection of emissions from the factory was impossible
The weather now makes it difficult to see clearly
Drone inspection failed due to intense smog
Have a look behind to see if anyone is following us
The MEP paid an unannounced visit to the factory
This choking smell of sulfur dioxide must be the smoke
We can now see that a lot of smoke is leaking around the edges
This smoke is being emitted without any controls and released into the atmosphere
Why aren't you using the dust filters?
We are using them
Then why is there so much smoke?
They are operating, see it's being sucked up
Oh my god, have a look underneath
I'm going down to see
This must be the most dangerous thing I've done in my career, my life
Oh my god, it's too terrifying
Stop, stop, stop
Someone fell
The guy who fell was Inspector Zhang Dawei from the MEP North China Bureau of Environmental Supervision
We were all scared at the time because there weren't any lights or warning signs in the factory
There was a pit about 3 meters deep filled with steel and cement
Dawei wanted to go down and check for emissions from this place, and he fell in
Fortunately he wasn't injured seriously so we took him to the hospital and then back to Beijing that night
But what surprised me most was we put in so much effort, had so much trouble
and despite finding clear evidence of pollution in the end, this company was not penalized in any way
I asked Dawei why
He said, "You should ask my boss"
Xiong Yuehui - MEP Department of Science, Technology and Standards
Over 60% of steel firms have not completed the approval process
They did not bother to consult environmental protection law but only tried to stop the approval process
They stopped the approval process whether production is legal or not
They know there is no chance, so they act with utter recklessness
Their operations are completely unlicensed, even inspectors don't want to touch this industry in any way
Can you really shut them down?
Can you really stop them?
Why can't we shut them down?
You must be kidding, how many jobs does producing ten million tons of steel create?
One hundred thousand jobs
How important is the steel industry in Hebei?
It's so important that you can't simply shut them down
This province is filled with heavy industry, consuming large quantities of coal
without effective pollution controls, and the industries cannot be forced to shut down
What are the consequences of this?
I have a good friend, Hao, who was also colleague of mine on "News Investigation"
She also went with me ten years ago to Shanxi to report on the local pollution
She knew I was from Linfen (in Shanxi) and sometimes she would jokingly send me pictures
She would say, "I heard your hometown is now the most polluted city on the planet."
I was speechless, but after 10 years I sent this picture to her
Let's take a closer look
Celebrating the fact that our city's air is no longer the most polluted of 74 cities in China
This was a real banner in Hebei
Unfortunately, this city was once again the most polluted city on the list (3 months later)
But this kind of joke really makes me sad
And for people living in Beijing
every time the wind blows from the south the pollution from Hebei moves toward us like this
You can't keep the air out with a wall
So this what they mean when they say "Breath together and live together"
I have another friend, called Fan, from Jiangsu
I used to argue with Hao about which province is more polluted, Hebei or Shanxi
Fan used to say offhandedly, "Well, we southerners don't really have any pollution."
Now Eastern China also has severe pollution
But Fan was quite surprised
She said, "It's impossible, at least Eastern China's pollution can't have anything to do with coal
because I've never seen coal in my whole life"
Right
I showed her this image
These are the iron and steel factories near your house
These are power plants near your house
These are cement factories near your house
In Jiangsu there's one power plant for every 30 square kilometers
And what is the current state of emissions from these companies?
Here we can see their emissions in real time
The red spots indicate emissions exceeding the standards
As we zoom in, you can see how many firms in the east are emitting pollutants in excess of the limits
Among them, Shanghai which burns a lot of coal itself
is burning the largest quantity of coal per unit of area of all the metropolitan cities
10 kilograms of coal are burned for every square meter of land
What are the consequences of burning more coal?
One problem I never thought about is that high quality coal will become increasingly scarce
Right?
So what should we do?
Lower quality coal will become more common
How low can the quality be?
This is common coal
What about this, is this coal too?
At first I did not think this was coal, this must be wood, you can still see the texture and fossils on top
But people from coal washing factories told me that this is really coal, it's called brown coal (lignite)
It's the youngest coal in the world
It's so young that the level of coalification is extremely low
When it is burnt, half of it will turn to black smog, floating in the air
How much brown coal have we used?
This is a graph of brown coal production in recent years
And these are the consequences
On October 21, 2013, on the first day the district heating was turned on in Harbin
There was so much smog that that PM2.5 index exceeded 1000
This was how Harbin people spent that day
I talked with people from Harbin's environmental protection bureau
and mentioned that I heard buses got lost over those two days
He smiled bitterly and said: "Never mind the buses, even our own bureau director got lost
He said when he was inspecting sites on that day nobody recognized him because of the smog."
The smog in Harbin was caused by burning over 20 million tons of brown coal
Plus, in 2013, several hundred thousand coal burning boilers like these across China
did not comply with any environmental standard and were not regulated at all
The coal was burned, and pollutants were emitted and released into the atmosphere
When you look down from above it was as if 12 million people were buried under cement
Coal itself does not mean pollution
Germany also uses brown coal
But in Germany they first clean and wash the brown coal to improve its quality
Coal can be cleaned
The British wash 95% of their coal
And what about China?
We wash less than half of our coal
The other half, nearly several hundred million tons of coal
contains the useless, highly polluting and inefficient material called ash
But we transport it with trains, with trucks around the world and burn it in cooking stoves
Completely useless
The result is that most of the brown coal is burned in people's homes
Even in urban areas in China, one quarter of people burn brown coal
They don't burn a lot of coal, only 20% of the country's total but the sulfur dioxide
emitted from this burning is equivalent to the emissions from all the power plants together
That's how much of a difference washing coal can make
The most terrifying thing is, it's highly toxic
In Beijing, the toxicity of PM2.5 during winter is far greater than in summer
The carcinogen content in winter is 25 times higher than in summer
Why is PM2.5 so toxic in winter?
Mostly because people are burning scrap coal, which emits an extremely large quantity of carcinogens
For many years Chinese people have been suffering from the consequences of burning scrap coal
In Xuanwei (Yunnan) there's a town called Hutou
Burning scrap coal means it now has one of the highest lung cancer incidence rates in the world
This person is in the late stages of lung cancer, he was coughing up blood
He was too weak to brush away the flies, so he asked someone to put flypaper on his body
This old man was photographed with all the people close to him
whose lives were taken by lung cancer over these years
There are even entire families that have been wiped out
We always hear that that China is still a developing country
and that environmental protection is a luxury we cannot afford
But it's often the poorest people who suffer the most from pollution
They are the most likely to be hurt
They are the ones whose voices need most to be heard
They need help the most
These past few years, our coal consumption has been extremely high
As a result, the quality of the coal we use has decreased
We also don't wash our coal and there are almost no controls on emissions
This is the result
The places in China with the most coal consumption also have the highest concentrations of PM2.5
I mean, the easiest way to clean up the environment is to lower our consumption of coal below 2 billion tons
This will guarantee blue skies
If we can't reach this goal, we can try to centralize the burning of coal
and replace scrap coal burning with use in coal power plants instead
As a next step, if we still can't accomplish this, we can try to wash the scrap coal we use
If all the scrap coal is washed, how would that affect emissions?
It would halve our emissions at the very least
We can make two changes at present
First, we must reduce consumption of coal or we can wash our coal
Article 23 Atmospheric Protection Law
The government promotes washing and upgrading coal
Reduction of the sulfur and ash content in coal
Restrictions on extracting coal with high sulfur and ash content
Article 1 of the Ten atmosphere protection articles
Overhaul small-scale coal burners
Accelerating de-sulfurization and reducing nitrogen compounds and ash
In 2014, PM2.5 has been reduced 11.1% from its original level in 74 cities
but only 8 cities met the standards set by the government
If we could effectively implement environmental protection measures
just the ones we already have right now, have them 100% enforced, our ash and sulfur dioxide emissions
would be 60% lower than current levels, our nitrogen oxide emissions would be 35% lower
In order to solve the environmental problem in China
First, we need to have better management
Second, we still need better management
Third, is still better management
President Xi Jinping said: "The dignity of the law depends on its enforcement."
China took only 30 years to complete an industrialization process that took 100 years in other countries
Therefore, on top of the pollution from coal we have to account for the pollution from oil as well
So what happens to our oil?
Most of our oil is burnt by vehicles
In ten years, the number of vehicles in China has increased by about 100 million
Looking specifically at Beijing in 2010 how many cars were added in that one year?
800,000 more
What does 800,000 cars mean?
If all these cars were placed end-to-end, they would stretch from Beijing to Shenzhen and back again
That's one year's increase
The result is as follows
The primary source of PM2.5 within Beijing is these vehicles
But there is another city that surprised me, a city which is under haze for over 200 days per year
You can guess which city that is
Which one?
Let's try another picture
Qinghai you say?
Qingdao?
Hangzhou
To be honest I am as shocked as you are, because I always thought
these were the scenes of misty rain described in all those famous poems
Later I made a call to the Hangzhou MEP and they confirmed this
It's because vehicle ownership per capita in Hangzhou is the highest of all cities in China
On average, there is one car for every two people
So the vehicles of Hangzhou contribute nearly 40% of its air pollution
Do more cars necessarily mean more pollution?
Here's a question we often hear
Aren't there more cars in Tokyo than in Beijing?
Why don't we see such severe pollution in Tokyo?
This is the explanation given by the Beijing Municipal Commission of Transport:
More than 90% of Tokyo's residents commute by rail
Less than 6% of them drive
What about in Beijing?
34% of Beijing residents drive cars
And they drive in the city center, usually stuck in traffic jams
When they are stuck their cars are idling, doubling the rate of emissions
And when they brake, even more heavy metals are released
So every day during rush hour in Beijing how much PM2.5 is emitted in one hour within the 6th ring?
One ton
How many Beijing residents would drive if they are going less than 5km?
Close to half
12% of all residents would drive within 2km
And 7% would drive within 1km
How far is 1km?
That's just a trip to the supermarket or produce stand
Do we really love driving so much?
Perhaps a few of us do
But there can't be so many irrational people, right?
My family owns a car, but after our child was born we made a rule
basically we would only drive for our parents, our kid, or to the airport or hospital
When my husband goes to work every day, he rides a bicycle
This is how you ride a bicycle in front of our apartment building
That's the only way to ride
Why?
This is our bicycle lane
It's almost always full of cars
Beijing has over 5 million vehicles but only half of them have a parking space
But no car can park mid-air, so you find them in bicycle lanes and on sidewalks
That's how they park
Of course, humanity is the same throughout the world
Without regulations, this can happen anywhere
Let's check London
It seems they also parked like this in the old days
then the parking meters were installed
and they parked like this
Then London raised its parking fee and congestion charge
so they parked like this
A few days ago, I heard they are also trying to raise parking fees in Shenzhen
So the folks in Shenzhen parked like this
The same thing happened in Tokyo 50 years ago
It's not that easy
It took them a long time to clear the cars out of the way one by one
This is a test of meticulous city management
Car lovers have another question
As this photo shows there are no vehicles in Beijing at midnight, are there?
Why is the pollution still so severe?
Is it really caused by cars?
This question also troubled me for a long time, until the Chinese Academy of Sciences showed me this graph
There's always a peak in pollution before dawn in Beijing
It shows up consistently every day
At this peak, carbon emissions are about twice as high as the peak in the afternoon on the same day
So what exactly is this?
I wanted to know as well, so we went to Yanqing district of Beijing
Yanqing - Kangzhuang Toll Station, 2:30am 11 October 2014
Inspector: Halt!
Vehicle type: Futian Aoling
Displayed emissions standard: National Standard 4
This truck doesn't have the basic equipment for a Standard 4
Chai: So in fact it's not a Standard 4 vehicle
Driver: So what should I do?
I just bought this new truck
This is my environmental protection label
It was issued this year
Random inspection of another vehicle
Vehicle type: Chang'an Kaima
Displayed emissions standard: National Standard 3
What does 3.29 mean?
It's above the limit
This is even beyond Standard 1
So it has no emission control device at all?
No, basically no emission control at all
He has the green label
It says Standard 3
Who issued it?
Hebei Province Department of Environmental Protection
When I bought it they said it was Standard 3
How could I know? I was just buying a truck
Finally, the truck was not given an on the spot fine
His truck is on the green channel. It's carrying eggs, milk, and oil
It's part of the city's supply system so according to the regulations, we should not penalize this truck
Li Kunsheng, Director of Beijing Municipal Environmental Protection Bureau, Vehicular Emissions Department
Fake cars are common, or to put it in more serious terms, fake cars are everywhere
It's a secret kept in automotive industry
90% of environmental protection devices are not installed
So how does that play out in terms of emissions?
If 30,000 noncompliant vehicles enter the city
it's equivalent to several million compliant vehicles on the road at night
What kind of emissions result if emission control devices are not used?
The quantity of particulate emissions from just one vehicle with no safeguards
is 500 times the emissions from a vehicle of National Standard 4
Diesel vehicles do not make up a big proportion of the total, similar to the scrap coal case
There are not many, only 17% of all cars are diesel
but their emissions of nitrogen oxides make up 70% of all vehicle emissions
and as for their proportion of primary particle emissions?
They make up 99%
There's an even scarier aspect to this too
The particulates in diesel vehicle emissions have exceptionally high toxicity
PAHs are carcinogens
But diesel vehicles emit PAHs on steroids
Nitro-PAHs, which are an order of magnitude more carcinogenic
When I saw those drivers of diesel vehicles in Yanqing
I realized that they themselves are the biggest victims of their own diesel emissions
They are a group at very high risk for cancer
Besides, it seems fairly unreasonable to punish these people
They spent their own money
They bought vehicles with legal certificates issued by the government
What reason do we have to fine them?
If we want to lay blame, shouldn't we start with those responsible for manufacturing these fake vehicles?
Chai: Could you explain why the emission devices weren't installed during production?
Boss: Well, there are trucks for export exporting to Africa and other places
There are also National Standard 1 and 2 and European Standard 1 and 2 and 0 as well
And some African ones
But your trucks have National Standard 4 labels on them
Well... perhaps they... export... like if they export
They are sold for export
Ummm... so that's how it happened
You mean you put the wrong labels on by mistake?
Yeah, maybe they stuck, stuck, something of their own
Someone wants the cars
So, so, so, we sold them
I don't know how our African brothers would feel after hearing this
A business always has its rationalizations and reasons
But what makes me curious is for more than ten years
if such fake manufacturers are so common and widespread
and are known by the supervisory departments why aren't they dealt with?
Don't we have laws?
Don't we have regulations to recall defective automotive products?
Such products can surely be recalled, can't they?
However, from 2004 to today how many times has this law been applied to these kinds of vehicles?
Not even once
Why?
This is the answer I got: "Only when the defects pose unreasonable danger
toward the safety of people or their property, can the product be recalled"
They say leaving environmental protection devices out has nothing to do with safety
It won't kill anyone, so there's no reason for a recall
Then do we have the right to impose fines or destroy noncompliant products?
We do
The "Atmospheric Pollution Prevention Act" states that:
You can make these factories stop illegal production
You can fine them, or confiscate and destroy their products
More than ten years have passed since 2002
How many times has this law been used?
Not even once
Why?
This is the answer I got
This law can only be enforced by the departments with the legal right of supervision
Everyone says, "I don't know which department that is."
Since there are only a few departments related to automotive management, I just called them one by one
First I asked the Ministry of Environmental Protection
They said: "As far as we know, it's not us."
Then I asked the Ministry of Industry and Information Technology, they said: "It's definitely not us."
Then I asked the General Administration of Quality Supervision and Inspection, they said:
"It should be all three of us."
I think they do have a reason to be confused
Why doesn't the law just clarify who is in charge of this management?
I had to turn to the National People's Congress
So I called the NPC, and this was their reply:
"The issue of this law's execution is indeed unclear"
This is a very rare case in our legislative process
Why would it exist nowhere else but in Article 53 of the Law on Atmosphere?
Ding Yan - Director of MEP Vehicular Pollution Research Institute
We asked them (NPC) back then, "Why did you write the law like this, why not just let us take charge?
They replied that because when they were making this law, many departments opposed it
saying that the MEP should not be in charge, so the bill could not pass
In the end the NPC had to use a vague term to make it pass
So only departments with executive authority can enforce this law
It sounds like all three departments are responsible for supervision, but in reality we cannot control it
Their certificates are all valid, and so are the vehicles' types
The MEP issues them green labels of National Standard 4
but not a single department actually goes out and looks at the cars which are in fact only up to Standard 1
If you (the MEP) assert you have legal authority, no one can deny that, so why not just execute the law?
The MEP is indeed suspected of not doing its best, I admit this
The situation is that we didn't pursue this issue further
So after so many years your law enforcement powers are still completely toothless?
Nowadays I don't dare open my mouth out of fear that people will see I have no teeth
That's the awkward thing about the MEP's situation
This isn't just awkward for the MEP, truck companies are also in an awkward position
The truck company with fake emissions stickers said
If the MEP can enforce the law and impound those "fake" trucks
I guarantee we would build "real" trucks the very next day
Otherwise, if we build "real" trucks and others build "fake" trucks, we would be bankrupt tomorrow
So I asked Ding Yan, do you think this perspective is reasonable?
He said "Yes"
Not enforcing the law forces people to cheat
The truck company owner also said National Standard 4 has already been set and it applies to all new vehicles
But National Standard 4 compliant fuel is still scarce and the fuel quality is not as high as it should be
When we were in Yanqing and randomly checked this diesel truck
The diesel gas came from Beijing and was expected to be of high quality, the highest level in China
But when the diesel test results came out, the sulfur content
was 25 times higher than European, Japanese, and US diesel
That's the top level of quality
What about the quality of our gasoline?
This is a table I got from Chinese Research Academy of Environmental Science
This table pains me every time I look at it because I cannot understand it at all
Fortunately they gave me the conclusion
This shows our national fuel quality is normally
two or three grades lower than fuel found in developed countries
If we can raise our national fuel quality by just one grade we can reduce emissions by 10%
It seems that we have some good fuel available in China
We have Standard 4 and higher quality fuel, but these only make up 3% of China's total fuels
This is Hangzhou's problem
Hangzhou has money and wants to buy high quality fuel
But until 2013 there was no high quality fuel available
Even after a huge effort the best you can manage is Standard 3 fuel
Even in Beijing, it looks like our sulfur content is on the same level as in Europe and America
But look at the four items in this box
These cryptic figures carry a hidden danger
They either increase oxidants in the atmosphere, creating more fine particulates, or increase toxicity
The last item is increasing evaporative pressure
it increases the rate of gasoline evaporation into the air
I originally thought, really, how much can it possibly evaporate?
Then the CRAES expert showed me this clip
This is filmed with an infrared camera
If gas stations don't install a part on the nozzle to recapture gasoline vapor
then this is how much can evaporate
1.5 grams for each liter of gasoline will go into our atmosphere
The gas in the tanks of the cars we all drive also evaporates in the same way
How strong is the evaporative power?
In Beijing, more airborne hydrocarbons come from evaporation than from car emissions
and these substances are a major component of PM2.5
So why don't we make the fuel cleaner right away?
The petrochemical industry told us this
The national standard is set too low
This sentence seems reasonable
How could you reasonably require companies to produce fuel that's better than the official standard? Right?
Then I asked the MEP and CRAES, the people involved in setting the standard
Why don't you set the standard higher?
This is the answer he gave me
The standards subcommittee is actually mostly... yes, mostly made up of people from the oil industry
About 67%
The full standards committee has even more, in the full committee, it's almost...
over 90%, as I recall, are people from this industry
The committee secretariat is also located in the petrochemical industry
Then the head of this standards committee is also a member of the petrochemical industry
I used to think you guys (in Environmental Protection) had a veto right
Yeah, you'd think so, right? (Since we're in) environmental protection?
This dark joke from Yue Xin left a very deep impression on me
He said, "The only time I felt like I even existed was when I came
in the door and wrote my name on the sign-in sheet, because before, I didn't even have a vote."
He said he and his colleagues will do everything they can to push for better fuel quality
But the oil fuel industry has always explained it like this:
Most of the fuel in our country is imported from the Middle East, right?
Well then, most oil from Iran, for example, is high in sulfur
In Tehran, they themselves are also facing problems caused by poor-quality fuel
The smog there is severe
But Iran's problem is they don't have the technology to improve fuel quality
Chinese companies, on the other hand, do have these techniques
Where is the split between government and industry?
Money
From Standard 3 to Standard 4, the MEP says 7 cents per liter is enough
The industry says: no, give me 50 cents
I say, both of you can sit down, show your expenses and calculate how much it should be, it's a simple thing
He had another wry smile
Don't say it's me, go ask the National Development and Reform Commission Economic Department and see
(Source: Anonymous NDRC official)
You can't control them
Say you have an only child, and this child is learning bad behavior
As his mother, what can you do?
All you can do is give him one good beating, but you can't beat him everyday
Somebody else may have 10 kids, so they won't make trouble
They are right in front of you
They don't pay us any mind, these deputy-level units
What can you do about it, are they going to pay any mind to you?
If your department doesn't raise the price this year, next year they'll come knocking
Are you going to raise it or not? If you don't, I'll cut off the supply
I didn't know whether to trust these things the MEP and NDRC said
Is it the truth? Does it have any basis in reality?
So I had to verify it
I reached out to the Head of the National Oil Fuel Standard Committee
and former Chief Engineer at China Petrochemical Corporation (Sinopec)
Mr. Cao Xianghong
Asking if I can meet him to chat and ask a few questions
He agreed
First Question: Why has the process of setting fuel standards been led by the oil industry?
If the majority of participants come from industry, this might be against the best interest of the public
When convening a committee to set petroleum product standards, you shouldn't be looking for
someone who doesn't understand the oil refining business
People from the MEP don't understand it?
The MEP, no, I don't believe they understand
Second Question: Who should set the standard?
If you set a standard, then when the time comes to improve it, you say it's impossible
then when the deadline arrives, you say you cannot provide fuel
Now you may have all sorts of reasons for this, but people may not believe you
But if Sinopec doesn't take the lead in drafting this who else is there to draft it?
Well firstly, some countries' environmental protection agencies have people who understand the industry
Yes
Second, before they submit the draft
they take plenty of time with industry people to understand, communicate and debate
At the very end, their health reports, economic reports, these are all provided in full to the committee
And then through an open, public process, they let everyone judge it for themselves
They all have opportunities to express their opinions and debate with one another
If it's done with this method, do you think you could consider accepting that?
I could accept that... I've wanted to give up this Standards Committee chairmanship for quite a long time
Really?
Really
People on the outside say, "You're too partial to Sinopec."
But then Sinopec says, "Stop biting the hand that feeds you."
You can't satisfy everyone
Third Question: Why won't you publicize the costs of upgrading our fuel?
Can you publish either your input costs or upgrade costs, and show it to the public?
In society nowadays, naturally when it comes to Sinopec, or the China National Petroleum Corporation
people have a feeling of mistrust
Do you feel this mistrust–
Many people don't bother with rational discussion
if there is some tiny flaw, they will blow it up into something huge, it just makes matters worse
It's better to not say anything at all
Fourth Question: Can we raise the standard and force a fuel upgrade?
Many people will say why don't we raise the standard a bit and force improvement in the fuel quality?
If there were an interruption to the fuel supply resulting in social instability
There would be turmoil in our society
Then would it be possible to fully open the market for finished petroleum products?
That would eliminate the possibility of interruptions to the fuel supply
If it wasn't done right, it could be a disaster
Not every Tom, Dick, and Harry can run a fuel company
Then he might think why can only Sinopec and CNPC make money?
Everybody else can make money too
Yes, everybody can make money
So I agree with deepening reform and gradual opening up
If the government wants to decide and push through this kind of reform
Then they should do some research first and find out what kind of risks there might be
Fifth Question: Can [oil companies] take on more social responsibility?
Many people will say, Sinopec is already a Fortune 500 global company
It's just announced an income of 2 trillion RMB ($319 billion) last year
It's a large state-owned company
So, when it comes to environmental issues why can't it take on more of its own social responsibility?
Sinopec is huge
Like a person
Very big
But it's all fat and no muscle
Petroleum companies all over the world will try to protect the interests of their industry
That's the nature of a corporation and it's not going to change
We wanted to know in other countries, who sets the fuel standards?
This is our conclusion so far:
In Australia, Korea, Japan, Mexico, and Canada
environmental agencies are basically in charge of setting the standards
Even in the EU, where the European Standards Committee decides, they hear from industry associations
But there's never been a case when the petrochemical industry actually led the standards process
But why are fuel quality standards in China set by the oil industry?
Each country's choice is rooted in its history
In the 1960s, China was facing an extreme gasoline shortage
Buses on Chang'an Street, Beijing's busiest street, carried big bags of diesel on the roof during operation
We were a long way from worrying about environmental standards for gasoline
The MEP didn't exist at the time, so the Petrochemical Research Institute
under the Ministry of Petroleum regulated fuel standards
In 1983 as part of institutional reforms, the Ministry of Petroleum was dissolved
and the Petrochemical Research Institute became a department of Sinopec
With that, the government ministry's role in regulating fuel standards was handed to a corporation
In the year 2005, the first Chinese Petrochemical Standards Committee was founded
and the oil industry naturally took on a leading role in the group
For the past ten years China has been faced with soaring needs for both fuel quality and fuel quantity
China faces an unprecedented challenge with pressing needs in both respects
As the Chinese economy develops further, environmental protection is receiving more attention
With the Chinese public calling for higher fuel standards real changes have been made within the CPSC
Although members from the oil industries still make up over half of the committee
the number of members from outside the oil industry has increased during the past two years
The committee has also set up a voting system
In the end, each country's standards for oil and gasoline quality
emerge from balancing the needs of the economy and the environment
Future changes to the CPSC will emerge from this balancing act
In China, in addition to the low oil standards there is
another problem that I could never have imagined before I started out
That is, half of the oil in China is completely unregulated
Out of the world's top ten ports, seven are in China
Ocean-going cargo vessels cause so much pollution that within 400 meters of the coast
emissions from ships are equivalent to emissions from 500,000 trucks
So, in Shenzhen, 60% of the sulfur dioxide is from ships
Maybe you don't live by a harbor, but you do live by a river
There are more than 200,000 boats like this in China burning heavy oil of the lowest quality
How polluting can it get?
At some harbors, you can even pick up grains of black carbon with your hand
Or maybe you live near an airport
When a plane takes off, that's one ton of kerosene burned and when it lands, that's another ton
So, at Baiyun Airport in Guangzhou, the daily emissions are equivalent to emissions from 600,000 taxis
Maybe you don't live by a harbor, along a river, or near an airport
but you've certainly seen vehicles like this
These are construction vehicles
Once in Hebei province I saw one of these and I thought something up ahead was on fire
When I overtook it on the road, I realized it was the source of that black smoke
Then we followed it into a village
The entrance of the village looked like this (Sign: Diesel)
We saw a small room at the entrance with villagers playing mahjong and selling lottery tickets
They sold diesel and coal slurry, too
I had no idea where the diesel came from
I was with some officials from the MEP and they suggested we should go investigate
So they bought a diesel can on the spot and then went into the nearest privately-owned gas station
I was the last one out of the car and by the time I got out
the official's government ID had already been taken away by the station owner
Station Owner: You... you guys... what do you want...
I'm... I'm not giving (your ID) back
Environment Officer: (We are from) the EPB enforcement
EPB enforcement? What are you doing here?
This is a random inspection
You... You want to inspect? Inspect what...?
No... What right do you EPB guys have to take samples for investigation...
EPB... do... do... do... do you even have...?
We're going to run a test
No no no... You EPB guys have... what is this...
Yes, yes, of course we have the authority to monitor diesel quality
there is... the Technical Monitoring Authority...
Diesel Quality Monitoring Authority... governed by the Oil Union Authority
The EPB has the authority too
Environmental Protection... This is the first time I've heard of it, what does the EPB care?
Let me tell you... you... take... take... take the sample... take a prepared sample
Yes... there is this... Technical Monitoring Authority... there is this... that...
Yes... there's the "Air Pollution Prevention Act"
"Air Pollution Prevention Act?"
"The EPB has the obligation and authority..."
You... have the obligation... you have the obligation, but not the authority
When the owner finished that sentence each of us was left speechless
All we could do was take our diesel can and leave
He'd put it so ruthlessly
From coal, to oil, and on down the list
We consume so much coal and oil
Our coal and oil quality is relatively low
We don't do enough to clean it and when we emit, we don't regulate that enough either
All along, I have wanted to know why until this gas station owner
Without even realizing it himself, in a single sentence cut straight to the heart of the matter
Less than half of our coal is washed
There are no restrictions
There are no standards
There are no national regulations
Requirements for coal washing: none
What about the steel industry in Hebei?
It's reached the point where nothing can stop them
Polluting companies: unstoppable
The operators of this truck have not been fined
No penalties have been applied in 14 years? No, never
Over-emitting vehicles: responsibility unclear, cannot be recalled
Over 90% are individuals from the petrochemical industry
I don't think the environmental protection authorities understand
Petroleum standards: unregulatable
This is the conundrum of environmental protection
Now I don't dare open my mouth
I fear that people will see I have no teeth
The EPD has the authority and obligation
You have the obligation, but not the authority
Petroleum product quality: no inspection authority
"Isn't that the conundrum of environmental protection?"
So one night there was an environmental protection professional who sent me this photo
This is a photo taken in 1999
He graduated from university that year
He said he was motivated by a calling, so he went to work for the Environmental Protection Bureau
He wanted to make a difference
He said, "Sometimes, I feel like I'm nothing more than a mascot."
So I tried to console him
I asked, "Why do you think so?"
He said, "You are an investigative reporter you must know this better than me"
2004 interview: Ren Baoming - Legal representative, Hongta Coal Washing & Coking Factory
Suppose you didn't get government approval for land use, would you still build?
We wouldn't dare
What about the Administration for Industry and Commerce, or the Taxation Bureau
Would you still build?
No, no
So why, when you don't have EPB approval, it's all fine?
We should have EPB approval
We ought to
Eventually, we will get it
Exactly
Zeng Shumao - Bureau Chief, Xiaoyi City EPB, Shanxi
Did you know about these situations?
We have taken steps On-site checking, inquiries and records then impose a penalty
But the fact is he still went ahead and built, and even went into production
We finished the procedure that was required
We issued the Letter of Penalty that was required
There is nothing we can do if the enterprises do not stop
This is a kind of helplessness
Then what you've got here should be considered illegal construction
Oh well, it's hard to find factories that do not violate regulations
Zhang Xuguang - Mayor, Xiaoyi City, Shanxi
The government's attitude toward coal coking is always cool-headed
After we took steps, previous trends were stopped by us
They were stopped
If they stopped, why are there more than 30 projects still violating regulations?
As the Xiaoyi municipal government, our attitude is clear and firm
If your attitude is clear and firm
Then not one of these unlawful projects should have been started
Liu Xiangdong - Bureau Chief, Shanxi Provincial Environmental Protection Bureau
This cat, it's the local government's cat
Whether this cat can catch mice or not and how many mice it can catch, is decided by the local government
It is not decided by the EPB
We walked for hundreds of meters along the coastline and saw the same black chemical silt
We could smell 4-5 different kinds of chemicals
The odor here is the kind of smell that stings your nose, what is that?
Chen Zhiming - Vice General Manager, Zhejiang Haizheng Pharmaceutical
My sense of smell may not be as sensitive as yours
You said that you cannot smell it
My sensitivity is not as good as yours
If you cut all the costs of environmental protection measures from producing one ton of steel
you could save 100 RMB ($16) per ton
For one ton of coal, you could save 156 RMB ($25)
On one truck, if you avoid installing any environmental protection equipment you can save 20,000 RMB ($3,200)
If you avoid upgrading petroleum products by a single grade you can save 50 billion RMB ($8 billion)
10 years ago I asked what the smell in the air was
I received no answer
Now I know
It's the stink of money
In that interview I recorded years ago the local secretary said to me:
"You absolutely must film my achievements in pollution management!"
So he made me film this clip
He was quite satisfied and said
"Miss Chai, I demolished this smokestack especially for you!"
3 years later, I went there again
An even larger smokestack had been built in the same place
Actually, smoke scrubbers were installed
But when I asked: "Have the scrubbers ever been used?"
The manager rubbed his hands together, and answered, "Yes... Soon, soon."
At that time the local secretary said to me:
"Everyone tells me, 'Environmental Protection, Environmental Protection...'
Let me ask you, who would dare slow down China's economic development?"
I was also keen to know the answer, so 10 years later I visited a steel market in Hebei Province
When I went in it was quite empty
The raw steel was already rusting, hidden in the wild grass
Some of it had even become birds' nests
I asked this young steel salesman:
"How is your business?"
He replied: "Do you see any trucks coming to carry the steel?"
He said, "So many steel enterprises all produce completely identical, low-end products
They compete with each other only on the basis of quantity and price
At this point I'd rather be selling cabbages!"
When we produce one ton of steel how many resources will we consume?
600 kilograms of coal
3 to 6 tons of water
And what pollutants will we emit?
1.53 kilograms of sulfur dioxide
1 kilogram of smoke and soot
And what is the profit for producing one ton of steel?
You can take a guess
How much?
RMB 1000 ($160)?
Not even enough to buy a pickled egg
In 2014, profit from one ton of steel was less than 2 RMB ($0.30)
What about when we burn one ton of coal?
How much pollution will we release?
1.53 kilograms of sulfur dioxide
3 to 9 kilograms of nitrogen dioxide
2 kilograms of carbon monoxide
9-11 kilograms of soot
Can you guess how much profit there is in one ton of coal?
Two pickled eggs?
You're still overestimating
You couldn't even afford a soda
Of our 36 different heavy industries, 22 are in serious overproduction
Mr Cao Xianghong from Sinopec said one thing that was very accurate:
"It's like a person who looks big, but it's all fat and no muscle."
But these enterprises are still receiving large subsidies
You can see here, between 2011-2013
the government has given these publicly traded steel companies this many subsidies
In order to prevent one of the companies from being taken off the stock exchange
the government subsidized it every other year
How much has it been subsidized?
Tens, thousands, ten thousands, billions...
2 billion RMB ($320 million)
Two years later, another 2 billion RMB
Another one of these companies, which had already posted severe losses
hung a slogan in their office after receiving the subsidy:
"With intense struggle and indomitable spirit, we vow that our steel will be 100 RMB ($16) cheaper than XX Corporation's."
That's why the Deputy Head of the Central Bank, Mr Liu Shiyu, has called these companies ‘zombie companies'
They are consuming huge amounts of financial resources
They are going to bring a huge amount of unforeseeable risk to our real economy
And these companies are still expanding, even now
Two days ago I received a letter from a little girl
She said to me, a coke plant near her home is expanding and is going to demolish her family's house
Her dad refused to agree, and so he was beaten
She hoped I could help her
This is the same little girl I interviewed ten years ago
Little Wang Huiqing, who had never seen stars or white clouds
I asked her, "How is your health these days?"
She told me, "Auntie, I can't worry about my health now. I just want my whole family to have a place to live."
Thank goodness, when I gave her a call two days ago
she said the owner of the coke plant had just been taken away by the authorities
But, as for these industries that are already considered to be in serious overproduction
in half the provinces of China, they are still listed as ‘key industries'
in the 12th Five-Year Plan for economic development
There is a simple underlying reason
If we urbanize and continue to develop we only need to
increase urbanization by 1% and all this excess supply could easily be consumed
Where there is construction, there is demand for steel
Where there is road construction, there will be cars
Right?
Mr Jiang from Tsinghua University told me
China's urban development is itself in a severe state of over-production
The situation is even worse than in industry
I didn't really believe it because I feel like over the past 30 years
social changes in ordinary families such as mine and improvement in general living standards
were all achieved thanks to urbanization
When I was young my little sister and I grew up in a traditional house
It had 300 years of history and housed a dozen families
Later, our living conditions improved when we moved into housing provided by my mom's work unit
The accommodation we were given was 12 square meters and housed five of us
When we slept at night, we added a wooden plank to the bed frame and propped it up with a chair
Then it became a double bed
This was the window of my bedroom
Wasn't it nice?
In reality the bedroom was very small, there was no window so I could only hang a picture on the wall
It represented the fantasies of a very young creative spirit
This picture was taken when I was about to go off to university
It shows what our county seat looked like
I used to walk to school along this road
This is what it was like back in those days
The changes in living standards my family saw over the years
proves that there are millions of households all in need of new construction
(Mr Jiang) asked me
"Hasn't it been a long time since you last went back to Shanxi?"
I said he was right
He said, "Why don't you go back and have a look?"
This year I took my child to visit Shanxi and took this video with my phone along the way
(Billboards advertising new apartment complexes)
I am happy to see some changes in my hometown, because people there need wealth and development
But what surprises me is that I saw so many real estate ads in the city, and so many construction sites
But they're empty
I then asked a relative who has invested a lot in the local housing market
how many flats in this particular development have been sold
He said, only 20-30% have been sold
I asked, "How come they've sold so few?"
He hesitated and said:
"Since the real name policy was implemented for government officials
buying real estate, they haven't been selling too well."
(My relative) booked a local hotel for my family I was so shocked when I arrived at the hotel gate
because it claims to be a "five-star hotel" and I was booked into the "Presidential Suite"
I said, "No you don't have to!"
He said, "Don't worry
It only costs 200 RMB ($32 USD)."
We drove our car into the parking lot and it didn't have a single light, it was in total darkness
And then this middle-aged guy came along carrying a big flashlight to light our way
He guided us into the hotel lobby
He then continued to use his big flashlight and led us down the corridors to our room
There were no lights in the entire hotel because nobody was staying in it
When I got back to Beijing, I brought this up with Professor Jiang
He told me, "The Shanxi that you witnessed is a microcosm of the rest of the country
In China we lose 80 traditional villages everyday
Houses have an average lifespan of a mere 30 years
There are more than 200 municipalities in China
184 of which have plans to become so-called "international metropolises"
We have a population of 1.3 billion
If we take into account the plans laid out by these municipalities the population adds up to 3.4 billion
I came to Beijing carrying a small suitcase in 1998
I studied, worked and found in this city a sense of self-worth and belonging
If China hadn't been urbanized, I'd still be in Shanxi, working a menial job that my parents found for me
Wearing blue overalls and using an abacus for the rest of my life
Cities gave us our personal freedom and gave this nation three decades of prosperity
When there are 300-400 million people knocking on our cities' doors, urbanization is an unavoidable reality
and those who enter will bring unimaginable culture and wealth to this country
But if we don't change our current model of using capital
to fuel industry and urban development, what will be the consequences?
The Development Research Center of the State Council projects that in 15 years our
coal consumption will rise to 6 billion tons, while the number of vehicles will rise to 400 million
So what does that mean for us?
Professor Ni of Tsinghua University told me
"This means that even before we run out of natural resources
we will have exhausted the capacity of our environment."
This means that now in China the pollution and traffic jams have just started
National requirements stipulate that cities, including
Beijing
Nanjing, Xi'an and Chengdu
14 cities in total, as defined by their city limits
were demanded by the State Council to stop projects that do not comply with environmental regulations
demanding they reduce administrative regulations on businesses
demanding local governments abolish policies favoring businesses that adversely affect the public
demanding they implement policies taking resource limits into account
and give them economic incentives for observing the limits
This photo was taken during the APEC summit in Beijing
One morning, my husband took me to a place he often visited as a child
His father taught him ice skating, swimming, and fishing there
He said he loved to look at the texture of the ice in winter
It spread all the way to the corner turret of the Forbidden City
That was his memory of this elegant and ancient city
We looked at this scene together like a kid staring at the last piece of candy
You know that if you don't eat it, it will melt
But you also know that once you eat it, it will disappear
Now we felt that same sense of sweetness, anxiety and frustration
I am a native of Beijing, when I was a child, the sky was blue and the clouds were white
The canals were so clear we could see the bottom, we could catch fish with our hands
I also grew up here, and I also still remember what it was like when I was a child
Standing on Chang'an Avenue, we could see all the way to the Western Hills
Having clean air is not an impossible task, it's completely achievable
It just depends how determined you are
I hope and believe that with dedication and hard work, we'll be able to keep our "APEC Blue"
When I got back, I asked the experts at the Chinese Academy of Sciences:
"Can you tell me, what would it take if we want to keep our APEC Blue?"
He said, we must cut emissions of sulfur dioxide by this much against 2013 levels
nitrogen oxide by this much
and PM2.5 by this much
In short, we would have to cut our pollutants by more than half in exchange for that blue sky
During the APEC Summit, China and the US issued a joint statement
China pledged that its carbon emissions will peak around 2030
and non-fossil energy sources will make up 20% of its energy infrastructure
Coal dominates China's energy infrastructure, and is a source of both carbon emissions and smog
Reducing coal use addresses both problems
Xie Zhenhua, Vice-Chairman, National Development and Reform Commission
When I set the goal for 2030, I specified that should be our peak. It's actually creating an incentive
So we will start moving on the green, low-carbon path
People may ask, to protect the environment, do we really have to sacrifice economic development?
That's a debt you have to settle
If you've acted wrongly before, you have to make up for it now
The real problem now becomes, how do we increase the employment rate and the average income?
Through transformation
What if during this transformation, some workers in some industries lose their jobs?
Right now, China's energy-saving and environmental protection industries generate over
3.7 trillion RMB ($590 billion) a year, and employ around 39 million people
Don't forget, this is an industry too
But many people may wonder, will the Chinese government keep investing in economic growth?
If we want to maintain the rate of economic growth, the way to do it
is precisely through green, low-carbon, recycling-focused programs
Consider the Great Smog of 1952 in London or the smog crisis in Los Angeles
It took them six to seven decades to solve their problems
We can learn from their experience
We will get through this stage much more quickly than they did
Before, I was worried that Beijing is still expanding
The number of cars is still increasing
Can pollution there really be reduced?
But this is Los Angeles
A place very similar to Beijing
It also has mountains on three sides, so it's hard for polluted air to disperse
That's why LA has also experienced large-scale photochemical smog
You can look at 1950
These cans were sold in shops in Hollywood, containing Los Angeles air
The can has a slogan on it: "Buy one for somebody you hate!"
You can imagine the feelings and resentment of those who lived in LA at the time
However, the number of cars in LA has been increasing since 1970
It has actually tripled
But what about emissions?
They have decreased by 75%
How did they do it?
I went to LA to find out
We are now in the air over Santa Monica
You can see a layer of haze over there
That's the smog
We've often seen these tall buildings in Hollywood movies, but Los Angeles isn't really a skyscraper city
All around those skyscrapers is a flat expanse of one- and two-story buildings
This low-density urban development means you have to drive to get around in LA
Los Angeles' sprawl is considered a classic case of failed urban planning
Its public transportation has not been developed or utilized to its fullest potential
This has caused an inevitable increase in car ownership
In a city of 1.7 million people, there are about 1.3 million cars - that's almost one car per person
850 million trips are made every day in the whole of California
If you add up all the fuel, it's enough to travel to the moon and back 1,600 times
California Air Resources Board
Inspection and enforcement vehicle near an industrial zone in Irvine, CA, July 7, 2014
Over there is a beer brewery, and over there are huge warehouses
This truck just came from the port of Long Beach
Take a look at this big Optimus Prime-looking guy
18 wheels and over 20 meters long, it's built like a tank or some armored vehicle
California has 1,061,745 diesel vehicles
Each vehicle consumes an average of 35.2 litres of fuel each day
CARB estimates that 71% of the carcinogens in Southern California's atmosphere come from diesel vehicles
So all diesel vehicles are required to install a diesel particulate filter (DPF)
This is a special type of filter, it's like putting a dust mask on your truck
It can filter out 99% of particles
This driver is from Mexico, he drives an old 2005 model truck
The law says he must install a DPF, but he hasn't done it
Although his truck's emission level is within compliance, he will be still be fined $1,000
Why didn't you install the DPF?
Not much money
He was waiting till the last minute
He makes around $4,000 a month, now he has to pay a $1,000 ticket
That's a pretty high price
Sir, how many kids do you have?
Six
What if he still doesn't install the DPF?
We'll keep ticketing him
If you still don't comply, we'll report you to the DMV
And not allow you to renew your license plates
If you can't renew your plates, you can't drive, so you can't make money
To manage its pollution, California had to enact the strictest standards for new motor vehicles
The EPA has the authority to inspect any new vehicle
It has the right to inspect any car in use with up to 12,000 miles on it
If it finds a factory has been violating the regulations
it will fine the manufacturer $25,000 for each day since the vehicle left the factory
The EPA has the authority to require car manufacturers to recall all affected vehicles
Paul Jacobs, California Air Resource Board, Branch Chief
45% of the citizens want to comply and be good corporate citizens
And 45% say, "Well, I don't really want to, but I'm going to because I might get caught."
And 10% say, "Catch me"
"I'm gonna go in the left lane of the freeway and go 100 miles an hour, come and catch me."
Over 29913 summons are issued annually for heavy diesel trucks
Ultimately, over 3281 are settled
$1,336,880 in fines
This court settlement particularly interests me
I only realized afterwards that the vehicle that was fined was imported from China
It was because of environmental labeling fraud
But this time, once they were caught, they were fined about 400 million RMB ($64 million)
Two of the people in charge went to jail
Human nature is the same all around the world
In the US, you can also find people who want to avoid punishment or break the law
But you can control 90% of them if you strictly enforce the law
If you do not enforce the law, it will be like the Beijing Environmental Protection Bureau said
90% of vehicles will continue to commit environmental fraud
This year, the "Atmospheric Pollution Prevention Law" will finally be revised
In the current draft, it authorizes the Chinese EPA to fine or recall fraudulent vehicles
However, it won't take effect until September 2015 at the earliest
So before then, every night, even at this very moment
millions of trucks are traveling across and polluting China's vast landscape
How many have fake emissions certificates, how many are emitting particles and pollution?
This is what we're all enduring
So before our original "Atmospheric Pollution Prevention Law of the People's Republic of China" expires
Can we use it at least once?
Can we prevent it from being viewed in our history like this?
Back when the U.S. wanted strict standards, their auto industry cried and moaned just like ours
They constantly sued the EPA and did not want to change
Then, some foreign car manufacturers said "I can do it, I can comply!"
Once the U.S. car manufacturers heard this, they immediately made the effort and caught up
But sadly, by then they'd lost half of their market share
So I asked officials in the U.S. environmental protection agencies
"Are you afraid that you're hurting your national auto industry?"
They said: Environmental protection isn't a burden
It's innovation
Protecting a backward industry is no way to promote innovation
The government's role is to set standards and then ensure fair competition in the market
You win the market through fair competition
But in China, coal accounts for 70% of our energy consumption
Within the energy infrastructure we have, how can we reduce coal?
Let's look at this graph of how London did it
Many people argue that it took London 40 or 50 years to get its air pollution under control
So we have to wait just as long
But is that true?
Look at this
In just the first ten years after they started to manage pollution, they reduced pollutants by 80%
That's a huge improvement
Let's see how London accomplished this
When the Great London Smog of 1952 took place, 90% of England's energy consumption was coal
In 1953, the average density of particulate matter was 10 times higher than the EU standard
The pressure to control the smog was even greater than ours in China now
England passed the "Clean Air Act" in 1956
At every colliery we used to run waterers on the surface
so the coal would've been washed before being sold on to customers
To use ordinary coal or to to use it in an open grate would be illegal
And that by the way is the grate
Do you still use it?
We do sometimes
It's a smokeless coal. And this is called "home fire."
The government funded 70% of the cost of furnace renovations for citizens
But punishments were strict as well
Violation could result in a £100 fine, or even jail time
Installation of any apparatus emitting smoke is strictly prohibited
Smoke wardens could inspect a shop and decide that it was selling illegal materials
This is the last cart of coal from a former coal mine in South Wales
It stopped on this track in 1983
In the 20 years following the Great Smog of 1952, oil replaced more than 20% of coal
Natural gas replaced more than 30% of coal
Across the whole country's energy infrastructure, coal dropped from 90% to 30% of total consumption
And heavy industry's share of the GDP also dropped 10%
Many coal mines and coal factories closed down
"And that's another London landmark gone."
Millions of people used to work for the coal industry
How do you earn money today?
Well, you have to find alternative employment
I'm not a rich man, but at least I don't have to worry about paying bills
Mining to me, it was just a job
100 years ago, we had a million miners in the United Kingdom
We've just got tens of thousands now
But we've got more people in jobs than ever before in our history
If an industry is on its way out, there's another industry coming up
From 1960 to 1970, in the first ten years after England began controlling its air pollution
Not only did the economy not shrink, GDP actually doubled
Ten years later, the U.K had entered the age of oil and natural gas
Its economic power quadrupled
Once the U.K. used cleaner energy sources, oil and natural gas
Natural gas, in particular, replaced coal
They achieved blue skies and white clouds
The interesting thing is, when we were in London looking for historical sources on how
coal contributed to air pollution, the best, most thorough, and most authoritative source we could find
was from a natural gas company
The name is simple: "Guilty Chimneys"
Natural gas quickly gained market share through competition
And replaced its competitor
The U.K. Energy Minister asked me
Do you know what London's economic level was at the beginning of the environmental reforms?
Their per capita GDP was the same as China's
Most importantly, the government shouldn't subsidize backward-thinking, polluting, unprofitable businesses
The government needs to give new, innovative companies a fair chance to compete
If you do, they will surprise you
London's success story tells us
China needs to leave the era of coal and enter the era of oil and natural gas
Only if we do that can we have cleaner air
In the world today, the share of natural gas in energy consumption is fairly high
Natural gas accounts for around 24% of the world's energy consumption
because natural gas is a relatively clean energy source
How about China?
Just 5% of our energy comes from natural gas
Why is this number so low?
The standard answer I've heard since I was young is
It's because we're a country with lots of coal, insufficient oil and not enough natural gas
Is that really true?
It's true
But is it the whole story?
So I wrote to the director of the Mineral Resources Reserve Center in the Ministry of Land and Resources
He sent me a few numbers
How much of our potential natural gas reserves have actually been investigated?
22%
That means we have a lot of undiscovered natural gas under us
How about oil?
38%
For the resources we have verified, let's say natural gas
We've found 900 billion cubic meters, but how much have we started to extract?
100 billion cubic meters
We have so many resources that we know are there, but we aren't taking advantage of them
Why is that?
Director Zhang Dawei sent me another very simple reply
Just a few numbers
For instance, the United States is the biggest natural gas producer
They have 6,300 natural gas and oil companies
How many do we have?
70% of them are under one company: China National Petroleum Corporation
America has 160 natural gas pipeline companies
How many do we have?
70% of them are under one company: China National Petroleum Corporation
This is the answer he gave me
If we open up this market, our annual production of natural gas will double each year
Our verified reserves will double each year
Why have we been so slow to join the oil and gas age?
Why can't we develop more natural gas?
The petrochemical industry is not open
Each sector of the industry is basically a monopoly
A monopoly can't innovate
People outside of the industry can't get into it
It's like an only child, the toys are all his. He plays with them any way he wants, and he throws them around
You just have to listen to what they tell you
The oil business is a security issue, and if it's not managed well the consequences can be serious
It depends on how you understand energy security
Well, energy security is really important
But, the new technologies that we can work on together are answering that problem
As long as there is competition, then the industry will try its hardest to innovate and change
You may be interested to know that the company that controls the
electricity distribution around this city, London, is Chinese-owned
Only if we bring down the price of energy will there be competitiveness
I think by being open, you share ideas, you innovate, you get the best from the world
What is the key to controlling China's smog?
Reform of energy systems and policies
I encountered China's energy problems for the first time while preparing this documentary
I only had a rough feeling for the problem
China's reform and opening up was not how I originally imagined it
Like the process of a chick hatching from its egg
As soon as it hatches it is already complete and alive
It's more like the process of a cicada shedding its shell
little by little, emerging from the shell it originally had
And energy is the last part that remains in the shell
It has always been considered important to national security
and economic security, so it has not been treated as a commodity
It was impossible to expose it to real market forces
But the shell itself is also paying a price
This is a diagram showing a network of corruption in the energy industry over the past two years
Energy is a sector with a high rate of corruption
The former director of the National Energy Administration, Liu Tienan
said during his court hearing that in order to curb high rates of corruption
those rights that should have originally belonged to the market should be given back to the market
So in June 2014 China's national energy security strategy stated that energy is a commodity
We need to build an effective market structure and market system
and we need to change the method of supervision that the government uses for energy
But what can we do while we're waiting for the country to build and improve a massive energy system?
Even the most powerful government in the world can't control pollution by itself
It needs to rely on ordinary people like you and me
Our choices, and our determination
In 2003, when I was reporting on SARS, the most important lesson I learned was that
information disclosure is a prerequisite for public participation
Over the past three years, at the same time as providing air quality forecasts, the government has also
established the largest online monitoring network in the world to monitor polluting enterprises
What we need to do is to use this data, and not waste the money spent on it
Let everyone see the data, put it out in the sunlight
This is a mobile app
After downloading this software, you can see on your phone
which enterprises in an area about 5 kilometers around you are emitting pollutants
These red circles all show enterprises exceeding emissions standards
China's 6,000 key enterprises discharge 65% of China's waste emissions
You can submit a report to the environmental protection authorities, or share the details on Weibo
All the traces of blue are companies reported by the public that have promised to take corrective action
Of course the shame is that if the data for some places is not disclosed at all, what can we do?
So last year I attended a forum where local environmental legislation
was drafted with public participation for the first time
I heard a lot of disputes during the forum
The main dispute was around whether to force key enterprises to disclose information
In the end, Hebei Province published the first regulations with public participation
The regulations required that key polluting enterprises must publicize their information
If they don't publish this information, citizens can file lawsuits, and the companies must pay a daily fine
with the maximum being 100,000 RMB ($16,000) per day
But who is going to file these lawsuits?
Only 1% of major environmental disputes go to court in China
Why such a small number?
Can you guess before this year how many NGOs in China were allowed to file lawsuits?
None
This is because at the time regulations in the Civil Procedural Law
stated that only "relevant organizations" can file lawsuits
As to who these relevant organizations are, no one knows
But from January 1 2015, the new Environmental Protection Law states that as long as an organization
has been carrying out environmental protection work for 5 or more years,
and has not broken the law in any way, then they can qualify to file lawsuits
At present, some people from among the over 700 environmental protection organizations are already trying
The slogan proposed is
"Does the new environmental law have what it takes? Our partners are testing it right now."
As for ordinary people like us, if you don't have time to
join an environmental protection organization, then what else can you do?
In cooperation with Friends of Nature we have made a short animation
To Fight Smog, I'll Do My Bit For Clean Air
If you're going less than 5km please take public transportation, ride a bike, or carpool
If you drive a car, don't let the engine idle longer than 30 seconds
If you see a diesel vehicle belching black exhaust
Try calling 12369 to report it
Those "black tails" behind diesel trucks are full of PM2.5 and they endanger public health
If you see a restaurant releasing cooking smoke
Ask them to install a filtering system, or leave them a negative review online
If you see dust blowing from uncovered piles at construction sites
If you think there might be a leak at a gas station
Try calling 12369
If you burn coal at home
As much as you can, try to avoid low-quality coal
Ask your mom to clean the kitchen range and hood to keep the family healthy
And you can try taking pictures to help locate industrial pollution sources
supervise and report illegal activity and tweet @ your local environmental bureau on Weibo
Check out the list of polluting manufacturers and boycott their products
When our air quality laws are being written and revised
participate in the public commenting process and make your voice heard
With a little thought and care, the smog will start to clear
Before, when I walked by the uncovered construction site near my home
I usually just covered my nose and went on past
But now I know, at least 15% of Beijing's PM2.5 pollution comes from blowing dust
I decided I had to try
Chai: We live nearby
Why haven't you covered this dirt?
Worker: Ask our boss
Okay, where's your boss?
Over there, go look over there
You haven't covered that huge dirt pile alongside the road, the dust flies everywhere when the wind blows
Boss: I know, I know, I know, I know
It's our fault
So when are you going to cover it?
Right away
Okay
Sorry, sorry
The whole process took less than five minutes
Right before I left
The worker who told me where to find the boss said
"Do you know why he's afraid of you?"
He pointed at the mobile phone in my hand
He's afraid you'll expose him
In my building, there is a restaurant downstairs serving meat pies, and every mealtime
everything in the building smells like smoke
Before, I didn't think this is was a problem, isn't every Chinese restaurant in the world like this?
But now I know, Beijing's food service industry creates at least 6% of our PM2.5 pollution
And Beijing is home to 12% of the country's food service industry
For such a high-volume restaurant, I used to think there was nothing to be done about it
until I went to London and ate at a Chinese restaurant there, I discovered there was no smoke smell at all
Why?
The boss took me up on the roof, where I saw this
It's called a soot purifier
The London city government required them to install it, and the city inspects it regularly
I thought it must be pretty high-tech until I came back to Beijing
I found that not only does Beijing have them too, installing them is actually required
I called 12369 to make a report, and a week later, this item was delivered
The whole thing took less than half an hour
When I was filming this video clip, the restaurant boss came over and said
"Thank you for your supervision as a resident here, we hope to see you in our restaurant in the future"
For the past year, our office lunches have been nothing but meat pies
Sometimes when I walk by the neighborhood gas station, we have one downstairs
I can smell the very strong scent of gasoline
But I thought that all gas stations worldwide were like this, until I went to the United States
I saw this thing on their gas pump nozzles it's called "gasoline vapor recovery equipment"
I thought it was another high-tech thing until I came back to Beijing and discovered
we've had these things for ages, and they've been required since 2008
but many people don't maintain them properly, so they release a lot of gasoline vapor
So I called 12369 again
If you look at it facing the sun, there's a lot coming out, that means there's definitely a problem
It's not normal to smell this kind of odor when you are filling the tank
Do you see these gasoline vapors?
There shouldn't be fuel here
Right
Oh, it's wet here
That means extra gasoline was spilled
Right, fewer vapors went in
Part of the gasoline vapors escaped and went into the atmosphere
We will stop using it and it will be fixed immediately
This requires that the gas station must conduct
one compulsory inspection of its gasoline vapor recovery equipment each year
You can call 12369, that's our complaint hotline
Are you sure you will go and check it out?
Absolutely
We go 100% of the time
They promised that they would come 100% of the time
I don't know if they will really come, but by putting this sentence up here, we can see it as a kind of test
We can remember this number
If you don't call that number, then it will forever remain just a number
I've said that this wasn't a happy year for me
I've felt like my life has been quite uncertain from day to day
That's true
Whenever the pollution was bad I didn't know where I'd be tomorrow or where I'd be in the future
But still, the moment the restaurant owner finished installing the smoke filtering device
I suddenly felt like my feet had landed on solid ground
It's a hard feeling to describe
You know perfectly well that the effect on improving air quality is completely minuscule
but if one person knows that because they did one small thing
the situation actually improved a little bit that person can feel more at peace about things
So when you look back at the war between people and pollution you see this is how history is made
It's tens of millions of ordinary people
One day they say "No"
I'm not satisfied
I don't want to wait
I'm not going to shirk the responsibility, I'm going to stand up and do something
I'm going to do it, right now
At this moment, at this place
I am going to do it
Unless we do bring these chemicals under better control, we're certainly headed for disaster
This whole system that we call home
People in Tokyo suffering from asthma are suing Japanese car manufacturers for compensation
for the harm caused by tailpipe emissions
We have the right to know, the right to participate, the right to sue for damages
Everyone join together
Together we will make our generation's choice to go green successful
If you don't know how to fix it, please stop breaking it
You grown ups say you love us
Please, take action
And for me, it is absolutely my responsibility to do whatever it takes to protect my child
When the smog becomes heavy, there's at least one thing we can do
That is to protect yourself and your loved ones
When I drew this little bear on a piece of paper
I recalled all the feelings from when my daughter was ill
all my fear of losing her and all my hope of protecting her
I wish that all other mothers in this world would never have to feel the same
Now she has grown up, healthy and recovered, strong and lively, and as chubby as before
She loves nature, and the small animals in it
but often I cannot take her outdoors
So in her own little flower pot, she has been raising a snail
When she wakes up every morning, she runs to the pot and blows on the snail, hoping to help it grow up
She love this world so much
Right now, tens of thousands of mothers are pregnant with or giving birth to their children
to whom these rivers, skies and lands should belong
We have no right to consume without restraint
We have no right to complain without building anew
We have a responsibility to prove to them
that a world illuminated by energy can, at the same time, be clean and beautiful
Every time I look into the night sky and see this planet's lonely rotations
I sense a kind of indescribable attachment and warmth
Someday in the future, I will leave this world
but my child will continue among the living, and I'll still be connected to it
And so I gaze upon it, just as I gaze upon you
And so I protect it, just as I protect you
Subtitles: Crowdsourced by Linghein Ho and friends
Under The Dome, by Chai Jing