Este gráfico muestra el índice PM2.5 de Beijing en Enero de 2013
En un único mes hubo 25 días de polución
Yo estaba en Beijing en aquel momento
y mientras miraba este gráfico a lo largo del año
intente recordar todos los sentimientos y emociones
pero no pude
Entonces todo el mundo decía que la niebla era
creada por condiciones climáticas aleatorias
Casi nadie se se lo tomaba en serio
En ese mes, hice cuatro viajes de negocios:
a Shaanxi, Henan, Jiangxi y Zhejiang
Recordando el cielo en esos viajes
parece que entonces China estaba immersa en una niebla tóxica
cubriendo 25 provincias y 600 millones de personas
Yo estaba en medio de eso, pero ni siquiera me di cuenta
Per la sensación en mi garganta permaneció
Cuando estaba en Xi´an, tosía tanto que no pude ni dormir
Corte un limon y lo puse a lado de la almohada
Cuando regrese a Beijing
Me entere de que estaba embarazada
Así era la primera vez que la ví
En ese momento, supe que era una niña
Porque parece que tenia un corte de pelo de niña
Cuando oí el latido de su corazón por primera vez,
No había nada que quisiera más para ella que estar sana
Pero
mi niña fue diagnosticada con un tumor benigno
que nécessiterai cirugia nada mas nacer
Before the anaesthesia, the doctor told me
Antes de la anestesia, el doctor me dijó
“Tu bebe es tan joven que existe la posibilidad
de que no sobreviviese a la anestesia general
Necesitas preparar para lo peor”
Antes de poder incluso abrazarla, se la llevaron al quirófano
Después de eso, la enfermera me dio un oso de peluche
que era usado para calmar a niños
Pero esta vez, se usaba para calmar me a mi
Cuando vi a mi pequeño angel después de la cirugía, ella estaba inconsciente
El doctor me dijo,
La operación ha tenido éxito
Pero hay algo que tienes que perdonarme
Ella es tan regordeta que tuve que probar varias veces para encontrar una vena para la anestesia
Le agarre la mano, llena de marcas de agujas
y la puse en mi cara
La llame por su nombre
hasta que ella abro los ojos y me miro
Soy una persona con mucha suerte
Después, deje mi trabajo para poder
pasar mi tiempo haciendo compañía y cuidandola
Mientras estemos juntas, a salvo, nada importa
Pero ya en el camino desde el hospital, me empece a asustar
El olor de humo negro y fuego esta por todas partes
Le cubre la nariz con mi pañuelo
Se que suena muy estupido
porque en su lucha por respirar atraves de el, ella respiraría mas polución
Hasta entonces, nunca había temido la contaminación del aire
y nunca lleve una mascarilla antipolución
Y ahora, con una pequeña vida en tus brazos
toda su respiración,  comida y bebida depende de ti
Ahi es donde empiezas a tener miedo
Esa polución grave al final de 2013 duró como 2 meses
La larga polución me pareció mas que nada una ocurrencia aleatoria
y que no podia acabarse rapido
Era el mismo cielo que cuando lo vi hace 10 años, cuando estaba en Shanxi
Entrevista 2004
Chai: “Es así todos los días?”
Niño “Es así todos los días, todos los años¡
Dura 3 años ya, no solo 1 o 2 días.”
“benzopireno es un fuerte cancerígeno
Conforme pasa el tiempo, se va acumulando en tu cuerpo
Cuando esta suficientemente acumulado, incrementa el riesgo de padecer cancer en esa persona.”
Rios de Shanxi: 88.4% están contaminados, 62% no se pueden usar mas
Chai: “Señor, cree usted que esto es aun un rio?”
Wang: “Esto no es un rio, son aguas residuales.
Los test muestran que la media anual del
nivel de benzopireno aquí es 290 veces el limite regulatorio.”
Mina abandonada: Niveles de agua subterránea han caído; la crisis ambiental es inminente
Persona: “Todos esos arboles por ahi han muerto.
Esos dos grandes arboles se han abierto completamente.”
Chai: “Has visto alguna vez las estrellas?”
Wang Huiqing: “No, no las he visto”
Chai: “Y el cielo azul lo has visto?”
Wang Huiqing: “Una vez vi uno un poco azul”
Chai: “Y las nubes blancas?”
Wang Huiqing: “No, no las he visto.”
Cuando entreviste a esta niña de 6 años en 2004,
no, se me cruzo por mi mente, que lo que ella decía
podía ser la misma experiencia que mi hija podría tener
Estas fotos muestran cada día de 2014 en Beijing
Solo cuando la calidad del aire es buena se me ocurría sacar a mi hija afuera
Pero cuantos días buenos hubo?
175 días fueron contaminados
Eso quiere decir que en 1 año, la mitad del tiempo no tengo otra elección
que dejarla en casa como una prisionera
Hace 10 años, el director de la agencia medioambiental me dijo,
“Xiaoyi es el microcosmos de Shanxi, Shanxi es el microcosmos de China.”
En solo una decada,
He visto sin poder hacer nada como esto ocurría
En Marzo-Abril de 2014
46 fotografias
Imágenes grabadas del cielo por 40 días consecutivos
Tianjin - 197 días con polución en 2014
Shenyang - 152 días con polución en 2014
Chengdu - 125 días de polución en 2014
Lanzhou - 112 días de polución en 2014
Shijiazhuang - 264 días de polución en 2014
Una vez vi una serie de TV llamada ”La cúpula" (Under the Dome en inglés)
Era sobre una pequeña ciudad que se queda de repente envuelta bajo una cúpula
Desconectada del mundo, sin salida
Y un día me entere que nosotros estamos viviendo en la misma realidad
A veces, cuando me levanto por la mañana
Veo a mi hija enfrente del balcón golpeando la ventana de cristal
Esa es su forma de decirme que quiere salir afuera
Creo, que un día me preguntará
Mama, ¿porqué me tienes encerrada dentro de casa?
¿Qué es lo que hay de verdad afuera?
¿Algo me hará daño?
Todo lo que he hecho este año
es contestar las preguntas que ella me preguntará en el futuro
¿Qué es la polución?
¿De donde viene?
¿Qué podemos hacer al respecto?
Entonces, ¿qué es la polución?
A veces, apago la luz
y quiero verla
Se que el PM2.5 está ahí
Son partículas en el aire con un diámetro de 2.5 milímetros
así que reflejan un montón de luz visible,
dejándonos en un mundo con poca visibilidad
Pero no puedo verlas
porque las partículas más pequeñas que el ojo puede ver son 20 veces más grandes
En otras palabras, es una lucha con un enemigo invisible
Solo hay una forma de verlas
Es esta
Esto es un dispositivo de medición de PM2.5
Le puse un filtro de muestras muy limpio
Y lo lleve durante 24 horas
26 deNoviembre, 2014 - AQI (Indice de Calidad del aire): 282
Así estaba el filtro cuando empezamos, verdad?
Después de 24 horas
se ve así
Si no hago nada para proteger a mi niña
ella aspirara todo esto
Cuando aspirara?
305.91 microgramos por metro cúbico
Pero ¿quién entiende este número? Sólo podemos compararlo
(Gráfica: Límites de la concentraciones de PM 2.5, media cada 24 horas)
Esta la OMS estándar para el máximo diario de PM2.5
Este es el estándar de EEUU
Este es el estándar de Europa
y este es el estándar de China
¿Cuando hemos aspirado en ese día?
Casi 5 veces el máximo diario de China
Aunque parece solamente un número alarmante
quería saber realmente que substancias habían en la muestra
El profesor Qiu Xinhua de la Universidad de Peking fue tan amable
de realizar esta prueba para mi
Estos son los resultados de su análisis
La muestra contiene 15 tipos de cancerígenos
incluyendo benzo [a] pireno, uno de los cancerígenos más potentes
¿Cuántas veces el estándar estaba allí?
14 veces el estándar del gobierno
No podía cree este número
Os acordáis del vídeo, cuando estaba en Xiaoyi
rodeada de plantas de carbón?
La cantidad de benzo[a]pireno que estaba respirando ahí
era solo 9 veces el estándar legal
Ahora, vivo en el centro de una ciudad internacional
Cuando miro alrededor, no puedo ver ninguna fábrica o chimenea
So how can it possibly be 14 times the legal limit?
Entonces, ¿como puede ser que sea 14 veces ele límite legal?
El profesor Qiu dudo de los resultados también
Me dijo “No puede ser posible que sea tan algo. Realizare otra el análisis.”
Me llamo al día siguiente y me dijo
“No hay errores, es 14 veces el límite.”
“Nuestro muestreo más amplio mostró
que hay gente cuya exposición era incluso mas grande que la tuya,20 veces el límite legal.”
Todos estos cancerígenos estaban en el filtro de  muestra que visteis antes
unido a una sustancia llamada de carbono negro
Es muy diminuta, solo 0.2 milímetros
Pero tiene una estructura de cadena, así si se desenrolla
2 gramos es el tamaño de un campo de basquet
Por esto, puede absorber muchas partículas de cancerígenos y metales pesados
Cuando carbon negro hay en China?
Esta es la estimación de la NASA desde 2009
Ese punto violeta y blanco es China
Nos esta sobre nosotros como un fantasma
Así que fui a la Universidad de Peking
Sabía que tenían un laboratorio para esos experimentos
Pregunte a un experto si podia hacer de voluntaria
“Si podían poner en una cámara cerrada con alta concentración de carbón negro
y observar y probar mi reacciones físicas,
así powder mostrar a todo el mundo los resultados.”
El dudo un momento y me contesto
“Perdón, no puedo hacer este experimento.”
Yo pregunte porque.
Me dijo, “Cada experimento requiere limites éticos académicos.
Estos límites previenen de daño extremo a los participantes.
No puedo realizar un experimento con estos límites
incluso si la concentración afuera is mayor que en la cámara cerrada."
"Para decirlo de otra manera, cada uno de nosotros
esta viviendo en una cámara experimental toda su vida
y no sabemos cual será el resultado de este experimento.”
La universidad de Beijing usa un sistema diferente
Ellos toman datos de como las personas reaccionan a la contaminación del aire directamente
Durante 1 año, participe en este experimento
Y descubrí
que tenía una inflamación crónica respiratoria y que pertenecía a grupo sensible
Las partículas finas impactan en el sistema respiratorio, exacerbando las inflamaciones de la traca respiratoria
y afectan al sistema cardíovacular entero
Pequeñas partículas se correlacionan con una mayor posibilidad de insuficiencia cardiaca debido a la reducción de suministro de sangre cardíaca
Yo no entiendo muy bien lo que significa la jerga médica
Por lo tanto, con la ayuda de los científicos
hicimos una animación para explicar el efecto
Yo soy PM 2.5
Tengo muchos hermanos y hermanas
Hidrocarbonatos policíclicos aromáticos y otros metales pesados
cada unoarmando
En el juego de atacar cuerpos humanos
Rara vez me fracaso
Escena 1: Fosa nasal
El Bello nasal y las mucosas pueden bloquear partículas grandes
El 90% de las partículas son mayores de 10 micras y son anuladas automáticamente
pero no pueden pararme
Escena 2: Garganta
El tracto respiratorio superior tiene cilios de menos de 10 micras de longitud
Vibran 20 veces por segundo, pero paso a través de ellos con facilidad
Los músculos suaves de la tráquea se irritan, contraen y
tratan de bloquearme, pero este acoso no puede pararme
Escena 3: Tracto respiratorio inferior
Aquí los bronquios se dividen en pequeños bronquiolos
Estas son las mejores pendientes de esquí para nosotros
Por el camino luchamos con leucocitos y linfocitos
Estas luchas causarán todos tipo de inflamaciones en el cuerpo humano
Nuestra tropa finalmente llega a su destino:
Los alveolos pulmonares
El pulmón humano cuenta con más de 300 millones de alveolos
Si bloqueamos los alveolos, el humanos no será capaz de respirar más
Sin embargo, nuestro más feroz enemigo está aquí: Los macrófagos
Su especialidad es devorar materia externa
y son conocidos como los barrenderos del cuerpo
Esta va a ser una batalla dura
Sin embargo, les superamos en número
Nuestro núcleo es complejo de quebrar y contenemos metales pesados tóxicos
Los macrófagos no pueden neutralizarnos a todos nosotros
y pueden ser fácilmente eliminados por sobredosis
Así es como el sistema inmune humano se desmantela
Tenemos otra fuerza especial:
partículas de menos de 0,5 micras
Una vez han llegado a los alevéolos, son suficientemente pequeñas para pasar a los vasos sanguíneos a través de las membranas
dañando el revestimiento de los vasos sanguíneos, forzando a las arterias a estrecharse
lo que produce una subida de la presión arterial y trombosis
incluso podemos entrar el centro de los cuerpos humanos
a través del sistema circulatorio pulmonar
y atacar tu corazón
causando enfermedades coronarias y aritmias
que producen ataques al corazón
Aterrorizáos, humanos
Estamos en cada respiración
Estas medidas han sido suministradas por la Academia China de Ciencias (CAS)
Está trama compleja demuestras
que a menudos que la concentración de PM2,5 crece,
la mortalidad humana también aumenta
muchas otras instituciones de investigación científica han observado la misma tendencia
El ex ministro de sanidad Chino Chen Zhu
ha calculados que el número de muertes prematuras causadas por
la polución del aire en China es
500.000 personas
En la batalla contra la humanidad,
las poblaciones más frágiles y vulnerables son
nuestros hijos y padres
Estos bebés tienen unos dos meses
Nunca han estado en el exterior
pero se les ha diagnosticado con neumonía
Están recibiendo terapia nebulizadora
Los padres de estos bebes me pidieron que fotografiara a sus hijos
sospechaban que sus hijos se pusieron enfermos debido a la falta de protección durante la niebla tóxica densa
El médico les dijo:
"Sólo puedo diagnosticar 'Neumonía por causa desconocida'"
debido a la falta de estudios epidemiológicos actualizados
Pero puedo deciros esta estadística:
En enero de 2013 durante la niebla tóxica densa
por todo el país
27 ciudades sufrieron crecidas exponenciales en las visitas a las unidades de urgencias
Una vez, las madres de mi comunidad hablaron sobre este evento
Una madre me preguntó:
"¿Cómo debería lidiar con la nube tóxica?"
¿Deberíamos dejar a nuestros hijos exponerse a la nube tóxica
tan pronto como sea posible para entrenarlos, y que así se acostumbren
¿y no estén en desventaja desde el primer momento?
Un experto médico de Los Ángeles,
una ciudad que una vez sufrió una extrema contaminación atmosférica, nos informó
sobre los riesgos de exponer los niños a la contaminación atmosférica
esperando que sean capaces de ajustarse a las condiciones:
No creo que tengamos ninguna información
que sugiera que exponiendo a los niños a la contaminación atmosférica
les va a ayudar a adaptarse.
Si los exponemos el primer día, perderán algunas funciones.
Si los exponemos el segundo día, no perderán la misma cantidad.
Pero eso no no es porque se hayan adaptado,
si no porque ya han perdido las funciones,
y ya están afectados.
Se ha mostrado en varios estudios a largo de todo el mundo,
que los niños en entornos más limpios crecen más rápido
que los niños que crecen en zonas más contaminadas.
El funcionamiento pobre de los pulmones en las etapas tempranas de la vida
es un indicativo de problemas pulmonares en el futuro.
or ello, hacer algo sobre el aire mientras un niño está creciendo
puede crear cambios en la vida de tu hijo.
Esto es abajo donde vivo
y tomé esta foto hace dos días durante una nube tóxica severa.
El AQI (Indice de Calidad del aire) ese día había superado los 500,
por encima del nivel "Nocivo" de contaminación
Sin embargo, los niños en la escuela básica de al lado
estaban en la calle jugando a la pelota, corriendo y jugando.
Mientras la gente hace ejercicio
respira entre cinco y diez veces más profundo de lo normal
cuando vi esto, me di cuenta del hecho de que
No podía proteger a mi hija siempre
Algún día tendrá que unirse al resto de la sociedad
y siempre tendrá que respirar
es algo inevitable
Y eso (PM2.5) esta siempre en cada respiración
Un adulto como nosotros respira aproximadamente 25000 veces al día
Al pasar el tiempo, esto se acumula ¿Qué sucede con estas sustancias dentro de nuestros pulmones?
Estamos muy agradecidos con un paciente y un doctor
en el Hospital de Cáncer de Beijing que nos permitieron filmar esta cirugía
Es un paciente en una etapa temprana de cáncer pulmonar
Mujer, 50 años
y trabaja en el departamento de contabilidad del hospital
Ella y su familia no tienen historial de fumadores
El siguiente vídeo fue filmado con el permiso de la familia del paciente y del hospital
Las siguientes escenas pueden resultar incomodas, por favor veánlas bajo su propia discreción
Dentro de la cavidad pulmonar
Todo el mundo respira en estos puntos negros
Incluídos nosotros
¿Esta persona fuma?
No, ella no es fumadora
Pero es de la ciudad de (censurado)
En su pueblo natal
La calidad del aire es realmente mala
Sí, no es nada limpio (allá)
Así que esto puede ser a causa de lo que hay en el aire
El color del ganglio linfático pulmonar - el acumulamiento de partículas conforme ha pasado el tiempo lo ha tornado completamente negro
En todo su cuerpo solo los ganglios linfáticos son negros
Esto se debe a que ha inhalado mucho polvo
El sistema linfático es crucial para el funcionamiento de nuestro sistema inmunológico
Yang Yue, Director del 2do Dept. Torácico del Hospital de Cáncer de la Universidad de Pekín
esto quiere decir que ayuda a nuestro sistema inmunológico a combatir las enfermedades
Cuando las manchas negras se acumulan sobre la superficie
¿afectan la habilidad de nuestro cuerpo para combatir células cancerígenas?
Puede ser que esto haya sobrecargado de más el sistema linfático
Este año la Organización Mundial de la Salud (OMS)
ha reportado que las enfermedades pulmonares crónicas
son unos de los factores de más alto riesgo del cáncer pulmonar
Podemos consolarnos con el hecho de
que este tipo de cirugía es muy exitosa
y el paciente puede hacer una recuperación completa
una vez que se hayan extraído los tumores
Después de haber extraído los ganglios linfáticos negros
el doctor se los entregó a la familia del paciente
Le preguntaron: “¿Porqué le dio cáncer a mi esposa?”
El respondío, “Sólo puedo decir que de acuerdo con mi experiencia clínica
sospecho que fue debido a la polución del aire”
(Conforme incrementa el número de partículas y deteriora la calidad del aire, también incrementa el riesgo de cáncer pulmonar, y las partículas han sido identificadas entre los principales cancerígenos en los humanos
Cuando me dijo esto yo tuve una pregunta
¿ No tiene el cáncer de pulmón un periodo de incubación
de por lo menos diez años?
Pero sólo empezamos a saber sobre la polución del aire apenas hace dos años ¿correcto?
Entonces ¿cómo es posible que haya causado  cáncer tan rápido?
Así que pedí un favor a la NASA
que me mandasen imágenes satelitales
del aire sobre el norte de China durante los últimos 10 años
Esto fue lo que conseguí
El aire sobre Beijing
Beijing en diciembre
El aire sobre el norte de China
Veamos lo 10 años atrás
El norte de China en el 2005
Pero no podía creerlo
Yo había estado viviendo bajo estos cielos en el norte de China durante ese tiempo
¿Cómo es que no me di cuenta que había polución en el aire por 10 años?
Así que busqué al jefe de la calidad del aire para las Olímpiadas de nuestro país
Un académico llamado Dr. Tang Xiaoyan
Ella me proporcionó esta gráfica
Es de 2004
Hace 11 años
Entonces, aún no monitoreámos los niveles de PM2.5
Pero tenemos los niveles de PM10
Me dijo que de acuerdo con estimaciones de entonces
Entonces
cuando estaba muy contaminado
PM2.5 pudieron haber alcanzado los 300-400
Hoy lo clasificaríamos como polución muy nociva
Le pregunté
¿Es posible que en realidad estaba tan ciega?
Yo estaba en Beijing en el 2004
Me dijo, ves esta imagen
¿Qué es eso?
Dije, es probablemente polución ¿Cierto?
¿Entonces cómo es que no sabía en ese entonces?
Me respondió, deberías ver
que titulares de noticias había entonces
“El Aeropuerto Internacional de Pekín experimenta la mayoría de los retrasos de los últimos años debido a la neblina” - 2 de Diciembre, 2004, Sina News
Entonces creíamos que era sólo neblina
Seguíamos llamándola “neblina”
Así que ví esta fotografía
Como ex-reportera
estaba muy arrepentida
porque todos esos años de reportera siempre pensaba que
estaba informando sobre polución por todo el país
Pero siempre pensé que
sólo se le llamaba polución cuando oía explosiones en las minas
it was only called pollution when I saw smoke from factory chimneys
sólo se llamaba polución cuando veía humo salir de las chimeneas de las fábricas
Nunca pensé que para nosotros que vivíamos en el centro de una ciudad
the sky we saw everyday
el cielo que veíamos todos los días
también tenía polución
Entonces ya no era reportera
Me había convertido ya en una espectadora
Pero aún tenía una pregunta
Si realmente era así
cuando era joven, cada familia
quemaba queroseno en sus estufas ¿no?
Cada noche nos
dormíamos y despertábamos con el olor a humo
¿Cómo es posible que entonces no se supiera de ninguna persona contrayendo cáncer de pulmón?
Seguí haciendo esta pregunta
hasta que conocí al profesor He Xingzhou
que ha estado investigando este tema por más de 30 años
Me dio un libro con información
This
Este
Un informe sobre la relación entre la polución del aire y las causas de fallecimiento en 26 ciudades chinas 1976-1981
Para que todo veamos claro
He puesto la conclusión aquí en la pantalla
Es muy simple
La polución de ese entonces
estaba ya relacionada con fallecimientos a causa del cáncer de pulmón
La polución de ese entonces se debía a la quema de carbón
Sólo que en ese entonces esos datos
eran considerados información reservada
No era que la gente entonces
no pudiera oler el humo sofocante
Pero el calor y la energía que proporcionaba el carbón
era más importante entonces
Alrededor de 1980,
había 3700 fábricas en Beijing
para un país mayoritariamente agropecuario, ansioso por desarrollarse
las chimeneas era una señal de progreso
Para algunas personas, son solo dos chimeneas
Para algunas personas, son referencias que te llevan a casa
No teníamos en absoluto experiencia o conciencia de la contaminación
Ni la capacidad para controlarla
Los principales contaminantes no tenían normas establecidas
Incluso la cantidad de carbón que quemábamos no está cerca de la que se quema ahora
La contaminación creada era enorme
En términos de niveles de PM 2.5
En 2006, la concentración media de PM2.5 fue mayor que la de hoy en día
Ese año China propuso el ahorro de energía y reducir las emisiones
Y el establecimiento de normas para el dióxido de azufre y otros contaminantes
Después, la contaminación del aire empezó a descender
Pero la cantidad de pequeñas partículas que afectaban a la visibilidad aumento
La cantidad de días extremadamente contaminantes aumentó
La gente empezó a encontrarse mal por la contaminación
El desarrollo económico ha aumentado la esperanza de vida en China
Y hoy hay más formas de curarse de las enfermedades
Pero el riego que viene de la contaminación del aire se ha vuelto obvia
En los últimos 30 años,
el índice de mortalidad de cáncer de pulmón en China aumentó en un 465%
Aunque fumar o el envejecimiento de la población
Son los principales factores de la estadística
El riesgo de desarrollar cáncer de pulmón proviene de las partículas finas
está recibiendo mayor atención
Monitorizar el nivel de PM2.5 empezó en el 2012
China puso en marcha su ¨plan de prevención de la contaminación del aire
Como los sueldos aumentaron y la información se hizo más transparente
las expectativas de la gente sobre el medio ambiente también aumentaron
Una persona
o incluso no una persona
Cómo debería vivir un organismo vivo?
Cuando el verano llega, se abren las puertas
el viento sopla
y el olor de las flores llena el aire
y los colores vuelven a la vida
Algunas veces cuando llueve
o cuando hay niebla
No puedes evitar que aspirar fuerte el aire en tus pulmones
y la sensación de pequeñas gotas de agua llenando los
No sólo frío penetrante, sino también puro y fresco
En otoño
puedes pasar unas tarde entera
con un ser querido y no hacer absolutamente nada
disfrutando del sol
En invierno
querrás ir fuera con tus hijos
cuando esté nevando
y ella sacará la lengua para atrapar copos de nieve
Tendrás que enseñarle
sobre la naturaleza y la belleza de la vida
Pero ahora...
Este año, todos los días cuando me levanto
lo primero que hago es
comprobar la calidad de aire (AQI) en mi móvil
Porque determinará mi dia entero
Y si dependo deun viento que viene del noroeste para vivir mi vida
Llevaré una mascarilla cuando salga a pasear
Llevaré una mascarilla cuando vaya a comprar
Llevaré una mascarilla cuando vea a mis amigos
Usaré una cinta para tapar
todos los huecos de la ventana y de la puerta de mi casa
Cuando llevo a mi hija a vacunar
Tengo miedo incluso cuando ella me sonríe
Realmente, no tengo miedo a la muerte
Solo que no quiero vivir así
Así que cuando alguien me pregunta
Porque estás haciendo esto?
Solo puedo decir
Esto en una batalla
entre la contaminación del aire y yo
¿de donde viene esta contaminación del aire?
Me gustaría saber de donde viene
Me gustaría entender qué está pasando realmente
Examiné una tira de muestras
bajo un microscopio
y observe como era
La contaminación no era la colección de partículas idénticas
que imaginaba que iba a ser
Es un mezcla de pequeñas cosas
y ser una mezcla lo hace más tóxico
así como permitir que se extienda más rápidamente
Los contaminantes puede reaccionar químicamente entre ellos
La Academia de Ciencia de China me explicó las fuentes de contaminación
la quema de carbón, aceite, de materiales orgánicos
industria, agricultura, fertilizantes químicos, emisión de polvo
Muchas de estas causas son antropogénicas en la naturaleza
Si analizamos estos factores
encuentras de donde viene la mayor contaminación
Esta es la conclusión
El 60% de PM2.5 en China viene de
la quema de carbón y petróleo
Es decir, la quema de combustibles fósiles
PM2.5 ha existido
antes incluso que los humanos
erupciones volcánicas
e incendios forestales emiten gran cantidad de partículas
Empezando cuando se descubrió como hacer fuego con madera
la actividad humana ha contribuido al PM 2.5
En el pasado, el uso de carbón en grandes cantidades
condujo a una grave contaminación
en Inglaterra  y Alemania
y cuando entramos la era del petróleo
la quema de petróleo condujo a serios problemas de contaminación en América y Japón
En este momentos hay aún muchos
países desarrollados en proceso de industrialización
India
Iran
Pakistán
Afganistán
Todos se enfrentan a problemas con la contaminación de la quema de combustibles fósiles
como lo hace China, el país que
más rápido se ha desarrollado en el mundo
Su gran tamaño
ha llevado a la quema de grandes cantidades de ambos tipos de combustibles fósiles
Cuánto fuel estamos actualmente quemando?
Podemos verlo en el año 2014
Los números representan
la cantidad de fuel que ha sido quemado alrededor del mundo
Puedes ver como brilla China
Esa zona blanca y roja brillante
ese es nuestro país (China)
De la imagen podemos ver que
China quema 3 o 4 veces más combustible fósil que Europa
Hemos quemado demasiado combustible fósil
Pero lo más sorprendente
que los contaminantes de carbón y petróleo pueden tener
reacciones químicas a gran escala.
Wang Yuesi, Du Jiming y Tang Xiaoyan
Todavía no hemos tratado con la contaminación de carbón
y ahora la contaminación por vehículos se han añadido a la mezcla
Ahora, la contaminación en China
es básicamente una superposición de estos dos tipos de contaminación
Todos los tipos de partículas
reacción entre ellas en el aire.
El movimiento del aire ha disminuido
pero la misma cantidad de contaminantes permanecen
Desafortunadamente las cosas son así
estos contaminantes no se han extendido
sino que están reaccionando entre ellos
esto es a lo que llamamos partículas secundarias
Contaminantes complejos
absorben
adhieren
chocan
funden
Son juntos una mezcla
No tenemos ninguna forma de cambiar las condiciones naturales
sólo podemos cambiarnos a nosotros mismos
y la manera de hacerlo
es reduciendo emisiones
Todo el mundo necesita quemar carbón y petróleo, ¿no?
¿Así que qué tiene de malo nuestro carbón?
¿Sabes cuánto carbón ha quemado China?
En 2013
Ya habíamos quemado 3.6 billones de toneladas
¿Pero sabes cuánto
han quemado todos los demás países del mundo juntos?
Hemos quemado más carbón
que el resto del mundo
La última vez que un país tuvo este tipo de consumo
fue Inglaterra en 1860
Pero como consecuencia,
pagaron un precio muy alto
En lo profundo de la minas abandonadas en el sur de Gales
yace el corazón de la edad industrial de Inglaterra
Que solía ser el motor
del imperio más poderoso del mundo
Pero también llevó a este país
a un desastre espeluznante y negro
Estas cuatro chimeneas tienen 103 metros de altura
Son símbolos de la era industrial de Inglaterra
Cuando se construyó la planta de electricidad de Battersea en 1930
quemaba aproximadamente 10,000 toneladas de carbón por semana
para producir un quinto de la electricidad de la ciudad de Londres
Se podría decir que Londres comía carbón para sobrevivir
trenes, barcos,
hierro, acero, objeto del día a día
En todo Londres, era como si
millones de micro-volcanes hicieran erupción todos a la vez
Debido a que quemaban grandes cantidades de carbón de baja calidad
y emitían polución de baja altitud
la cantidad de polución de chimeneas familiares
equivalía al doble de contaminación de la industria
Y paulatinamente
Londres se cubrió por completo de hollín
La gente se veía forzada a usar máscaras para ir a la escuela
Y usaba máscaras para ir de compras
Usaba mascarillas para pasear a sus perros
E incluso para besar
El día del desastre fue
el 5 de diciembre de 1952
un frente frío se expandió a lo largo del Canal de la Mancha
y cubrió todo el valle del río Támesis
Lo cual mantuvo al smog debajo de las nubes,
y no permitió que se disipara
Un humo venenoso cubría todo
Los habitantes tenían dificultades para respirar el pesado aire
La gente que caminaba por la calle no podía siquiera ver sus propios pies
Se necesitaba un ciego para llevarte a casa
La policía de tránsito usaba grandes lámparas para iluminarse a sí mismos
y prevenir que los atropellen
Todo Londres estaba callado
Sólo se podían ver ambulancias, ya que debían de llevar
a quienes sufrían peligro de perder la vida al hospital
Pero cuando estaban en camino dependían
de que personas con antorchas les mostrarán el camino
Al final, 12.000 personas murieron en la contaminación
Se tomaron muestras de los pulmones de los muertos
y de las pruebas se confirmó que la causa de muerte había sido
exposición prolongada a carbón negro, una consecuencia de quemar carbón
así como una sobre exposición de corto plazo a una alta concentración
de partículas finas que contenían metales pesados
La Coalición por el Aire Limpio calculó que
la concentración de contaminación en Londres en ese momento
podría haber sido superior a la polución actual de China por un margen amplio
Aunque no se medía PM2.5 en el momento
Durante el Gran Smog
la concentración de dióxido de sulfuro
era 190 veces el estándar de la OMS
y excedía el estándar de China en relación con el PM2.5
por una orden de magnitud
En la década de 1960, después del Gran Smog de Londres,
otros países empezaron a reducir el uso que hacían del carbón
Pero ese fue también el momento en que China inició sus reformas económicas
Un país que había estado cerrado por tantos años
necesitaban desesperadamente cantidades enormes de energía para desarrollarse
Y buscó aquella energía en el carbón
Esta curva muestra el crecimiento del carbón como fuente de energía
India está en un camino parecido
En el futuro cercano, India será el segundo consumidor de carbón del mundo
Pero hasta el momento, India no ha impuesto estándares
para las emisiones de contaminantes importantes en sus industrias
India también es un país que sufre de contaminación aérea muy severa
Pero ¿dónde se termina usando todo el carbón en China?
Veamos las 3.6 mil millones de toneladas de carbón que se consumieron en 2013
380 millones de toneladas fueron quemadas en Beijing, Tianjin y Hebei
De esas 380 millones de toneladas, 300 millones de toneladas
se quemaron en Hebei
Yo estaba muy sorprendida porque
Siempre pensé que éramos nosotros los de Shanxi los que quemábamos más carbón
¿Cuándo empezó Hebei a quemar tanto carbón?
El Dr. Hao Jiming de la Universidad de Qinghua me preguntó
¿Has visto los rankings mundiales de la producción de carbón y acero?
Me dijo que China está en primer lugar
Y Hebei, en el segundo
Tangshan, en el tercero
Y Estados Unidos en el cuarto (risas)
También dijo que, originalmente,
Tangshan mintió para quedar en el quinto lugar (risas)
¿Conlleva el uso de más carbón e industrialización necesariamente a más contaminación?
Otros países producen acero
He said
Me dijo,
Lo entenderas si vas a Tangshan
Así que, en octubre pasado
en conjunto con el MEP del Centro de Supervisión del Norte de China
Visitamos Tangshan, armados con drones
para ver las condiciones reales
Zhang Dawe - MEP del Buró de Supervisión Ambiental
¿Puedes ver el humo que emerge de allí?
No hay claridad debido a la gran cantidad de humo
La inspección visual de las emisiones desde la fábrica resultó ser imposible
El clima ahora dificulta ver con claridad
La inspección de los drones falló debido al intenso smog
Mira detrás a ver si alguien nos está siguiendo
El MEP visitó, sin anunciarse, la fábrica
Este olor asfixiante de dióxido de sulfuro debe ser el humo
Que se puede ver en estos momentos
hay mucho humo que se cuela por las esquinas
Este humo
se emite sin ningún control o supervisión
y se queda en la atmósfera
Porque no estas usando filtros de polvo?
Estamos usándolos
Entonces, porque hay tanto humo?
Están funcionando, mira están llenos
Dios mío, mira abajo
Voy abajo a ver
Esto es lo más peligroso que he visto en mi carrera, en mi vida
Dios mío, es aterrador
Para, para, para!
Alguien se ha caído
El que se cayó es el Inspector Zhang Dawei
del Buró MEP del Norte de China
Todos estábamos asustados en ese momento
porque no había luces ni señales en la fábrica
Había un huevo de 3 metros lleno de acero y cemento
Dawei quiso bajar y medir las emisiones en ese sitio
y se cayó
Por suerte, no se hirio gravemente
así que lo llevamos de vuelta al hospital en Beijing esa noche
Pero lo que más me sorprendió cómo nos esforzamos
tantos problemas y aunque encontramos clara evidencia de la contaminación
al final, la compañía no fue multada
Pregunté a Dawei porque
Me dijo,  “Deberías preguntar a tu jefe”
Xiong Yuehui - Departamento MEP de Ciencia, Technologia y Estandars
Más del 60% de las compañías de acero
no han completado el proceso de certificación
No se preocupan de informarse de las leyes de protección ambiental
sino que intentan parar el proceso de certificación
Parán el proceso de certificación aunque la producción sea legal o no
Saben que no hay alternativa, así que actúan con total imprudencia
No tienen licencia para sus operaciones
Los inspectores ni siquiera quieren ir o tocar esta industria
Puedes realmente cerrarlas (empresas del acero)?
Puedes realmente pararlas?
Porque no podemos cerrarlas?
Debes de estar de broma
Sabes cuantos trabajos creas cuando produces 10 millones de acero?
100.000 trabajos
¿Qué tan importante es la industria del acero en Hebei?
Es tan importante que no puedes simplemente cerrarlas
Esta provincia tiene una enorme cantidad de industria pesada dispersada,
consumiendo grandes cantidades de carbón
sin controles de contaminación eficaces
y las industrias no pueden ser obligadas a cerrar
¿Cuales son las consecuencias de todo esto?
Tengo un buen amigo, Hao
que también es colega de News Investigation
Ella es la que me acompañó hace 10 años
a Shanxi a informar de la contaminación local
Ella sabía que yo era de Linfen (en Shanxi) y
a veces me enviaba bromeando algunas fotos
Me decía, “He oído que tu ciudad natal es ahora
el lugar más contaminado del planeta”
Me quedé sin palabras
Pero hace 10 años le envié esta foto
Veámosla de más cerca
Celebramos que el aire de nuestra ciudad
no es más entre las 74 ciudades más contaminadas de China (risas)
Esta pancarta es real en Hebei
Por desgracia, esta ciudad fue una vez más la ciudad más contaminada en la lista (3 meses después)
Pero esta broma me pone triste
Y para gente que  vive en Beijing
cada vez que el viento sopla del sur
la contaminación de Hebei se mueve con el
No puedes mantener el aire fuera con un muro
Eso es lo que quieren decir cuando dicen
“Respiremos y vivamos juntos”
Tengo, otro amigo, se llama Fan
Ella es de Jiangsu
Yo solía discutir con Hao
sobre que provincia es más contaminada, si Hebei o Shanxi
Fan solía decir,
"Bueno, nosotros los sureños en realidad no tenemos ningún tipo de contaminación"
Ahora el este de China también tiene contaminación extrema
Pero Fan estaba sorprendida
Ella decía, “Es imposíbe,
al menos la contaminación del este de China no tiene nada que ver con el carbón
porque nunca he visto carbón en mi vida”
Cierto
le mostré esta imagen
Estas son las fábricas de hierro y acero cerca de su casa
Estas centrales de electricidad cerca de tu casa
Estas las fábricas de cemento cerca de tu casa
En Jiangsu, hay una central de electricidad cada 30 km cuadrados
y cual es el estado actual de emisiones de esas compañías?
Aquí podemos ver las emisiones en tiempo real
Los puntos rojos muestran las emisiones excediendo los estándares
Si nos acercamos,
podemos ver cuantas compañías en el este
están emitiendo contaminantes excediendo los límites
Entre ellas, Shanghai
que quema un montón de carbón sola
esta quemando la mayor cantidad de carbón por metro cuadrado
de todas las ciudades
10 Kg de carbón se queman
por cada metro cuadrado de tierra
Cuales son las consecuencias de quemar tanto carbón?
Un problema que nunca pense
es que el carbón de alta calidad será cada vez más escaso
Cierto?
Entonces qué debemos hacer?
Carbón de más baja calidad será más común
¿Qué tan bajo puede ser la calidad?
Este el carbón común
Y este, es carbón también?
Al principio no podía pensar que era carbón
será madera,
todavía se puede ver la textura y los fósiles en la parte superior
Pero la gente de las fábricas de lavado de carbón me dijeron que
pero es también carbón
Se llama lignito, o lignito
Es el carbón más joven del mundo
Es tan joven que el nivel de carbonización es extremadamente baja
Cuando se quema, la mitad de ella
se convertirá en negro humo, flotando en el aire
¿Cuánto lignito hemos utilizado?
Este es un gráfico de la producción de carbón marrón en los últimos años
Y estas son las consecuencias
El 21 de octubre de 2013
en el primer día que la calefacción urbana se encendió en Harbin
Había tanto humo que
que el índice superó PM2.5 1000
Así fue como la gente de Harbin pasaron ese día
Hablé con la gente de la oficina de protección ambiental de Harbin
y mencioné que oí autobuses se perdieron durante esos dos días
Él sonrió amargamente y dijo
No importan los autobuses, incluso nuestro propio director de la oficina se perdió (risas)
Nos dijo que cuando estaba supervisando los sitios ese día.
nadie lo reconoció debido al smog.
El smog en Harbin
fue ocasionado por la quema
de más de 20 millones de toneladas de carbón marrón.
Adicionalmente, en el 2013, varios cientos de miles de plantas de carbón como esta a lo largo de China
no cumplían con ningún estándar ambiental
y no estaban reguladas en modo alguno.
El carbón era quemado
y las sustancias contaminantes eran emitidas
y liberadas hacia la atmósfera.
Cuando miras abajo desde el cielo
es como si 12 millones de personas estuviesen
enterradas bajo cemento.
No obstante, el empleo de carbón no significa necesariamente polución.
Alemania también emplea carbón marrón,
pero allá primero limpian y lavan el carbón marrón para mejorar su calidad.
El carbón puede ser limpiado,
y, de hecho, los británicos lavan el 95% de su carbón.
¿Y cómo es en China?
Aquí lavamos menos de la mitad de nuestro carbón.
La otra mitad, varios cientos de millones de toneladas de carbón
contenían el prácticamente inútil, altamente contaminante e ineficiente
material llamado polvo.
Pero lo transportamos en trenes y camiones
alrededor del mundo y lo quemamos en las estufas de nuestras cocinas.
Y (ese polvo) es completamente inútil.
El resultado es que
la mayor parte del carbón marrón se quema en las casas.
Incluso en las áreas urbanas de China
la cuarta parte de la población quema carbón marrón.
No queman tanto carbón,
sólo es 20 % del total en el país,
pero el dióxido de azufre que emiten
equivale a las emisiones de todas las centrales eléctricas (de China) combinadas.
Así de grande es la diferencia que lavar el carbón puede hacer.
Lo más preocupante es que (el carbón no lavado) es altamente tóxico.
En Beijing, el nivel de toxicidad del PM2.5 durante el invierno
es mucho más alto que en el verano.
Su contenido carcinógeno en invierno
es 25 veces mayor que en verano.
¿Por qué el PM 2.5 es tan tóxico en invierno?
Principalmente porque la gente quema más “carbón chatarra”
Esta clase de carbón emite cantidades masivas de cacerinógenos.
Por varios años la población china
ha venido sufriendo las consecuencias de quemar “carbón chatarra”.
En Xuanwei (Yunnan) hay un pueblo llamado Hutou.
Debido a la quema de “carbón chatarra” (el pueblo) ahora tiene
uno de los mayores índices de cáncer de pulmón en el mundo.
Esta persona está en una fase avanzada del cáncer de pulmón.
Está tosiendo sangre.
Se sentía muy débil para espantar a los mosquitos,
así que le pidió alguien poner papel matamoscas encima de su cuerpo.
Este anciano fue fotografiado junto con toda la gente cercana a él
que perdió la vida debido al cáncer de pulmón en años recientes.
Hay incluso familias enteras que han fallecido debido a este mal.
Siempre oímos decir que China es todavía un país en vías de desarrollo
y que la protección del medio ambiente es un lujo que no podemos permitirnos.
Pero frecuentemente son los más pobres
quienes sufren más debido a la polución.
Son quienes tienen mayores posibilidades de ser perjudicados
y cuyas voces necesitan más ser escuchadas.
Son quienes más necesitan ayuda.
Estos últimos años, nuestro consumo de carbón ha sido extremadamente alto.
Como resultado, la calidad del carbón que usamos ha disminuido.
Además no lavamos nuestro carbón
y casi no hay controles sobre las emisiones.
Este es el resultado.
Los lugares de China
con mayor consumo de carbón
también tienen las mayores concentraciones de PM 2.5.
La forma más fácil de limpiar nuestro ambiente
sería reducir nuestro consumo de carbón a menos de 2 mil millones de toneladas.
Ello garantizaría cielos azules.
Si no podemos alcanzar dicha meta,
podemos tratar de centralizar la quema de carbón
y reemplazar la de “carbón chatarra” con el empleo de centrales eléctricas de carbón.
Como siguiente paso,
si aún no podemos lograr mejorar el ambiente,
podemos intentar lavar el “carbón chatarra” que usamos.
Si se lava todo el “carbón chatarra”, ¿cuál sería el efecto sobre las emisiones?
Como mínimo reduciría nuestras emisiones a la mitad.
Actualmente, podemos realizar dos cambios
Primero, debemos reducir el consumo de carbón
o podemos lavar nuestro carbón.
El Artículo 23° de la Ley de Protección de la Atmósfera
señala que el gobierno promueve el lavado y la mejora en la calidad del carbón,
la reducción del contenido de polvo y azufre en el carbón ,
y restricciones en las extracción de carbón con alto contenido de polvo y azufre.
“1° de los Diez artículos sobre protección de la atmósfera”:
Deben renovarse los pequeños incineradores de carbón,
acelerando la des-sulfurización y la reducción de componentes de nitrógeno y polvo.
En 2014, el PM se redujo 11.1% de su nivel máximo en 74 ciudades,
pero sólo 8 ciudades alcanzaron los estándares fijados por el gobierno.
Si pudiésemos implementar eficazmente todas las medidas de protección ambiental vigentes,
sólo las que tenemos actualmente, y hacerlas cumplir al 100%,
nuestras emisiones de polvo y dióxido de azufre
disminuirían en un 60% respecto a su nivel actual,
nuestras emisiones de óxido de nitrógeno serían un 35% más bajas.
Para solucionar el problema ambiental en China,
primero, necesitamos tener una mejor gestión,
segundo, necesitamos una gestión todavía mejor,
tercero, necesitamos una aún mejor gestión.
El presidente Xi Jinping dijo:
“La dignidad de las leyes depende de su cumplimiento”.
China necesitó 30 años
para completar un proceso de industrialización
que tomó cien años en otros países.
Por tanto, por encima de la polución producida por el carbón,
tenemos que además hacer frente
a la polución generada por el petróleo.
¿Así que qué pasa con nuestro petróleo?
La mayoría es quemado por automóviles.
En diez años, el número de automóviles en China
ha aumentado aproximadamente en 100 millones.
Fijándonos específicamente en Beijing en el 2010,
¿cuántos automóviles se añadieron sólo ese año?
800.000 más.
¿Qué significan 800000 automóviles más?
Si todos esos vehículos fuesen colocados en fila de un extremo a otro, se extenderían de Beijing a Shenzen.
y de vuelta a Beijing.
Ese ha sido el incremento de un año.
El resultado es el siguiente:
la principal fuente de PM2.5 dentro de Beijing
son esos vehículos.
Pero hay otra ciudad que me sorprendió.
Esta ciudad está bajo la niebla más de 200 días al año.
Pueden adivinar qué ciudad es,
¿cuál de ésta?
Miremos otra foto
¿Qinghai dicen?
¿Qingdao?
Hangzhou
Honestamente, estoy tan concertada como ustedes.
Porque siempre pensé
que este era el escenario de la lluvia brumosa descrita en tantos poemas famosos.
Más tarde llamé a la Agencia de Protección Ambiental de Hangzhou
y me confirmaron aquel dato.
Ello se debe a que la tasa de propiedad de automóvil por habitante en Hangzhou
es la más alta entre todas las ciudades de China.
En promedio, hay un carro por cada dos habitantes.
Así que los vehículos de Hangzhou
contribuyen a cerca del 40% de la contaminación del aire en ella.
Do more cars necessarily mean more pollution?
Here’s a question we often hear
Aren’t there more cars in Tokyo than in Beijing?
Why don’t we see such severe pollution in Tokyo?
This is the explanation given by the Beijing Municipal Commission of Transport:
More than 90% of Tokyo's residents commute by rail
Less than 6% of them drive
What about in Beijing?
34% of Beijing residents drive cars
And they drive in the city center, usually stuck in traffic jams
When they are stuck their cars are idling
which doubles the rate of emissions
And when they brake, even more heavy metals are released
So every day during rush hour in Beijing
how much PM2.5 is emitted in one hour
within the 6th ring?
One ton
How many Beijing residents would choose to drive
if they are going somewhere within 5km?
Close to half
12% of all residents
would drive within 2km
And 7%
would drive within 1km
How far is 1km?
That’s a trip to the supermarket
or greengrocer's
Do we really love driving so much?
Perhaps a few of us do
But there can’t be so many irrational people, right?
My family owns a car, but after our child was born we made a rule
basically we would only drive for our parents, our kid
or when we go to the airport or hospital
When my husband goes to work every day, he rides a bicycle
This is how you ride a bicycle
in front of our apartment building
That’s the only way to ride
Why?
This is our bicycle lane
It’s almost always full of cars
Beijing has over 5 million vehicles
but only half of them have a parking space
But no car can park in the air
so you find them in bicycle lanes
and on sidewalks
That’s how they park
Of course, humanity is the same throughout the world
Without regulations, this can happen anywhere
Let’s check London
It seems they also parked like this in the old days
then the parking meters were installed
and they parked like this
Then London raised its parking fee and congestion charge
so they parked like this
A few days ago, I heard that people are trying the same thing in Shenzhen
they started to charge high parking fees
Then the folks in Shenzhen parked like this (laughter)
The same thing happened in Tokyo 50 years ago
It’s not that easy
It took them a long time
to clear the cars out of the way one by one
This is a test of meticulous city management.
Car-lovers have another question
As this photo shows
there are no vehicles in Beijing at midnight, are there?
Why is the pollution still so severe?
Is it really caused by cars?
This question also troubled me for a long time
Until the Chinese Academy of Sciences showed me this chart
Before every dawn in Beijing
There’s always a peak in pollution
It shows up consistently every day
At this peak, carbon emissions are about twice as high
as the peak in the afternoon on the same day
So what exactly is this?
I wanted to know the answer as well
So we went to Yanqing district of Beijing
Yanqing - Kangzhuang Toll Station, 2:30am 11 October 2014
Inspector: Halt!
Vehicle type: Futian Aoling
Displayed emissions standard: National Standard 4
This truck doesn't have the basic equipment for a Standard 4
Chai: So in fact it's not a Standard 4 vehicle
Driver: So what should I do?
Driver: I just bought this new truck
This is my environmental protection label
It was issued this year
Random inspection of another vehicle
Vehicle type: Chang'an Kaima
Displayed emissions standard: National Standard 3
What does 3.29 mean?
It’s above the limit
This is even beyond Standard 1
So it has no emission control device at all?
No, basically no emission control at all
He has the green label
It says Standard 3
Who issued it?
Hebei Province Department of Environmental Protection
When I bought it they said it was Standard 3
How could I know? I was just buying a truck
Finally, the car was not given an on the spot fine
His truck is on the green channel
It's carrying eggs, milk, and oil
It’s part of the city’s supply system
According to the regulations, we should not penalize this truck
Li Kunsheng, Director of Beijing Municipal Environmental Protection Bureau, Vehicular Emissions Department
Fake cars are common
Or if we put it in more serious terms, fake cars are everywhere
It's a secret kept within the automotive industry
90% of basic environmental protection devices are not installed
So how does that play out in terms of emissions?
If 30,000 [noncompliant] vehicles enter the city
It's equivalent to several million [compliant] vehicles on the road at night
What kind of emissions result if emission control devices are not used?
The quantity of particulate emissions
from just one vehicle [with no safeguards]
Is 500 times the emissions from a vehicle of National Standard 4
Diesel cars do not make up a big proportion of vehicles
It’s similar to the case of scrap coal
There are not many
Only 17% of all cars are diesel
but their emissions of nitrogen oxides
make up 70% of all vehicle emissions
and as for their emission of primary particles
relative to all vehicles?
99%
There's an even scarier aspect to this too
The particulates in diesel vehicle emissions
have exceptionally high toxicity
PAHs are carcinogens
But diesel vehicles emit PAHs on steroids
Nitro-PAHs, which are an order of magnitude more carcinogenic
When I saw those drivers of diesel vehicles in Yanqing
I realized that they themselves are the biggest victims of their own diesel emissions
They are a group at very high risk for cancer
Besides, it seems fairly unreasonable to punish these people
They spent their own money
They bought vehicles with legal certificates
issued by the government
What reason do we have to fine them?
If we want to blame someone
shouldn’t we start with those
responsible for manufacturing these fake vehicles?
Chai: Could you explain why
the emission devices weren't installed during production?
Boss: Well, there are trucks for export
exporting to Africa and other places
There are also National Standard 1 and 2
and European Standard 1 and 2 and 0 as well
And some African ones
But your trucks have National Standard 4 labels on them
Well... perhaps they... export... like if they export
They are sold for export
Ummm... so that's how it happened
You mean you put the wrong labels on by mistake?
Yeah, maybe they stuck, stuck, something of their own
Someone wants the cars
So, so, so, we sold them (laughter)
I don’t know how our African brothers would feel after hearing this
A business always has its rationalizations
and reasons
But what makes me curious is
for more than ten years
if such fake manufacturers are so common and widespread,
and are known by the supervisory departments
why aren't they dealt with?
Don’t we have laws?
Don’t we have regulations
to recall defective automotive products?
Such products can surely be recalled, can't they?
However, from 2004 to today
how many times has this law been applied
to these kinds of vehicles?
Not even once
Why?
This is the answer I got
only when the defects pose unreasonable danger
toward the safety of people or their property
can the product be recalled
They say
leaving environmental protection devices out of manufacturing
has nothing to do with safety
It won’t kill anyone
so there’s no reason for a recall
Then do we have the right to fine the manufacturers or make them destroy their products?
We do
The “Atmospheric Pollution Prevention Act” states that:
You can make these factories stop their illegal production
You can fine them
You can also confiscate and destroy their products
More than ten years have passed since 2002
How many times has this law been used?
Not even once
Why?
This is the answer I got
This law can only be enforced by the departments with the legal right of supervision
Everyone says
I don’t know which department that is
Since there are only a few departments related to automotive management
I just called them one by one
First I asked the Ministry of Environmental Protection
They said:
As far as we know, it’s not us
Then I asked the Ministry of Industry and Information Technology
They say: It’s definitely not us
Then I asked the General Administration of Quality Supervision and Inspection, they said:
It should be all three of us
I think they do have a reason to be confused
Why doesn’t the law
just clarify who is in charge of this management?
I had to turn to the National People’s Congress
So I called the NPC
And this was their reply:
The issue of this law's execution is indeed unclear
This is a very rare case in our legislative process
Why would it exist nowhere else but in Article 53 of the Law on Atmosphere?
Ding Yan - Director of MEP Vehicular Pollution Research Institute
We asked them (NPC) back then
Why did you write the Law on Atmosphere like this?
Why don’t you just let us take charge of it?
They replied that because when they were making this law
many departments opposed it
saying that the MEP should not be in charge
so the bill could not pass
In the end the NPC had to use a vague term to make it pass
So it says that only departments with executive authority can enforce this law
It sounds like all three departments are responsible for supervision
But in reality we cannot control it
Their certificates are all valid
so are the vehicles' types
The MEP issues them green labels
of National Standard 4
but not a single department actually goes out and looks at the cars
which are in fact only up to Standard 1
If you (at the MEP) assert you have legal authority, no one can deny that
So why don't you just execute the law?
The MEP is indeed suspected of not doing its best, I admit this
The situation is that we didn’t pursue this issue further
So after so many years your law enforcement powers are still completely toothless?
Nowadays I don't dare open my mouth out of fear that people will see I have no teeth.
That’s the awkward thing about the MEP's situation.
This isn't just awkward for the MEP
Truck companies are also in an awkward position
The truck company with fake emissions stickers said
If the MEP can enforce the law
and impound those “fake” trucks
I guarantee we would build “real” trucks the very next day
Otherwise, if we build "real" trucks
and others build "fake" trucks
we would be bankrupt tomorrow
So I asked Ding Yan, do you think this perspective is reasonable?
He said “Yes”
Not enforcing the law forces people to cheat
The truck company owner also said
National Standard 4 has already been set and it applies to all new vehicles
But National Standard 4 compliant fuel is still scarce
and the fuel quality is not as high as it should be
When we were in Yanqing
and randomly checked this diesel truck
The diesel gas came from Beijing
and was expected to be of high quality, the highest level in China
But when the diesel test results came out,
the (sulfur content) was 25 times higher than European, Japanese, and US diesel
That's the top level of quality
What about the quality of our gasoline?
This is a table I got from Chinese Research Academy of Environmental Science
This table pains me every time I look at it
because I cannot understand it at all
Fortunately they gave me the conclusion
This shows our national fuel quality is
normally two or three grades lower than fuel found in developed countries.
If we can raise our national fuel quality by just one grade
we can reduce emissions by 10%
It seems like we have some good fuel available in China
We have Standard 4 and higher quality fuel
but these only make up 3% of China's total fuels
This is Hangzhou's problem
Hangzhou has money and
wants to buy high quality fuel
But until 2013 there was no high quality fuel available
Even after a huge effort
the best you can manage is Standard 3 fuel
Even in Beijing, it looks like our sulfur content
is on the same level as Europe's
on the same level as America's
But look at the four items in this box
These cryptic figures carry a hidden danger
They either
increase oxidants in the atmosphere
creating more fine particulates
or increase toxicity
The last item is increasing evaporative pressure
It increases the rate of gasoline evaporation into the air
I originally thought, really, how much can it possibly evaporate?
Then the CRAES expert told me
look at this clip
This is filmed with an infrared camera
If gas stations don’t install
a part on the nozzle to recapture gasoline vapor
then this is how much can evaporate
1.5 grams for each liter of gasoline will go into our atmosphere
The gas in the tanks of the cars we all drive also evaporates in the same way
How strong is the evaporative power?
In Beijing, more airborne hydrocarbons come from evaporation
than from car emissions
And these substances are a major component of PM2.5
So why don’t we make the fuel cleaner right away?
The petrochemical industry told us this
“The national standard is set too low.”
This sentence seems reasonable
How could you reasonably require companies to produce
fuel that's better than the official standard? Right?
Then I asked the MEP and CRAES
the people involved in setting the standard
Why don't you set the standard higher?
This is the answer he gave me
The standards subcommittee (Petroleum Fuel and Lubricant Technology Committee)
Is actually mostly... yes, mostly made up of
people from the oil industry
About 67%
The full standards committee (National Petroleum Fuel and Lubricant Technology Committee)
has even more, in the full committee, it's almost...
over 90%, as I recall are people from this industry
The secretariat of the full committee is also located in the petrochemical industry
Then the head of this standards committee
He's also a member of the petrochemical industry
I used to think
you guys (in Environmental Protection) had a veto right
Yeah, you'd think so, right?
(Since we're in) environmental protection?
This dark joke from Yue Xin
left a very deep impression on me
He said, “The only time I felt like I even existed
was when I came in the door
and I wrote my name on the sign-in sheet
Because before, I didn’t even have a vote.”
He said he and his colleagues will do everything they can
to push for better fuel quality
But the oil fuel industry has always explained it like this:
Most of the fuel in our country
is imported from the Middle East, right?
Well then, most oil from Iran, for example, is high in sulphur
In Tehran, they themselves are also facing
problems caused by poor-quality fuel
The smog there is severe
But Iran's problem is
they don’t have the skills to improve fuel quality
Chinese companies, on the other hand, do have these techniques
Where is the split between government and industry?
Money
From Standard 3 to Standard 4
the MEP says 7 cents per liter is enough
The industry says: no
Give me 50 cents
I say, both of you can sit down and show the expenses
and calculate it
Calculate how much it would be, it's a simple thing
He had another wry smile
Don’t say it's me, go ask the National Development and Reform Commission Economic Department
and see if they know
(Source: Anonymous NDRC official)
You can't control it.
Say you have an only child
And this child is learning bad behavior
As his mother, what can you do?
All you can do is give him one good beating
You can't  beat him everyday
Somebody else may have 10 kids
they won't make trouble
They are right in front of you
They don’t pay us any mind
These deputy-level units
What can you do about it?
Are they going to pay any mind to you?
If your price department doesn't raise the price this year
next year they'll be at your door
Are you going to raise it or not?
If you don't, I'll cut off the supply
That's what they say
I didn't know whether to trust these things the MEP and NDRC said
Is it the truth?
Does it have any basis in reality?
So I had to verify it
I reached out to the Head of the National Oil Fuel Standard Committee
and former Chief Engineer at China Petrochemical Corporation (Sinopec)
Mr. Cao Xianghong
Asking if I can meet him to chat
And ask a few questions
He agreed
First Question: Why has the process of setting fuel standards been led by the oil industry?
If the majority of participants come from industry
This might be against the best interest of the public
When convening a committee to set petroleum product standards
You shouldn't be looking for
someone who doesn't understand the oil refining business
People from the MEP don’t understand it?
The MEP, no, I don't believe they understand
Second Question: Who should set the standard?
If you set a standard
then when the time comes to improve it, you say it's impossible
Then when the deadline arrives, you say you cannot provide fuel
Now you may have all sorts of reasons for this, but people may not believe you
But if Sinopec doesn’t take the lead in drafting this
who else is there to draft it?
Well, for example, in some countries
first, their environmental protection agencies have people who understand the industry
Yes
Second, before they submit the draft
they take plenty of time with industry people to understand, communicate and debate
At the very end, their health reports, economic reports, these are all provided in full to the committee
And then through an open, public process
They let everyone judge it for themselves
And they all have opportunities to express their opinions and debate with one another
If it's done with this method, do you think you could consider accepting that?
I could accept that
I've wanted to give up this Standards Committee chairmanship for quite a long time
Really?
Really
People on the outside say, “You're too partial to Sinopec.”
But then Sinopec says, “Stop biting the hand that feeds you.”
You can't satisfy everyone
Third Question: Why won't you publicize the costs of upgrading our fuel?
Can you publish either your input costs or upgrade costs?
Show it to the public?
In society nowadays, naturally when it comes to
Sinopec, or the China National Petroleum Corporation
People have a feeling of mistrust
Do you feel this mistrust–
Many people don’t bother with rational discussion
If there is some tiny flaw, they will blow it up into something huge
It just makes matters worse
It's better to not say anything at all
Fourth Question: Can we raise the standard and force a fuel upgrade?
Many people will say why don’t we raise the standard a bit
and force improvement in the fuel quality?
If there were an interruption to the fuel supply
resulting in social instability
There would be turmoil in our society
Then would it be possible to fully open the market for finished petroleum products?
That would eliminate the possibility of interruptions to the fuel supply
If it wasn't done right, it could be a disaster
Not every Tom, Dick, and Harry can run a fuel company
Then he might think
why can only Sinopec and CNPC make money?
Everybody else can make money too
Yes, everybody can make money
So I agree with deepening reform and gradual opening up
If the government wants to decide
and push through this kind of reform
Then the government should go do some research first
and find out what kind of risks there might be
Fifth Question: Can [oil companies] take on more social responsibility?
Many people will say
Sinopec is already a Fortune 500 global company
It's just announced an income of 2 trillion RMB ($319 billion) last year
It's a large state-owned company
So, when it comes to environmental issues
why can't it take on more of its own social responsibility?
Sinopec is huge
Like a person
Very big
But it's all fat and no muscle
Petroleum companies all over the world
will try to protect the interests of their industry
That's the nature of a corporation
and it's not going to change
We wanted to know
in other countries, who sets the fuel standards?
This is our conclusion so far:
In Australia, Korea, Japan, Mexico, and Canada
Environmental agencies are basically in charge of setting the standards
Even in the European Union,
where it is decided by the European Standards Committee
they hear from industry associations
But there's never been a case when the petrochemical industry actually led the standards process
But why are fuel quality standards in China set by the oil industry?
Each country's choice is rooted in its history
In the 1960s, China was facing an extreme gasoline shortage
Buses on Chang'an Street, the busiest street in Beijing
had to carry a big bag of diesel fuel on the roof during operation
We were a long way from worrying about environmental standards for gasoline
At the time, the MEP didn't exist
so the Petrochemical Research Institute under the Ministry of Petroleum regulated fuel standards
In 1983 as part of institutional reforms
the Ministry of Petroleum was dissolved
and the Petrochemical Research Institute became a department of Sinopec
With that, the government ministry's role in regulating fuel standards
was handed over to a corporation
In the year 2005, the first Chinese Petrochemical Standards Committee was founded
and the oil industry naturally took on a leading role in the group
For the past ten years China has been faced with
soaring needs for both fuel quality and fuel quantity
China faces an unprecedented challenge
with pressing needs in both respects
As the Chinese economy develops further
environmental protection is receiving more attention
With the Chinese public calling for higher fuel standards
real changes have been made within the CPSC
Although members from the oil industries still make up over half of the committee
the number of members from outside the oil industry
has increased during the past two years
The committee has also set up a voting system
In the end, each country's standards for oil and gasoline quality
emerge from balancing the needs of the economy and the environment
Future changes to the CPSC will emerge from this balancing act
In China, in addition to the low oil standards
there is another problem that I could never have imagined before I started out
That is, half of the oil in China is completely unregulated
Out of the world’s top ten ports, seven are in China
Ocean-going cargo vessels cause so much pollution
that  within 400 meters of the coast
emissions from ships are equivalent to emissions from 500,000 trucks
So, in Shenzhen, 60% of the sulfur dioxide is from ships
Maybe you don’t live by a harbor, but you do live by a river
There are more than 200,000 boats like this in China
burning heavy oil of the lowest quality
How polluting can it get?
At some harbors, you can even pick up
grains of black carbon with your hand
Or maybe you live near an airport
When a plane takes off, that's one ton of kerosene burned
and when it lands, that's another ton
So at Baiyun Airport in Guangzhou
the daily emissions are equivalent to emissions from 600,000 taxis
Maybe you don’t live by a harbor, along a river, or near an airport
but you've certainly seen vehicles like this
These are construction vehicles
Once in Hebei province I saw one of these
and I thought something up ahead was on fire
When I overtook it on the road
I realized it was the source of that black smoke
Then we followed it into a village
The entrance of the village looked like this
(Sign: Diesel)
We saw a small room at the entrance with villagers playing mahjong and selling lottery tickets
They sold diesel and coal slurry, too
I had no idea where the diesel came from
I was with some officials from the MEP
and they suggested we should go investigate
So they bought a diesel can on the spot
and then went into the nearest privately-owned gas station
I was the last one out of the car and by the time I got out
the official's government ID had already been taken away by the owner
Station Owner: You… you guys… what do you want…
I’m… I’m not giving (your ID) back
Environment Officer: (We are from) the EPB enforcement.
EPB enforcement? What are you doing here?
This is a random inspection.
You… You want to inspect? Inspect what...?
No… What right do you EPB guys have to take samples for investigation…
EPB… do... do… do... do you even have...?
We're going to run a test.
No no no... You EPB guys have... what is this...
Yes, yes, of course we have the authority to monitor diesel quality
there is… the Technical Monitoring Authority…
Diesel Quality Monitoring Authority… governed by the (Oil) Union Authority
The EPB has [the authority] too
Environmental Protection… This is the first time I’ve heard of it, what does the EPB care?
Let me tell you… you… take… take… take the sample… take a prepared sample
Yes… there is this… Technical Monitoring Authority… there is this… that...
Yes… there's the “Air Pollution Prevention Act”
“Air Pollution Prevention Act?”
“The EPB has the authority and obligation…”
You… have the obligation… you have the obligation, but not the authority
When the owner finished that sentence
each of us was left speechless
All we could do was take our diesel can and leave
He'd put it so ruthlessly
From coal, to oil, and on down the list
We consume so much coal and oil
Our coal and oil quality is relatively low
We don't do enough to clean it
and when we emit, we don't regulate that enough either
All along, I have wanted to know why
until this gas station owner
Without even realizing it himself, in a single sentence
cut straight to the heart of the matter
Less than half of our coal is washed
There are no restrictions
There are no standards
There are no national regulations
Requirements for coal washing: none
What about the steel industry in Hebei?
It's reached the point where nothing can stop them
Polluting companies: unstoppable
The operators of this truck
have not been fined
No penalties have been applied in 14 years? No, never
Over-emitting vehicles: enforcement responsibility unclear, cannot be recalled
Over 90% are individuals from the petrochemical industry
I don’t think the environmental protection authorities understand
Petroleum standards: unregulatable
This is the conundrum of environmental protection
Now I don't dare open my mouth
I fear that people will notice I have no teeth
Environmental protection authorities have an obligation and the authority
You have an obligation, but not the authority
Petroleum product quality: no inspection authority
“Isn't that the conundrum of environmental protection?”
So one night there was an environmental protection professional
who sent me this photo
This is a photo taken in 1999
He graduated from university that year
He said he was motivated by a calling
So he went to work for the Environmental Protection Bureau
He wanted to make a difference
He said, “Sometimes, I feel like I'm nothing more than a mascot." (laughter)
So I tried to console him
I said, “Why do you think so?”
He said, “You are an investigative reporter
you must know this better than me”
2004 interview
(Suppose) you didn’t get the government approval for land use do you dare to build?
Ren Baoming - Legal representative, Hongta Coal Washing & Coking Factory
We wouldn't dare
Suppose you don’t get the approval from the Administration for Industry and Commerce
Or the approval from Taxation Bureau
Do you dare to build?
No, no
So why, when you don't have EPB approval, it's all fine?
We should have EPB approval
We ought to
Eventually, we will get it
Exactly
Did you know about these situations?
We have taken steps
Zeng Shumao - Bureau Chief, Environmental Protection Bureau of Xiaoyi City, Shanxi
On-site checking, inquiries and records
then impose a penalty
But the fact is he still went ahead and built, and even went into production
We finished the procedure that was required
We issued the Letter of Penalty that was required
There is nothing we can do if the enterprises do not stop
This is a kind of helplessness
Then what you've got here should be considered illegal construction
Oh well, it's hard to find factories that do not violate regulations
Zhang Xuguang - Mayor, Xiaoyi City, Shanxi
The government’s attitude toward coal coking
We are always cool-headed
after we took steps
Previous trends were stopped by us
They were stopped
If they stopped, why are there more than 30 projects still violating regulations?
As the Xiaoyi municipal government, our attitude is clear and firm
If your attitude is clear and firm
Then these unlawful projects should be
Not one should have started
Liu Xiangdong - Bureau Chief, Shanxi Provincial Environmental Protection Bureau
This cat, it's the local government's cat
Whether this cat can catch mice or not
and how many mice it can catch, is decided by the local government
It is not decided by the environmental protection authority
We walked for hundreds of meters along the coastline and saw the same black chemical silt
We could smell 4-5 different kinds of chemicals
The odor here is the kind of smell that stings your nose
What is that smell?
Chen Zhiming - Vice General Manager, Zhejiang Haizheng Pharmaceutical
My sense of smell may not be as sensitive as yours
You said that you cannot smell it
My sensitivity is not as good as yours (laughter)
One ton of steel
if you cut all the costs of environmental protection measures
you could save 100 RMB ($16) per ton
For one ton of coal, you could save 156 RMB ($25)
On one truck, if you avoid installing any environmental protection equipment you can save 20,000 RMB ($3,200)
If you avoid upgrading petroleum products by a single grade
you can save 50 billion RMB ($8 billion)
10 years ago
I asked what the smell in the air was
I received no answer
Now I know
It is the stink of money
In that interview I recorded years ago
the local secretary said to me:
“You absolutely must film my achievements in pollution management!”
So he made me film this clip
He was quite satisfied and said
Miss Chai, I demolished this smokestack especially for you! (laughter)
3 years later, I went there again
An even larger smokestack had been built in the same place (laughter)
Actually, environmental protection facilities were installed at the same time
But when I asked: "Have the facilities ever been used?"
The manager rubbed his hands together, and answered, "Yes… Soon, soon."
At that time the local secretary said to me:
“Everyone tells me, 'Environmental Protection, Environmental Protection...'
Let me ask you, who would dare slow down China's economic development?"
I am also keen to know the answer
So 10 years later, I visited a steel market in Hebei Province
When I went in it was quite empty
The raw steel was already rusting
hidden in the wild grass
Some of it had even become birds' nests
I asked this young steel salesman:
“How is your business?”
He replied: “Do you see any trucks coming to carry the steel?”
He said, “So many steel enterprises
all produce completely identical,
low–end products
They compete with each other only on the basis of quantity
At this point I'd rather be selling cabbages!”
When we produce one ton of steel
how many resources will we consume?
600 kilograms of coal
3 to 6 tons of water
And what pollutants will we emit?
1.53 kilograms of sulfur dioxide
1 kilogram of smoke and soot
And what is the profit for producing one ton of steel?
You can take a guess
How much?
RMB 1000 ($160)?
Not even enough to buy a pickled egg
One ton of stell, in 2014
was less than 2 RMB ($0.30)
What about when we burn one ton of coal?
How much pollution will we release?
1.53 kilograms of sulfur dioxide
3 to 9 kilograms of nitrogen dioxide
2 kilograms of carbon monoxide
9-11 kilograms of soot
Can you guess how much profit there is in one ton of coal?
Two pickled eggs?
You're still overestimating
You couldn't even afford a soda
Of our 36 different heavy industries
22 are in serious overproduction
Mr Cao Xianghong from Sinopec
said one thing that was very accurate:
“It's like a person who looks big
but it's all fat and no muscle.”
But these enterprises are still receiving  large subsidies
You can see here, between 2011 – 2013
the government has given these publicly traded steel companies
this many subsidies
In order to prevent one of the companies
from being taken off the stock exchange
the government subsidized it every other year
How much has it been subsidized?
Tens, thousands, ten thousands, billions...
2 billion RMB ($320 million)
Two years later, another 2 billion RMB
Another one of these companies which had already posted severe losses
hung a slogan in their office after receiving the subsidy
It reads: “With intense struggle and indomitable spirit,
we vow that our steel will be 100 RMB ($16) cheaper than XX Corporation's.”
That's why the Deputy Head of the Central Bank, Mr Liu Shiyu, has called these companies ‘zombie companies’
They are consuming huge amounts of financial resources
They are going to bring a huge amount of unforeseeable risk to our real economy
And these companies are still expanding, even now
Two days ago I received a letter from a little girl
She said to me, a coke plant near her home
is expanding and is going to demolish her family's house
Her dad refused to agree, and so he was beaten
She hoped I could help her
This is the same little girl I interviewed ten years ago
Little Wang Huiqing, who had never seen stars or white clouds
I asked her, “How is your health these days?”
She told me, “Auntie, I can't worry about my health now.
I just want my whole family to have a place to live.”
Thank goodness, when I gave her a call two days ago she said
the owner of the coke plant had just been taken away by the authorities (laughter)
But, as for these industries that are already considered to be excessively over-producing
in half of the provinces of China, they are still listed as ‘key industries’
in the 25th Five-Year Plan for economic development.
There is a simple underlying reason
If we urbanize and continue to develop we only need to increase urbanization by 1%
and all this excess supply could easily be consumed
Where there is housing development, there is demand for steel
Where there is road construction there will be cars
Right?
Mr Jiang from Tsinghua University told me
China's urban development is itself in a severe state of over-production
The situation is even worse than in industry
I didn't really believe it
because I feel like over the past 30 years
social changes in ordinary families such as mine
and improvement in general living standards
were all achieved thanks to urbanization
When I was young my little sister and I grew up in a traditional house
It had 300 years of history
It housed a dozen families
Later, our living conditions improved when we moved into housing provided by my mom’s work unit
The accommodation we were given was 12 square meters and housed five of us
When we slept at night we added another wooden plank
to the bed frame and put a chair underneath to hold it up
Then it became a double bed
This was the window of my bedroom
Wasn’t it nice?
In reality the bedroom was very small, there was no window
so I could only hang a picture on the wall
It represented the fantasies of a very young creative spirit
This picture was taken when I was about to go off to university
It shows what our county seat looked like
I used to walk to school along this road
This is what it was like back in those days
The changes in living standards my family saw over the years
proves that there are millions of households all in need of new construction
(Mr Jiang) asked me
“Hasn't it been a long time since you last went back to Shanxi?”
I said he was right
He said, “Why don’t you go back and have a look?”
This year I took my child to visit Shanxi
and took this video with my phone along the way
(Billboards advertising new apartment complexes)
I am happy to see some changes happening in my hometown
because people there need wealth, they need development
But what surprises me
is that I saw so many advertisements for real estate
within the city, and so many construction sites
But they're empty
I then asked a relative who has invested a lot in the local housing market
how many flats in this particular development have been sold
He said, only 20-30% have been sold
I asked, “How come they've sold so few?”
He hesitated and said:
“Since the real name policy was implemented
for government officials buying real estate, they haven’t been selling too well.”
(My relative) booked a local hotel for my family
I was so shocked when I arrived at the hotel gate
because it claims to be a “five-star hotel”
and I was booked into the “Presidential Suite”
I said, “No you don’t have to!”
He said, “Don’t worry
It only costs 200 RMB ($32 USD).” (laughter)
We drove our car into the parking lot
and it didn't have a single light, it was in total darkness
And then this middle-aged guy came along carrying a big flashlight
to light our way
He guided us into the hotel lobby
He then continued to use his big flashlight and led us down the corridors to our room
There were no lights in the entire hotel because nobody was staying in it
When I got back to Beijing
I brought this up with Professor Jiang
He told me, "The Shanxi that you witnessed is a microcosm of the rest of the country
In China we lose 80 traditional villages everyday
Houses have an average lifespan of a mere 30 years
There are more than 200 municipalities in China
184 of which have plans to become so-called “international metropolises”
We have a population of 1.3 billion
If we take into account the plans laid out by these municipalities
the population adds up to 3.4 billion
I came to Beijing carrying a small suitcase in 1998
I studied, worked and found, in this city
a sense of self-worth and belonging
If China hadn’t been urbanized, I’d still be back in Shanxi
Working a menial job that my parents found for me
Wearing blue overalls and spending the rest of my life using an abacus
Cities gave us our personal freedom and gave this nation three decades of prosperity
When there are 300-400 million people knocking on our cities’ doors
Urbanization becomes an unavoidable reality
and those who enter will bring unimaginable culture and wealth to this country
But if we don't change our current model of using capital
to fuel industry and urban development, what will be the consequences?
The Development Research Center of the State Council projects that in 15 years
our coal consumption will rise to 6 billion tons
while the number of vehicles will rise to 400 million
So what does that mean for us?
Professor Ni of Tsinghua University told me
“This means that even before we run out of natural resources,
we will have exhausted the capacity of our environment.”
This means that now in China
the pollution and traffic jams have just started
The needs of a country
Beijing
Nanjing, Xi'an, Chengdu
This photo was taken during the November 2014 APEC summit in Beijing
One morning, my husband took me to a place he often visited as a child
His father taught him ice skating, swimming, and fishing there
He said he loved to look at the texture of the ice in winter
It spread all the way to the corner turret of the Forbidden City
That was his memory of this elegant and ancient city
We looked at this scene together like a kid staring at the last piece of candy
You know that if you don't eat it, it will melt
But you also know that once you eat it, it will disappear
Now we felt that same sense of sweetness, anxiety and frustration
Wang Yuesi, Researcher, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Institute of Atmospheric Physics
I am a native of Beijing
When I was a child, the sky was blue and the clouds were white
The canal water was so clear we could see the bottom, we could catch fish with our hands
I also grew up here
I also remember what it was like when I was still a child
Standing on Chang'an Avenue, we could see all the way to the Western Hills
Having clean air is not an impossible task
It's completely achievable
It just depends how determined you are
I hope and believe that with dedication and hard work, we'll be able to keep our "APEC Blue"
When I got back, I asked the experts at the Chinese Academy of Sciences:
“Can you tell me, what would it take if we want to keep our APEC Blue?”
He said, we must cut emissions of sulfur dioxide by this much against 2013 levels
nitrogen oxide by this much
and PM2.5 by this much
In short, we would have to cut our pollutants by more than half in exchange for that blue sky
During the APEC Summit, China and the US issued a joint statement
China pledged that its carbon emissions will peak around 2030
and non-fossil energy sources will make up 20% of its energy infrastructure
Coal dominates our country's energy infrastructure
and is a source of both carbon emissions and smog
Reducing our carbon output and cutting toxic emissions go hand in hand
When I set the goal for 2030, I specified that should be our peak
It is actually a “reverse coercion system.”
So we will start moving on the green, low-carbon path
People may ask, to protect the environment, do we really have to sacrifice economic development?
That's a debt you have to settle
If you've acted wrongly before, you have to make up for it now
The real problem now becomes, how do we increase the employment rate and the average income?
Through transformation
What if during this transformation some workers in some industries lose their jobs?
Right now, China's energy-saving and environmental protection industries generate over 3.7 trillion RMB ($590 billion) a year
and employ around 39 million people
Don't forget, this is an industry too
But many people may wonder, will the Chinese government keep investing in economic growth?
If we want to maintain the rate of economic growth
the way to do it is precisely through green, low-carbon, recycling-focused programs
Consider the Great Smog of 1952 in London
or the smog crisis in Los Angeles
It took them six to seven decades to solve their problems
We can learn from their experience
We will get through this stage much more quickly than they did
Before, I was worried that
Beijing is still expanding
The number of cars is still increasing
Can pollution there really be reduced?
But this is Los Angeles
A place very similar to Beijing
It also has mountains on three sides
So it's hard for polluted air to disperse
That’s why LA has also experienced large-scale photochemical smog
You can look at 1950
These cans were sold in shops in Hollywood
They contained Los Angeles air
The can has a slogan on it
“Buy one for somebody you hate!”
You can imagine the feelings and resentment of those who lived in LA at the time
However, since 1970
The number of cars in LA is still increasing
It has actually tripled
But what about emissions?
They have decreased by 75%
How did they do it?
I went to LA to find out
We are now in the air over Santa Monica
You can see a layer of haze over there
That's the smog
We've often seen these tall buildings in Hollywood movies
But Los Angeles is not really a city of skyscrapers
All around those skyscrapers is a  flat expanse of one- and two-story buildings
This low-density urban development means you have to drive to get around in LA
Los Angeles’ sprawl is considered a classic case of failed urban planning
Its public transportation has not been developed or utilized to its fullest potential
This has caused an inevitable increase in car ownership
In a city of 1.7 million people, there are about 1.3 million cars
That's almost one car per person
In the whole of California
850 million trips are made every day
If you add up all the fuel
It's enough to travel to the moon and back 1,600 times
Over there is a beer brewery,
and over there are huge warehouses
This truck just came from the port of Long Beach
Take a look at this big Optimus Prime-looking guy
18 wheels
Over 20 meters long
Its quality is like a tank or armored vehicle
CARB estimates that
71% of the carcinogens in Southern California’s atmosphere come from diesel vehicles
So all diesel vehicles are required to install a diesel particulate filter (DPF)
This is a special type of filter
It's like putting a dust mask on your truck
It can filter out 99% of particles
This driver is from Mexico
He drives an old 2005 model truck
The law says he must install a DPF
But he hasn't installed one
Although his truck's emission level is within compliance
He will be still be fined $1,000 US dollars
Why didn't you install the DPF?
Not much money
He was waiting till the last minute
He makes around $4,000 a month
Now he has to pay a $1,000 ticket
That's a pretty high price
Sir, how many kids do you have?
Six
What if he still doesn’t install the DPF?
We'll keep ticketing him
If you still don’t comply,
We'll report you to the DMV
And not allow you to renew your license plates
If you can't renew your plates,
You can't drive, so you can't make money
To manage its pollution,
California had to enact the strictest standards for new motor vehicles
The Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) has the authority to inspect any new vehicle
It has the right to inspect any car in use with up to 12,000 miles on it
If it finds a factory has been violating the regulations
It will fine the car manufacturer $25,000 for each day since the vehicle left the factory
The EPA has the authority to require car manufacturers to recall all affected vehicles
Paul Jacobs, California Air Resource Board, Branch Chief
45% of the citizens want to comply and be good corporate citizens
Another 45% say, “Well, I don’t really want to, but I’m going to because I might get caught.”
And 10% say, “Catch me.”
“I'm gonna go 100 miles per hour in the left lane of the freeway, come and catch me.”
This court settlement particularly interests me
I only realized afterwards that
The vehicle that was fined was imported from China
It was because of environmental labeling fraud
But this time, once they were caught,
They were fined about 400 million RMB [64 million USD]
Two of the people in charge went to jail
Human nature is the same all around the world
In the US, you can also find people
who want to avoid punishment
or break the law
But you can control 90% of them if you strictly enforce the law
If you do not enforce the law
It will be like the Beijing Environmental Protection Bureau said
90% of vehicles will continue to commit environmental fraud
This year, the government is finally revising the “Atmospheric Pollution Prevention Law”
In the current draft,
it authorizes the Chinese environmental
protection agencies to fine or recall fraudulent vehicles
However, it won't take effect until September 2015 at the earliest
So before then
Every night,
at this very moment
millions of trucks are traveling across
and polluting China's vast landscape.
How many of these trucks have fake environmental credentials?
How many of these trucks are emitting particles and pollution?
This is what we're all enduring
So before our [original] “Atmospheric Pollution Prevention Law of the People's Republic of China” expires
Can we use it at least once?
Can we keep it from being viewed in our history like this?
Back then
When the U.S. wanted to establish strict standards
Once the U.S. car manufacturers heard this, they immediately made the effort and caught up
They constantly sued the EPA and did not want to change
Then,
some foreign car manufacturers said
“I can do it, I can comply!”
Once the U.S. car manufacturers heard this,
they immediately made the effort and caught up
But sadly,
by then they’d lost half of their market share
So I asked the officials in the U.S. environmental protection agencies
“Are you afraid that you're hurting your national auto industry?”
They said
“Environmental protection isn't a burden”
“It’s innovation”
Safeguarding the past is no way to promote innovation
The government's role  is to set standards
and then ensure fair competition in the market
Fair competition will win in the market
But in China, coal  accounts for 70% of our energy consumption
Within the energy infrastructure we have,
how can we reduce coal?
Let's look at this graph of how London did it. (Graph: London Air Pollution Density, µg/m3)
Many people argue that it took London 40 or 50 years to get its air pollution under control
So we have to wait just as long
But is that true?
Look at this
In just the first ten years after they started to manage pollution,
they reduced pollutants by 80%
That's a huge improvement
Let’s see how London accomplished this
When the Great London Smog of 1952  happened,
90% of England’s energy consumption was coal
In 1953,
the average density of black particles
was 10 times higher than the European Union's standard
The pressure to control the smog
was even greater than ours in China now
The English passed the “Clean Air Act” in 1956
At every colliery we used to run waterers on the surface
so the coal would’ve been washed
before being sold on to customers
To use ordinary coal or to to use it in an open grate would be illegal
And that by the way is the grate
Do you still use it?
We do sometimes
It's smokeless coal. And this is called “home fire.”
The government funded 70% of the cost of furnace renovations for citizens
But punishments were strict as well
Violation could result in a £100 fine
Or even jail time
Installation of any apparatus emitting smoke is strictly prohibited
Smoke wardens could inspect a shop and decide that it was selling illegal materials
This is the last cart of coals from a former coal mine in South Wales
It stopped on this track in 1983
In the 20 years following the Great Smog of 1952,
oil replaced more than 20% of coal
Natural gas replaced more than 30% of coal
Across the whole country's energy infrastructure,
coal dropped from 90% to 30% of total consumption
And heavy industry's share of the GDP also dropped 10%
Many coal mines and coal factories closed down
“And that's another London landmark gone.”
Millions of people used to work for the coal industry
How do you (miner) make money today?
Well, you have to find alternative employment
I’m not a rich man,
but at least I don’t have to worry about paying the bills
Mining to me, it was just a job
100 years ago
We had a million miners in the United Kingdom
We’ve just got tens of thousands now
But we've got more people in jobs than ever before in our history
If an industry is on its way out
There is another industry coming up
From 1960 to 1970
In the first ten years after England began controlling its air pollution
Not only did the economy not shrink,
GDP actually doubled
Ten years after that
The U.K had entered the age of oil and natural gas
Its economic power quadrupled
Once the U.K. used  cleaner energy sources,
oil and natural gas
Natural gas, in particular, replaced coal
They achieved blue skies and white clouds
The interesting thing is,
when we were in London looking for historical sources
on how coal contributed to air pollution
The best, most thorough,
and most authoritative source is this one
we could find was from a natural gas company
The name is simple
“Guilty Chimneys”
Natural gas quickly gained market share through competition
And replaced its opponent
The U.K. Secretary of State for Energy and Climate Change asked me
Do you know what London's economic level was at the beginning of the environmental reforms?
Their per capita GDP was the same as China's
Most importantly, the government shouldn't subsidize backward-thinking, polluting, unprofitable businesses
The government needs to give new,
innovative companies a fair chance to compete
If you do, they will surprise you
London’s success story tells us
China needs to leave the era of coal and enter the era of oil and natural gas
Only if we do that can we have cleaner air
Today in the world,
the share of natural gas in energy consumption is fairly high
Natural gas accounts for around 24% of the world’s energy consumption
because natural gas is a relatively clean energy source
How about China?
Just 5% of our energy comes from natural gas
Why is this number so low?
The standard answer I've heard since I was young is
It's because we're a country
with lots of coal
insufficient oil
and not enough natural gas
Is that really true?
It's true
But is it the whole story?
So I wrote to hang Dawei,
which is the Director of Mineral Resources Reserve Center in the Ministry of Land and Resources
He sent me a few numbers
How much of our potential natural gas reserves have actually been investigated?
22%
That means we have a lot of undiscovered natural gas under us
How about oil?
38%
For the resources we have verified
let’s say natural gas
We’ve found 900 billion cubic meters of natural gas
How much have we started to extract?
100 billion cubic meters
We have so many resources that we know are there
But we aren't taking advantage of them
Why is that?
Director Zhang Dawei sent me another reply
Very simple
Just a few numbers
For instance, the United States is the biggest natural gas producer
They have 6300 natural gas and oil companies
How many do we have?
70% of them are under one company
China National Petroleum Corporation
America has 160 natural gas pipeline companies
How many do we have?
70% of them are under one company
China National Petroleum Corporation
This is the answer he gave  me
If we open up this market
Our annual production of natural gas will double yearly
Our verified reserves will double yearly
Why have we been so slow to join the oil and gas age?
Why can’t we develop more natural gas?
The petrochemical industry is not open
and each sector of the industry
is basically a monopoly
and a monopoly can't innovate，
People outside of the industry can't get into it
It’s like an only child
with a toy that only he can play with
and he can play with it until he’s sick of it
or just throw it away
You just have to listen to what they tell you
The oil business is related to security
and if it’s not managed well the consequences can be serious
It depends on how you understand energy security
So, energy security is important
But, the new technology will be welcomed
I’m answer this question
As long as there is competition
Then the industry will try its hardest to innovate and change
You may be interested to know that
the company that controls electricity distribution
around this city, London, is Chinese-owned
Only if we bring down the price of energy
will there be competitiveness
I think,
by being open,
you share ideas,
you innovate, you get the best from the world
What is the key to controlling China’s smog?
Reform of energy systems and policies
In preparing for this documentary
I encountered for the first time
China’s energy problems
I only had a rough feeling for the problem
China’s reform and opening up
was not how I had originally imagined it
Like the process of a chick hatching from its egg
As soon as it hatches it is already complete
and alive
But it’s more like the process of a cicada shedding its skin
little by little
emerging from the skin it originally had
And energy is the last part that remains in the shell
It has always been considered
important to national security
and economic security, so it has not been treated as a commodity
It has been impossible for it to be exposed to real market forces
But the shell itself is also paying a price
This is a diagram showing a network of corruption
in the energy industry over the past two years
Energy is a sector with a high rate of corruption
The former director of the National Energy Administration, Liu Tienan
during his court hearing said that
in order to curb high rates of corruption
those rights that should have originally belonged to the market
should be given back to the market
So in June 2014
China’s national energy security strategy
stated that
energy is a commodity
We need to build an effective market structure
and market system
and we need to change the method of supervision that the government uses for energy
But as we’re waiting for the country
to build and improve
a massive energy system
what can we do?
Even the world's most powerful government
can't control pollution by itself
It needs to rely on
ordinary people like you and me
Our choices
and our determination
In 2003, when I was reporting on SARS
the most important lesson I learned was that
only with information disclosure
can there be a basis for public participation
Over the past three years
at the same time as providing
air quality forecasts
the government has also established
the largest
online monitoring network in the world
to monitor polluting enterprises
What we need to do is to use this data
and not waste the money spent on it
Let everyone see the data
Put it out in the sunlight
This is a mobile app
After downloading this software
you can see on your phone
in an area about 5 kilometers around you
which enterprises are emitting pollutants
These red circles
all show enterprises exceeding emissions standards
China’s 6000 key enterprises
discharge 65% of China’s waste emissions
You can submit a report to the environmental protection authorities
You can also share these details on Weibo
All these with traces of blue
are enterprises reported by the public that have promised to
take corrective actions by a certain time
Of course the shame is that
if the data for some places
Is not disclosed at all
what can we do?
So last year
I attended
a forum which was the first time local environmental legislation had been drafted with public participation
During this forum
I heard lots of disputes
The main dispute was around
whether to force key enterprises
to disclose information
In the end
Hebei Province published the first
regulations with public participation
The regulations required that
key polluting enterprises
must publicize their information
If they don’t publicize this information
citizens can file lawsuits
requiring the enterprises to pay a daily fine,
with the maximum being 100,000 RMB (16,000 USD) per day
But
who is going to file these lawsuits?
Only 1% of major environmental disputes
go to court in China
What’s the reason for such a small number?
Can you guess
before this year
how many NGOs in China
were allowed to file law suits?
None
This is because at the time
regulations in the Civil Procedural Law stated that
only “relevant organizations” can file lawsuits
As to who these relevant organizations are
no one knows
But from January 1st this year
the new Environmental Protection Law ruled that as long as an organization
has been carrying out environmental protection work for 5 or more years,
and has not broken the law in any way,
then they can qualify to file lawsuits
At present
some people from among the more than 700 environmental protection organizations
are already trying
The slogan proposed is
“Does the new environmental law have what it takes?
Our partners are testing it right now.”
As for ordinary people like us,
if you don't have time to
join an environmental protection organization
then what else can you do?
In cooperation with Friends of Nature we
have made a short animation
If you're going less than 5km
please take public transportation, ride a bike, or carpool
If you drive a car
Don't let the engine idle longer than 30 seconds
If you see a diesel vehicle belching black exhaust
Try calling 12369 to report it
Those “black tails” behind diesel trucks are full of PM2.5
they endanger public health.
If you see a restaurant releasing cooking smoke
Ask them to install a filtering system
Or leave them a negative review online
If you see dust blowing from uncovered piles at construction sites
If you think there might be a leak at a gas station
Try calling 12369
If you burn coal at home
As much as you can, try to avoid low-quality coal
Ask your mom to clean the kitchen range and hood
to keep the family healthy
And you can try taking pictures to help locate industrial pollution sources
supervise and report illegal activity
and tweet @ your local environmental bureau on Weibo
Check out the list of polluting manufacturers
and boycott their products
When our air quality laws are being written and revised
participate in the public commenting process
and make your voice heard
With  a little thought and care,
the smog will start to clear
Before,
When I walked by the uncovered construction site near my home
I usually just covered my nose and went on past
But now I know
At lease 15% of Beijing's PM2.5 pollution
comes from blowing dust
I decided I had to try
(Chai) We live nearby
(Chai) Why haven't you covered this dirt?
(Worker) Ask our boss
(Chai) Okay, where's your boss?
(Worker) Over there, go look over there
(Chai) You haven’t covered that huge dirt pile alongside the road
(Chai) As soon as the wind blows, the dust flies everywhere
(Boss) I know, I know, I know, I know
(Boss) It’s our fault
(Chai) So when are you going to cover it?
(Boss) Right away
(Chai) Okay
(Workers) Sorry, sorry.
The whole process took less than five minutes
Right before I left
The worker who told me where to find the boss
said,
“Do you know why he's afraid of you?”
He pointed at the mobile phone in my hand
He's afraid you'll expose him
In my building there is a restaurant downstairs
It serves meat pies
And every mealtime
Everywhere in the building
smells like smoke
Before, I didn’t think this is was a problem
Isn't every Chinese restaurant in the world like this?
But now I know
Beijing's food service industry creates
at least 6% of our PM2.5 pollution
And Beijing is home to
12% of the country's food service industry
For such a high-volume restaurant,
I used to think there was nothing to be done about it
until I went to London
and had a meal in a Chinese restaurant there.
I discovered there was no smoke smell there at all
Why?
The boss took me
up to the roof
And I saw this
which is called a soot purifier
The London city government required them to install it
And the city inspects it regularly
I thought it must be pretty high-tech
until I came back to Beijing
I found that not only does Beijing have them too
installing them is actually required
I called 12369 to make a report
And a week later
this item was delivered:
It all took less than half an hour
When I was taking this video clip
The restaurant boss came over
and said, “Thank you for your supervision as a resident here
We hope to see you in our restaurant in the future”
For the past year, our office lunches have been nothing but meat pies.
Sometimes when I walk by the neighborhood gas station
(here's a gas station downstairs)
I can smell the very strong scent of gasoline
But I thought that all gas stations worldwide are like this
until I went to the United States
I saw this thing on their gas pump nozzles
it's called “gasoline vapor recovery equipment”
I thought it was another high-tech thing
until I came back to Beijing and discovered
We've had these things for ages
and they've been required since 2008
but many people don't maintain them properly
so they release a lot of gasoline vapor
Then
I called 12369 again
If you look at it facing the sun,
there’s a lot coming out.
That means there’s definitely a problem.
It's not normal to smell this kind of odor when you are filling the tank.
Do you see these gasoline vapors?
There shouldn’t be gasoline here.
Right.
It’s wet here.
That means extra gasoline was spilled.
Right, fewer vapors went in.
Part of the gasoline vapors
escaped and went into the atmosphere.
We will stop using it and
it will be fixed immediately.
This requires that the gas station
must every year
conduct one compulsory inspection
of its gasoline vapor recovery equipment.
You can call 12369.
That’s our complaint hotline.
Will you definitely go check it out?
Absolutely.
We go 100% of the time.
They promised that they would come 100% of the time.
Will they really come?
I don’t know,
but by putting this sentence up here
We’ll see it as a kind of test
We can remember this number
If you don’t call that number
Then it will forever remain just a number
I’ve said that this wasn’t a happy year for me
I’ve felt like my life has been uncertain from day to day
That’s true
Whenever the pollution was bad I didn’t know where I’d be tomorrow
or where I’d be in the future
But still
The moment the restaurant owner
finished installing the smoke filtering device
I suddenly felt like my feet had landed on solid ground
It’s a hard feeling to describe
You know perfectly well
that the effect on improving air quality
is completely minuscule
but if one person
knows that because they did one small thing
the situation actually improved a little bit
that person can feel more at peace about things
So when you look back
at the war between people and pollution
you see this is how history is made
It’s tens of millions of ordinary people
One day they say “No.”
I’m not satisfied
I don’t want to wait
I’m not going to shirk the responsibility
I’m going to stand up and do something
I’m going to do it
Right now
Right at this moment
Right here
I am going to do it
Unless we bring these chemicals under better control
We’re certainly headed for disaster
This whole system
that we call home
People in Tokyo suffering from asthma are suing for compensation from
the car factory owners of Tokyo and Japan
for the harm caused by tailpipe emissions
We have the right to know, the right to participate,
the right to sue for damages
Everyone join together
Together we will make
our generation’s
choice to go green successful
If you don’t know how to fix it, please stop breaking it
You grown ups say you love us
Please, take action
And for me,
it is absolutely my responsibility to do whatever it takes
to protect my child
When the haze gets serious,
there is at least one thing we can do.
That is to protect yourself
and your loved ones.
When I drew this little bear on paper,
I was reminded of,
when my daughter got sick,
all my fear of losing her
and all my hope of protecting her.
I wish that all other mothers in this world
would not have to feel the same.
Now, she has grown up,
healthy and recovered,
sturdy and lively,
and as chubby as before.
She is particularly fond of the nature and the small animals in it,
but many times I cannot take her outdoor.
So in her own little pot,
she has been raising a snail.
When she wakes up every morning,
she runs to the pot and gives a puff to the snail,
hoping to help it grow up.
She is so much in love with this world.
Tens of thousands of mothers are being pregnant with
or giving birth to their children,
to whom these rivers,
skies
and lands
should belong.
We have no right to consume
without controlling.
We have no right to complain
without constructing.
We are responsible to prove to them
that a world lit by energy
can meanwhile be clean and beautiful.
Every time I look into the night sky,
seeing this planet rotating lonely,
I sense a kind of
indescribable attachment and warmth.
Someday in the future,
I’ll leave this world,
but my child will continue to live in it,
so I’ll still be involved.
And so I stare at it,
just like I stare at you.
And so I protect it,
as much as I protect you.